<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Silent, alone, no one escorting us,</l>
		<l>we made our way-one went before, one after-</l>
		<l>as Friars Minor when they walk together.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The present fracas made me think of Aesop-</l>
		<l>that fable where he tells about the mouse</l>
		<l>and frog; for &quot;near&quot; and &quot;nigh&quot; are not more close</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>than are that fable and this incident,</l>
		<l>if you compare with care how each begins</l>
		<l>and then compare the endings that they share.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And even as one thought springs from another,</l>
		<l>so out of that was still another born,</l>
		<l>which made the fear I felt before redouble.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I thought: &quot;Because of us, they have been mocked,</l>
		<l>and this inflicted so much hurt and scorn</l>
		<l>that I am sure they feel deep indignation.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If anger&apos;s to be added to their malice,</l>
		<l>they&apos;ll hunt us down with more ferocity</l>
		<l>than any hound whose teeth have trapped a hare.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I could already feel my hair curl up</l>
		<l>from fear, and I looked back attentively,</l>
		<l>while saying: &quot;Master, if you don&apos;t conceal</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>yourself and me at once-they terrify me,</l>
		<l>those Malebranche; they are after us;</l>
		<l>I so imagine them, I hear them now.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;Were I a leaded mirror,</l>
		<l>I could not gather in your outer image</l>
		<l>more quickly than I have received your inner.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For even now your thoughts have joined my own;</l>
		<l>in both our acts and aspects we are kin-</l>
		<l>with both our minds I&apos;ve come to one decision.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If that right bank is not extremely steep,</l>
		<l>we can descend into the other moat</l>
		<l>and so escape from the imagined chase.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He&apos;d hardly finished telling me his plan</l>
		<l>when I saw them approach with outstretched wings,</l>
		<l>not too far off, and keen on taking us.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide snatched me up instantly, just as</l>
		<l>the mother who is wakened by a roar</l>
		<l>and catches sight of blazing flames beside her,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>will lift her son and run without a stop-</l>
		<l>she cares more for the child than for herself-</l>
		<l>not pausing even to throw on a shift;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and down the hard embankment&apos;s edge-his back</l>
		<l>lay flat along the sloping rock that closes</l>
		<l>one side of the adjacent moat-he slid.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No water ever ran so fast along</l>
		<l>a sluice to turn the wheels of a land mill,</l>
		<l>not even when its flow approached the paddles,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as did my master race down that embankment</l>
		<l>while bearing me with him upon his chest,</l>
		<l>just like a son, and not like a companion.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His feet had scarcely reached the bed that lies</l>
		<l>along the deep below, than those ten demons</l>
		<l>were on the edge above us; but there was</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>nothing to fear; for that High Providence</l>
		<l>that willed them ministers of the fifth ditch,</l>
		<l>denies to all of them the power to leave it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Below that point we found a painted people,</l>
		<l>who moved about with lagging steps, in circles,</l>
		<l>weeping, with features tired and defeated.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And they were dressed in cloaks with cowls so low</l>
		<l>they fell before their eyes, of that same cut</l>
		<l>that&apos;s used to make the clothes for Cluny&apos;s monks.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Outside, these cloaks were gilded and they dazzled</l>
		<l>but inside they were all of lead, so heavy</l>
		<l>that Frederick&apos;s capes were straw compared to them</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A tiring mantle for eternity!</l>
		<l>We turned again, as always, to the left,</l>
		<l>along with them, intent on their sad weeping;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but with their weights that weary people paced</l>
		<l>so slowly that we found ourselves among</l>
		<l>new company each time we took a step.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At which I told my guide: &quot;Please try to find</l>
		<l>someone whose name or deed I recognize;</l>
		<l>and while we walk, be watchful with your eyes.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And one who&apos;d taken in my Tuscan speech</l>
		<l>cried out behind us: &quot;Stay your steps, o you</l>
		<l>who hurry so along this darkened air!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Perhaps you&apos;ll have from me that which you seek.&quot;</l>
		<l>At which my guide turned to me, saying: &quot;Wait,</l>
		<l>and then continue, following his pace.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I stopped, and I saw two whose faces showed</l>
		<l>their minds were keen to be with me; but both</l>
		<l>their load and the tight path forced them to slow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When they came up, they looked askance at me</l>
		<l>a long while, and they uttered not a word</l>
		<l>until they turned to one another, saying:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The throbbing of his throat makes this one seem</l>
		<l>alive; and if they&apos;re dead, what privilege</l>
		<l>lets them appear without the heavy mantle?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then they addressed me: &quot;Tuscan, you who come</l>
		<l>to this assembly of sad hypocrites,</l>
		<l>do not disdain to tell us who you are.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I answered: &quot;Where the lovely Arno flows,</l>
		<l>there I was born and raised, in the great city;</l>
		<l>I&apos;m with the body I have always had.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But who are you, upon whose cheeks I see</l>
		<l>such tears distilled by grief? And let me know</l>
		<l>what punishment it is that glitters so.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And one of them replied: &quot;The yellow cloaks</l>
		<l>are of a lead so thick, their heaviness</l>
		<l>makes us, the balances beneath them, creak.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We both were Jovial Friars, and Bolognese;</l>
		<l>my name was Catalano, Loderingo</l>
		<l>was his, and we were chosen by your city</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>together, for the post that&apos;s usually</l>
		<l>one man&apos;s, to keep the peace; and what we were</l>
		<l>is still to be observed around Gardingo.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I then began, &quot;O Friars, your misdeeds . . . &quot;</l>
		<l>but said no more, because my eyes had caught</l>
		<l>one crucified by three stakes on the ground.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When he saw me, that sinner writhed all over,</l>
		<l>and he breathed hard into his beard with sighs;</l>
		<l>observing that, Fra Catalano said</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to me: &quot;That one impaled there, whom you see,</l>
		<l>counseled the Pharisees that it was prudent</l>
		<l>to let one man-and not one nation-suffer.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Naked, he has been stretched across the path,</l>
		<l>as you can see, and he must feel the weight</l>
		<l>of anyone who passes over him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Like torment, in this ditch, afflicts both his</l>
		<l>father-in-law and others in that council,</l>
		<l>which for the Jews has seeded so much evil.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I saw Virgil stand amazed above</l>
		<l>that one who lay stretched out upon a cross</l>
		<l>so squalidly in his eternal exile.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he addressed the friar in this way:</l>
		<l>&quot;If it does not displease you-if you may-</l>
		<l>tell us if there&apos;s some passage on the right</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that would allow the two of us to leave</l>
		<l>without our having to compel black angels</l>
		<l>to travel to this deep, to get us out.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He answered: &quot;Closer than you hope, you&apos;ll find</l>
		<l>a rocky ridge that stretches from the great</l>
		<l>round wall and crosses all the savage valleys,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>except that here it&apos;s broken-not a bridge.</l>
		<l>But where its ruins slope along the bank</l>
		<l>and heap up at the bottom, you can climb.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My leader stood a while with his head bent,</l>
		<l>then said: &quot;He who hooks sinners over there</l>
		<l>gave us a false account of this affair.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At which the Friar: &quot;In Bologna, I</l>
		<l>once heard about the devil&apos;s many vices-</l>
		<l>they said he was a liar and father of lies.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And then my guide moved on with giant strides,</l>
		<l>somewhat disturbed, with anger in his eyes;</l>
		<l>at this I left those overburdened spirits,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>while following the prints of his dear feet.</l>
	</p>
</page>
