<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Along the upper rim of a high bank</l>
		<l>formed by a ring of massive broken boulders,</l>
		<l>we came above a crowd more cruelly pent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And here, because of the outrageous stench</l>
		<l>thrown up in excess by that deep abyss,</l>
		<l>we drew back till we were behind the lid</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of a great tomb, on which I made out this,</l>
		<l>inscribed: &quot;I hold Pope Anastasius,</l>
		<l>enticed to leave the true path by Photinus.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;It would be better to delay descent</l>
		<l>so that our senses may grow somewhat used</l>
		<l>to this foul stench; and then we can ignore it.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So said my master, and I answered him:</l>
		<l>&quot;Do find some compensation, lest this time</l>
		<l>be lost.&quot; And he: &quot;You see, I&apos;ve thought of that.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;My son, within this ring of broken rocks,&quot;</l>
		<l>he then began, &quot;there are three smaller circles;</l>
		<l>like those that you are leaving, they range down.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those circles are all full of cursed spirits;</l>
		<l>so that your seeing of them may suffice,</l>
		<l>learn now the how and why of their confinement.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Of every malice that earns hate in Heaven,</l>
		<l>injustice is the end; and each such end</l>
		<l>by force or fraud brings harm to other men.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>However, fraud is man&apos;s peculiar vice;</l>
		<l>God finds it more displeasing-and therefore,</l>
		<l>the fraudulent are lower, suffering more.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The violent take all of the first circle;</l>
		<l>but since one uses force against three persons,</l>
		<l>that circle&apos;s built of three divided rings.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To God and to one&apos;s self and to one&apos;s neighbor-</l>
		<l>I mean, to them or what is theirs-one can</l>
		<l>do violence, as you shall now hear clearly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Violent death and painful wounds may be</l>
		<l>inflicted on one&apos;s neighbor; his possessions</l>
		<l>may suffer ruin, fire, and extortion;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>thus, murderers and those who strike in malice,</l>
		<l>as well as plunderers and robbers-these,</l>
		<l>in separated ranks, the first ring racks.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A man can set violent hands against</l>
		<l>himself or his belongings; so within</l>
		<l>the second ring repents, though uselessly,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>whoever would deny himself your world,</l>
		<l>gambling away, wasting his patrimony,</l>
		<l>and weeping where he should instead be happy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One can be violent against the Godhead,</l>
		<l>one&apos;s heart denying and blaspheming Him</l>
		<l>and scorning nature and the good in her;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, with its sign, the smallest ring has sealed</l>
		<l>both Sodom and Cahors and all of those</l>
		<l>who speak in passionate contempt of God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now fraud, that eats away at every conscience,</l>
		<l>is practiced by a man against another</l>
		<l>who trusts in him, or one who has no trust.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This latter way seems only to cut off</l>
		<l>the bond of love that nature forges; thus,</l>
		<l>nestled within the second circle are:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>hypocrisy and flattery, sorcerers,</l>
		<l>and falsifiers, simony, and theft,</l>
		<l>and barrators and panders and like trash.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But in the former way of fraud, not only</l>
		<l>the love that nature forges is forgotten,</l>
		<l>but added love that builds a special trust;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>thus, in the tightest circle, where there is</l>
		<l>the universe&apos;s center, seat of Dis,</l>
		<l>all traitors are consumed eternally.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Master, your reasoning is clear indeed,&quot;</l>
		<l>I said; &quot;it has made plain for me the nature</l>
		<l>of this pit and the population in it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But tell me: those the dense marsh holds, or those</l>
		<l>driven before the wind, or those on whom</l>
		<l>rain falls, or those who clash with such harsh ton</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>why are they not all punished in the city</l>
		<l>of flaming red if God is angry with them?</l>
		<l>And if He&apos;s not, why then are they tormented?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And then to me, &quot;Why does your reason wander</l>
		<l>so far from its accustomed course?&quot; he said.</l>
		<l>&quot;Or of what other things are you now thinking?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Have you forgotten, then, the words with which</l>
		<l>your Ethics treats of those three dispositions</l>
		<l>that strike at Heaven&apos;s will: incontinence</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and malice and mad bestiality?</l>
		<l>And how the fault that is the least condemned</l>
		<l>and least offends God is incontinence?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If you consider carefully this judgment</l>
		<l>and call to mind the souls of upper Hell,</l>
		<l>who bear their penalties outside this city,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you&apos;ll see why they have been set off from these</l>
		<l>unrighteous ones, and why, when heaven&apos;s vengeance</l>
		<l>hammers at them, it carries lesser anger.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O sun that heals all sight that is perplexed,</l>
		<l>when I ask you, your answer so contents</l>
		<l>that doubting pleases me as much as knowing.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Go back a little to that point,&quot; I said,</l>
		<l>&quot;where you told me that usury offends</l>
		<l>divine goodness; unravel now that knot.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Philosophy, for one who understands,</l>
		<l>points out, and not in just one place,&quot; he said,</l>
		<l>&quot;how nature follows-as she takes her course-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the Divine Intellect and Divine Art;</l>
		<l>and if you read your Physics carefully,</l>
		<l>not many pages from the start, you&apos;ll see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that when it can, your art would follow nature,</l>
		<l>just as a pupil imitates his master;</l>
		<l>so that your art is almost God&apos;s grandchild.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From these two, art and nature, it is fitting,</l>
		<l>if you recall how Genesis begins,</l>
		<l>for men to make their way, to gain their living;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and since the usurer prefers another</l>
		<l>pathway, he scorns both nature in herself</l>
		<l>and art, her follower; his hope is elsewhere.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But follow me, for it is time to move;</l>
		<l>the Fishes glitter now on the horizon</l>
		<l>all the Wain is spread out over Caurus;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>only beyond, can one climb down the cliff.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
