<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<lg>
		<l>When I had journeyed half of our life&apos;s way,</l>
		<l>I found myself within a shadowed forest,</l>
		<l>for I had lost the path that does not stray.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>Ah, it is hard to speak of what it was,</l>
		<l>that savage forest, dense and difficult,</l>
		<l>which even in recall renews my fear:</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>so bitter-death is hardly more severe!</l>
		<l>But to retell the good discovered there,</l>
		<l>I&apos;ll also tell the other things I saw.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>I cannot clearly say how I had entered</l>
		<l>the wood; I was so full of sleep just at</l>
		<l>the point where I abandoned the true path.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>But when I&apos;d reached the bottom of a hill-</l>
		<l>it rose along the boundary of the valley</l>
		<l>that had harassed my heart with so much fear-</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>I looked on high and saw its shoulders clothed</l>
		<l>already by the rays of that same planet</l>
		<l>which serves to lead men straight along all roads.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>At this my fear was somewhat quieted;</l>
		<l>for through the night of sorrow I had spent,</l>
		<l>the lake within my heart felt terror present.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>And just as he who, with exhausted breath,</l>
		<l>having escaped from sea to shore, turns back</l>
		<l>to watch the dangerous waters he has quit,</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>so did my spirit, still a fugitive,</l>
		<l>turn back to look intently at the pass</l>
		<l>that never has let any man survive.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>I let my tired body rest awhile.</l>
		<l>Moving again, I tried the lonely slope-</l>
		<l>my firm foot always was the one below.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>And almost where the hillside starts to rise-</l>
		<l>look there!-a leopard, very quick and lithe,</l>
		<l>a leopard covered with a spotted hide.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>He did not disappear from sight, but stayed;</l>
		<l>indeed, he so impeded my ascent</l>
		<l>that I had often to turn back again.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>The time was the beginning of the morning;</l>
		<l>the sun was rising now in fellowship</l>
		<l>with the same stars that had escorted it</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>when Divine Love first moved those things of beaut</l>
		<l>so that the hour and the gentle season</l>
		<l>gave me good cause for hopefulness on seeing</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>that beast before me with his speckled skin;</l>
		<l>but hope was hardly able to prevent</l>
		<l>the fear I felt when I beheld a lion.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>His head held high and ravenous with hunger-</l>
		<l>even the air around him seemed to shudder-</l>
		<l>this lion seemed to make his way against me.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>And then a she-wolf showed herself; she seemed</l>
		<l>to carry every craving in her leanness;</l>
		<l>she had already brought despair to many.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>The very sight of her so weighted me</l>
		<l>with fearfulness that I abandoned hope</l>
		<l>of ever climbing up that mountain slope.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>Even as he who glories while he gains</l>
		<l>will, when the time has come to tally loss,</l>
		<l>lament with every thought and turn despondent,</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>so was I when I faced that restless beast</l>
		<l>which, even as she stalked me, step by step</l>
		<l>had thrust me back to where the sun is speechless.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>While I retreated down to lower ground,</l>
		<l>before my eyes there suddenly appeared</l>
		<l>one who seemed faint because of the long silence.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>When I saw him in that vast wilderness,</l>
		<l>&quot;Have pity on me,&quot; were the words I cried,</l>
		<l>&quot;whatever you may be-a shade, a man.&quot;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>He answered me: &quot;Not man; I once was man.</l>
		<l>Both of my parents came from Lombardy,</l>
		<l>and both claimed Mantua as native city.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>And I was born, though late, sub Julio,</l>
		<l>and lived in Rome under the good Augustus-</l>
		<l>the season of the false and lying gods.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>I was a poet, and I sang the righteous</l>
		<l>son of Anchises who had come from Troy</l>
		<l>when flames destroyed the pride of Ilium.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>But why do you return to wretchedness?</l>
		<l>Why not climb up the mountain of delight,</l>
		<l>the origin and cause of every joy?&quot;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>&quot;And are you then that Virgil, you the fountain</l>
		<l>that freely pours so rich a stream of speech?&quot;</l>
		<l>I answered him with shame upon my brow.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>&quot;O light and honor of all other poets,</l>
		<l>may my long study and the intense love</l>
		<l>that made me search your volume serve me now.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>You are my master and my author, you-</l>
		<l>the only one from whom my writing drew</l>
		<l>the noble style for which I have been honored.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>You see the beast that made me turn aside;</l>
		<l>help me, o famous sage, to stand against her,</l>
		<l>for she has made my blood and pulses shudder,&quot;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>&quot;It is another path that you must take,&quot;</l>
		<l>he answered when he saw my tearfulness,</l>
		<l>&quot;if you would leave this savage wilderness;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>the beast that is the cause of your outcry</l>
		<l>allows no man to pass along her track,</l>
		<l>but blocks him even to the point of death;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>her nature is so squalid, so malicious</l>
		<l>that she can never sate her greedy will;</l>
		<l>when she has fed, she&apos;s hungrier than ever.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>She mates with many living souls and shall</l>
		<l>yet mate with many more, until the Greyhound</l>
		<l>arrives, inflicting painful death on her.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>That Hound will never feed on land or pewter,</l>
		<l>but find his fare in wisdom, love, and virtue;</l>
		<l>his place of birth shall be between two felts.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>He will restore low-lying Italy for which</l>
		<l>the maid Camilla died of wounds,</l>
		<l>and Nisus, Turnus, and Euryalus.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>And he will hunt that beast through every city</l>
		<l>until he thrusts her back again to Hell,</l>
		<l>for which she was first sent above by envy.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>Therefore, I think and judge it best for you</l>
		<l>to follow me, and I shall guide you, taking</l>
		<l>you from this place through an eternal place,</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>where you shall hear the howls of desperation</l>
		<l>and see the ancient spirits in their pain,</l>
		<l>as each of them laments his second death;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>and you shall see those souls who are content</l>
		<l>within the fire, for they hope to reach-</l>
		<l>whenever that may be-the blessed people.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>If you would then ascend as high as these,</l>
		<l>a soul more worthy than I am will guide you;</l>
		<l>I&apos;ll leave you in her care when I depart,</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>because that Emperor who reigns above,</l>
		<l>since I have been rebellious to His law,</l>
		<l>will not allow me entry to His city.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>He governs everywhere, but rules from there;</l>
		<l>there is His city, His high capital:</l>
		<l>o happy those He chooses to be there!&quot;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>And I replied: &quot;O poet-by that God</l>
		<l>whom you had never come to know-I beg you,</l>
		<l>that I may flee this evil and worse evils,</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>to lead me to the place of which you spoke,</l>
		<l>that I may see the gateway of Saint Peter</l>
		<l>and those whom you describe as sorrowful.&quot;</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>
		<l>Then he set out, and I moved on behind him.</l>
	</lg>
</page>