<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>That sinner raised his mouth from his fierce meal,</l>
		<l>then used the head that he had ripped apart</l>
		<l>in back: he wiped his lips upon its hair.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he began: &quot;You want me to renew</l>
		<l>despairing pain that presses at my heart</l>
		<l>even as I think back, before I speak.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But if my words are seed from which the fruit</l>
		<l>is infamy for this betrayer whom</l>
		<l>I gnaw, you&apos;ll see me speak and weep at once.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I don&apos;t know who you are or in what way</l>
		<l>you&apos;ve come down here; and yet you surely seem-</l>
		<l>from what I hear-to be a Florentine.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You are to know I was Count Ugolino,</l>
		<l>and this one here, Archbishop Ruggieri;</l>
		<l>and now I&apos;ll tell you why I am his neighbor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There is no need to tell you that, because</l>
		<l>of his malicious tricks, I first was taken</l>
		<l>and then was killed-since I had trusted him;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>however, that which you cannot have heard-</l>
		<l>that is, the cruel death devised for me-</l>
		<l>you now shall hear and know if he has wronged me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A narrow window in the Eagles&apos; Tower,</l>
		<l>which now, through me, is called the Hunger Tower,</l>
		<l>a cage in which still others will be locked,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>had, through its opening, already showed me</l>
		<l>several moons, when I dreamed that bad dream</l>
		<l>which rent the curtain of the future for me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This man appeared to me as lord and master;</l>
		<l>he hunted down the wolf and its young whelps</l>
		<l>upon the mountain that prevents the Pisans</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>from seeing Lucca; and with lean and keen</l>
		<l>and practiced hounds, he&apos;d sent up front, before him</l>
		<l>Gualandi and Sismondi and Lanfranchi.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But after a brief course, it seemed to me</l>
		<l>that both the father and the sons were weary;</l>
		<l>I seemed to see their flanks torn by sharp fangs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When I awoke at daybreak, I could hear</l>
		<l>my sons, who were together with me there,</l>
		<l>weeping within their sleep, asking for bread.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You would be cruel indeed if, thinking what</l>
		<l>my heart foresaw, you don&apos;t already grieve;</l>
		<l>and if you don&apos;t weep now, when would you weep?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They were awake by now; the hour drew near</l>
		<l>at which our food was usually brought,</l>
		<l>and each, because of what he&apos;d dreamed, was anxious</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>below, I heard them nailing up the door</l>
		<l>of that appalling tower; without a word,</l>
		<l>I looked into the faces of my sons.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I did not weep; within, I turned to stone.</l>
		<l>They wept; and my poor little Anselm said:</l>
		<l>&apos;Father, you look so . . . What is wrong with you?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At that I shed no tears and-all day long</l>
		<l>and through the night that followed-did not answer</l>
		<l>until another sun had touched the world.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As soon as a thin ray had made its way</l>
		<l>into that sorry prison, and I saw,</l>
		<l>reflected in four faces, my own gaze,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>out of my grief, I bit at both my hands;</l>
		<l>and they, who thought I&apos;d done that out of hunger,</l>
		<l>immediately rose and told me: &apos;Father,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>it would be far less painful for us if</l>
		<l>you ate of us; for you clothed us in this</l>
		<l>sad flesh-it is for you to strip it off.&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I grew calm, to keep them from more sadness;</l>
		<l>through that day and the next, we all were silent;</l>
		<l>O hard earth, why did you not open up?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But after we had reached the fourth day, Gaddo,</l>
		<l>throwing himself, outstretched, down at my feet,</l>
		<l>implored me: &apos;Father, why do you not help me?&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there he died; and just as you see me,</l>
		<l>I saw the other three fall one by one</l>
		<l>between the fifth day and the sixth; at which,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>now blind, I started groping over each;</l>
		<l>and after they were dead, I called them for</l>
		<l>two days; then fasting had more force than grief.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When he had spoken this, with eyes awry,</l>
		<l>again he gripped the sad skull in his teeth,</l>
		<l>which, like a dog&apos;s, were strong down to the bone.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Ah, Pisa, you the scandal of the peoples</l>
		<l>of that fair land where si is heard, because</l>
		<l>your neighbors are so slow to punish you,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>may, then, Caprara and Gorgona move</l>
		<l>and build a hedge across the Arno&apos;s mouth,</l>
		<l>so that it may drown every soul in you!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For if Count Ugolino was reputed</l>
		<l>to have betrayed your fortresses, there was</l>
		<l>no need to have his sons endure such torment.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O Thebes renewed, their years were innocent</l>
		<l>and young-Brigata, Uguiccione, and</l>
		<l>the other two my song has named above!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We passed beyond, where frozen water wraps-</l>
		<l>a rugged covering-still other sinners,</l>
		<l>who were not bent, but flat upon their backs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Their very weeping there won&apos;t let them weep,</l>
		<l>and grief that finds a barrier in their eyes</l>
		<l>turns inward to increase their agony;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>because their first tears freeze into a cluster,</l>
		<l>and, like a crystal visor, fill up all</l>
		<l>the hollow that is underneath the eyebrow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And though, because of cold, my every sense</l>
		<l>had left its dwelling in my face, just as</l>
		<l>a callus has no feeling, nonetheless,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I seemed to feel some wind now, and I said:</l>
		<l>&quot;My master, who has set this gust in motion?</l>
		<l>For isn&apos;t every vapor quenched down here?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;You soon shall be where your</l>
		<l>own eye will answer that, when you shall see</l>
		<l>the reason why this wind blasts from above.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And one of those sad sinners in the cold</l>
		<l>crust, cried to us: &quot;O souls who are so cruel</l>
		<l>that this last place has been assigned to you,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>take off the hard veils from my face so that</l>
		<l>I can release the suffering that fills</l>
		<l>my heart before lament freezes again.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To which I answered: &quot;If you&apos;d have me help you,</l>
		<l>then tell me who you are; if I don&apos;t free you,</l>
		<l>may I go to the bottom of the ice.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He answered then: &quot;I am Fra Alberigo,</l>
		<l>the one who tended fruits in a bad garden,</l>
		<l>and here my figs have been repaid with dates.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;But then,&quot; I said, &quot;are you already dead?&quot;</l>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;I have no knowledge of</l>
		<l>my body&apos;s fate within the world above.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For Ptolomea has this privilege:</l>
		<l>quite frequently the soul falls here before</l>
		<l>it has been thrust away by Atropos.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And that you may with much more willingness</l>
		<l>scrape these glazed tears from off my face, know this:</l>
		<l>as soon as any soul becomes a traitor,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as I was, then a demon takes its body</l>
		<l>away- and keeps that body in his power</l>
		<l>until its years have run their course completely.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The soul falls headlong, down into this cistern;</l>
		<l>and up above, perhaps, there still appears</l>
		<l>the body of the shade that winters here</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>behind me; you must know him, if you&apos;ve just</l>
		<l>come down; he is Ser Branca Doria;</l>
		<l>for many years he has been thus pent up.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I said to him: &quot;I think that you deceive me,</l>
		<l>for Branca Doria is not yet dead;</l>
		<l>he eats and drinks and sleeps and puts on clothes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;There in the Malebranche&apos;s ditch above,</l>
		<l>where sticky pitch boils up, Michele Zanche</l>
		<l>had still not come,&quot; he said to me, &quot;when this one</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>together with a kinsman, who had done</l>
		<l>the treachery together with him-left</l>
		<l>a devil in his stead inside his body.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But now reach out your hand; open my eyes.&quot;</l>
		<l>And yet I did not open them for him;</l>
		<l>and it was courtesy to show him rudeness.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Ah, Genoese, a people strange to every</l>
		<l>constraint of custom, full of all corruption,</l>
		<l>why have you not been driven from the world?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For with the foulest spirit of Romagna,</l>
		<l>I found one of you such that, for his acts,</l>
		<l>in soul he bathes already in Cocytus</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and up above appears alive, in body.</l>
	</p>
</page>
