<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The day was now departing; the dark air</l>
		<l>released the living beings of the earth</l>
		<l>from work and weariness; and I myself</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>alone prepared to undergo the battle</l>
		<l>both of the journeying and of the pity,</l>
		<l>which memory, mistaking not, shall show.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O Muses, o high genius, help me now;</l>
		<l>o memory that set down what I saw,</l>
		<l>here shall your excellence reveal itself!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I started: &quot;Poet, you who are my guide,</l>
		<l>see if the force in me is strong enough</l>
		<l>before you let me face that rugged pass.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You say that he who fathered Sylvius,</l>
		<l>while he was still corruptible, had journeyed</l>
		<l>into the deathless world with his live body.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For, if the Enemy of every evil</l>
		<l>was courteous to him, considering</l>
		<l>all he would cause and who and what he was,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that does not seem incomprehensible,</l>
		<l>since in the empyrean heaven he was chosen</l>
		<l>to father honored Rome and her empire;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and if the truth be told, Rome and her realm</l>
		<l>were destined to become the sacred place,</l>
		<l>the seat of the successor of great Peter.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And through the journey you ascribe to him,</l>
		<l>he came to learn of things that were to bring</l>
		<l>his victory and, too, the papal mantle.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Later the Chosen Vessel travelled there,</l>
		<l>to bring us back assurance of that faith</l>
		<l>with which the way to our salvation starts.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But why should I go there? Who sanctions it?</l>
		<l>For I am not Aeneas, am not Paul;</l>
		<l>nor I nor others think myself so worthy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, if I consent to start this journey,</l>
		<l>I fear my venture may be wild and empty.</l>
		<l>You&apos;re wise; you know far more than what I say.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as he who unwills what he wills</l>
		<l>and shifts what he intends to seek new ends</l>
		<l>so that he&apos;s drawn from what he had begun,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so was I in the midst of that dark land,</l>
		<l>because, with all my thinking, I annulled</l>
		<l>the task I had so quickly undertaken.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;If I have understood what you have said,&quot;</l>
		<l>replied the shade of that great-hearted one,</l>
		<l>&quot;your soul has been assailed by cowardice,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>which often weighs so heavily on a man-</l>
		<l>distracting him from honorable trials-</l>
		<l>as phantoms frighten beasts when shadows fall.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That you may be delivered from this fear,</l>
		<l>I&apos;ll tell you why I came and what I heard</l>
		<l>when I first felt compassion for your pain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I was among those souls who are suspended;</l>
		<l>a lady called to me, so blessed, so lovely</l>
		<l>that I implored to serve at her command.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Her eyes surpassed the splendor of the star&apos;s;</l>
		<l>and she began to speak to me-so gently</l>
		<l>and softly-with angelic voice. She said:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&apos;O spirit of the courteous Mantuan,</l>
		<l>whose fame is still a presence in the world</l>
		<l>and shall endure as long as the world lasts,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my friend, who has not been the friend of fortune,</l>
		<l>is hindered in his path along that lonely</l>
		<l>hillside; he has been turned aside by terror.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From all that I have heard of him in Heaven,</l>
		<l>he is, I fear, already so astray</l>
		<l>that I have come to help him much too late.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Go now; with your persuasive word, with all</l>
		<l>that is required to see that he escapes,</l>
		<l>bring help to him, that I may be consoled.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For I am Beatrice who send you on;</l>
		<l>I come from where I most long to return;</l>
		<l>Love prompted me, that Love which makes me speak.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When once again I stand before my Lord,</l>
		<l>then I shall often let Him hear your praises.&apos;</l>
		<l>Now Beatrice was silent. I began:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&apos;O Lady of virtue, the sole reason why</l>
		<l>the human race surpasses all that lies</l>
		<l>beneath the heaven with the smallest spheres,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so welcome is your wish, that even if</l>
		<l>it were already done, it would seem tardy;</l>
		<l>all you need do is let me know your will.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But tell me why you have not been more prudent-</l>
		<l>descending to this center, moving from</l>
		<l>that spacious place where you long to return?&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&apos;Because you want to fathom things so deeply,</l>
		<l>I now shall tell you promptly,&apos; she replied,</l>
		<l>&apos;why I am not afraid to enter here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One ought to be afraid of nothing other</l>
		<l>than things possessed of power to do us harm,</l>
		<l>but things innocuous need not be feared.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>God, in His graciousness, has made me so</l>
		<l>that this, your misery, cannot touch me;</l>
		<l>I can withstand the fires flaming here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In Heaven there&apos;s a gentle lady-one</l>
		<l>who weeps for the distress toward which I send you</l>
		<l>so that stern judgment up above is shattered.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And it was she who called upon Lucia,</l>
		<l>requesting of her: &quot;Now your faithful one</l>
		<l>has need of you, and I commend him to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Lucia, enemy of every cruelty,</l>
		<l>arose and made her way to where I was,</l>
		<l>sitting beside the venerable Rachel.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>She said: &quot;You, Beatrice, true praise of God,</l>
		<l>why have you not helped him who loves you so</l>
		<l>that-for your sake-he&apos;s left the vulgar crowd?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Do you not hear the anguish in his cry?</l>
		<l>Do you not see the death he wars against</l>
		<l>upon that river ruthless as the sea?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No one within this world has ever been</l>
		<l>so quick to seek his good or flee his harm</l>
		<l>as I-when she had finished speaking thus-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to come below, down from my blessed station;</l>
		<l>I trusted in your honest utterance,</l>
		<l>which honors you and those who&apos;ve listened to you.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When she had finished with her words to me,</l>
		<l>she turned aside her gleaming, tearful eyes,</l>
		<l>which only made me hurry all the more.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And, just as she had wished, I came to you:</l>
		<l>I snatched you from the path of the fierce beast</l>
		<l>that barred the shortest way up the fair mountain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What is it then? Why, why do you resist?</l>
		<l>Why does your heart host so much cowardice?</l>
		<l>Where are your daring and your openness</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as long as there are three such blessed women</l>
		<l>concerned for you within the court of Heaven</l>
		<l>and my words promise you so great a good?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As little flowers, which the chill of night</l>
		<l>has bent and huddled, when the white sun strikes</l>
		<l>grow straight and open fully on their stems,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did I, too, with my exhausted force;</l>
		<l>and such warm daring rushed into my heart</l>
		<l>that I-as one who has been freed-began:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O she, compassionate, who has helped me!</l>
		<l>And you who, courteous, obeyed so quickly</l>
		<l>the true words that she had addressed to you!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You, with your words, have so disposed my heart</l>
		<l>to longing for this journey-I return</l>
		<l>to what I was at first prepared to do.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now go; a single will fills both of us:</l>
		<l>you are my guide, my governor, my master.&quot;</l>
		<l>These were my words to him; when he advanced</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I entered on the steep and savage path.</l>
	</p>
</page>
