<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>I say, continuing, that long before</l>
		<l>we two had reached the foot of that tall tower,</l>
		<l>our eyes had risen upward, toward its summit,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>because of two small flames that flickered there,</l>
		<l>while still another flame returned their signal,</l>
		<l>so far off it was scarcely visible.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I turned toward the sea of all good sense;</l>
		<l>I said: &quot;What does this mean? And what reply</l>
		<l>comes from that other fire? Who kindled it?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;Above the filthy waters</l>
		<l>you can already see what waits for us,</l>
		<l>if it&apos;s not hid by vapors from the marsh.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Bowstring has not thrust from itself an arrow</l>
		<l>that ever rushed as swiftly through the air</l>
		<l>as did the little bark that at that moment</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw as it skimmed toward us on the water,</l>
		<l>a solitary boatman at its helm.</l>
		<l>I heard him howl: &quot;Now you are caught, foul soul!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O Phlegyas, Phlegyas, such a shout is useless</l>
		<l>this time,&quot; my master said; &quot;we&apos;re yours no longer</l>
		<l>than it will take to cross the muddy sluice.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as one who hears some great deception</l>
		<l>was done to him, and then resents it, so</l>
		<l>was Phlegyas when he had to store his anger.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide preceded me into the boat.</l>
		<l>Once he was in, he had me follow him;</l>
		<l>there seemed to be no weight until I boarded.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No sooner were my guide and I embarked</l>
		<l>than off that ancient prow went, cutting water</l>
		<l>more deeply than it does when bearing others.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And while we steered across the stagnant channel,</l>
		<l>before me stood a sinner thick with mud,</l>
		<l>saying: &quot;Who are you, come before your time?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I to him: &quot;I&apos;ve come, but I don&apos;t stay;</l>
		<l>but who are you, who have become so ugly?&quot;</l>
		<l>He answered: &quot;You can see-I&apos;m one who weeps.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I to him: &quot;In weeping and in grieving,</l>
		<l>accursed spirit, may you long remain;</l>
		<l>though you&apos;re disguised by filth, I know your name</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he stretched both his hands out toward the bo</l>
		<l>at which my master quickly shoved him back,</l>
		<l>saying: &quot;Be off there with the other dogs!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That done, he threw his arms around my neck</l>
		<l>and kissed my face and said: &quot;Indignant soul,</l>
		<l>blessed is she who bore you in her womb!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When in the world, he was presumptuous;</l>
		<l>there is no good to gild his memory,</l>
		<l>and so his shade down here is hot with fury.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>How many up above now count themselves</l>
		<l>great kings, who&apos;ll wallow here like pigs in slime</l>
		<l>leaving behind foul memories of their crimes!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;O master, I am very eager</l>
		<l>to see that spirit soused within this broth</l>
		<l>before we&apos;ve made our way across the lake.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;Before the other shore</l>
		<l>comes into view, you shall be satisfied;</l>
		<l>to gratify so fine a wish is right.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Soon after I had heard these words, I saw</l>
		<l>the muddy sinners so dismember him</l>
		<l>that even now I praise and thank God for it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They all were shouting: &quot;At Filippo Argenti!&quot;</l>
		<l>At this, the Florentine, gone wild with spleen,</l>
		<l>began to turn his teeth against himself.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We left him there; I tell no more of him.</l>
		<l>But in my ears so loud a wailing pounded</l>
		<l>that I lean forward, all intent to see.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The kindly master said: &quot;My son, the city</l>
		<l>that bears the name of Dis is drawing near,</l>
		<l>with its grave citizens, its great battalions.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I said: &quot;I can already see distinctly-</l>
		<l>master-the mosques that gleam within the valley,</l>
		<l>as crimson as if they had just been drawn</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>out of the fire.&quot; He told me: &quot;The eternal</l>
		<l>flame burning there appears to make them red,</l>
		<l>as you can see, within this lower Hell.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So we arrived inside the deep-cut trenches</l>
		<l>that are the moats of this despondent land:</l>
		<l>the ramparts seemed to me to be of iron.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But not before we&apos;d ranged in a wide circuit</l>
		<l>did we approach a place where that shrill pilot</l>
		<l>shouted: &quot;Get out; the entrance way is here.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>About the gates I saw more than a thousand-</l>
		<l>who once had rained from Heaven-and they cried</l>
		<l>in anger: &quot;Who is this who, without death,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>can journey through the kingdom of the dead?&quot;</l>
		<l>And my wise master made a sign that said</l>
		<l>he wanted to speak secretly to them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then they suppressed-somewhat-their great disdain</l>
		<l>and said: &quot;You come alone; let him be gone-</l>
		<l>for he was reckless, entering this realm.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Let him return alone on his mad road-</l>
		<l>or try to, if he can, since you, his guide</l>
		<l>across so dark a land, you are to stay.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Consider, reader, my dismay before</l>
		<l>the sound of those abominable words:</l>
		<l>returning here seemed so impossible.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O my dear guide, who more than seven times</l>
		<l>has given back to me my confidence</l>
		<l>and snatched me from deep danger that had menaced,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>do not desert me when I&apos;m so undone;</l>
		<l>and if they will not let us pass beyond,</l>
		<l>let us retrace our steps together, quickly.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These were my words; the lord who&apos;d led me there</l>
		<l>replied: &quot;Forget your fear, no one can hinder</l>
		<l>our passage; One so great has granted it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But you wait here for me, and feed and comfort</l>
		<l>your tired spirit with good hope, for I</l>
		<l>will not abandon you in this low world.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So he goes on his way; that gentle father</l>
		<l>has left me there to wait and hesitate,</l>
		<l>for yes and no contend within my head.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I could not hear what he was telling them;</l>
		<l>but he had not been long with them when each</l>
		<l>ran back into the city, scrambling fast.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And these, our adversaries, slammed the gates</l>
		<l>in my lord&apos;s face; and he remained outside,</l>
		<l>then, with slow steps, turned back again to me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His eyes turned to the ground, his brows deprived</l>
		<l>of every confidence, he said with sighs:</l>
		<l>&quot;See who has kept me from the house of sorrow!&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To me he added: &quot;You-though I am vexed-</l>
		<l>must not be daunted; I shall win this contest,</l>
		<l>whoever tries-within-to block our way.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This insolence of theirs is nothing new;</l>
		<l>they used it once before and at a gate</l>
		<l>less secret-it is still without its bolts-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the place where you made out the fatal text;</l>
		<l>and now, already well within that gate,</l>
		<l>across the circles-and alone-descends</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the one who will unlock this realm for us.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
