<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>I must make verses of new punishment</l>
		<l>and offer matter now for Canto Twenty</l>
		<l>of this first canticle-of the submerged.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I was already well prepared to stare</l>
		<l>below, into the depth that was disclosed,</l>
		<l>where tears of anguished sorrow bathed the ground;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and in the valley&apos;s circle I saw souls</l>
		<l>advancing, mute and weeping, at the pace</l>
		<l>that, in our world, holy processions take.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As I inclined my head still more, I saw</l>
		<l>that each, amazingly, appeared contorted</l>
		<l>between the chin and where the chest begins;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>they had their faces twisted toward their haunches</l>
		<l>and found it necessary to walk backward,</l>
		<l>because they could not see ahead of them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Perhaps the force of palsy has so fully</l>
		<l>distorted some, but that I&apos;ve yet to see,</l>
		<l>and I do not believe that that can be.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>May God so let you, reader, gather fruit</l>
		<l>from what you read; and now think for yourself</l>
		<l>how I could ever keep my own face dry</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when I beheld our image so nearby</l>
		<l>and so awry that tears, down from the eyes,</l>
		<l>bathed the buttocks, running down the cleft.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Of course I wept, leaning against a rock</l>
		<l>along that rugged ridge, so that my guide</l>
		<l>told me: &quot;Are you as foolish as the rest?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here pity only lives when it is dead:</l>
		<l>for who can be more impious than he</l>
		<l>who links God&apos;s judgment to passivity?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Lift, lift your head and see the one for whom</l>
		<l>the earth was opened while the Thebans watched,</l>
		<l>so that they all cried: &apos;Amphiaraus,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>where are you rushing? Have you quit the fight?&apos;</l>
		<l>Nor did he interrupt his downward plunge</l>
		<l>to Minos, who lays hands on every sinner.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>See how he&apos;s made a chest out of his shoulders;</l>
		<l>and since he wanted so to see ahead,</l>
		<l>he looks behind and walks a backward path.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And see Tiresias, who changed his mien</l>
		<l>when from a man he turned into a woman,</l>
		<l>so totally transforming all his limbs</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that then he had to strike once more upon</l>
		<l>the two entwining serpents with his wand</l>
		<l>before he had his manly plumes again.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And Aruns is the one who backs against</l>
		<l>the belly of Tiresias-Aruns who,</l>
		<l>in Luni&apos;s hills, tilled by the Carrarese,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who live below, had as his home, a cave</l>
		<l>among white marbles, from which he could gaze</l>
		<l>at stars and sea with unimpeded view.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And she who covers up her breasts-which you</l>
		<l>can&apos;t see-with her disheveled locks, who keeps</l>
		<l>all of her hairy parts to the far side,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was Manto, who had searched through many lands,</l>
		<l>then settled in the place where I was born;</l>
		<l>on this, I&apos;d have you hear me now a while.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When Manto&apos;s father took his leave of life,</l>
		<l>and Bacchus&apos; city found itself enslaved,</l>
		<l>she wandered through the world for many years.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>High up, in lovely Italy, beneath</l>
		<l>the Alps that shut in Germany above</l>
		<l>Tirolo, lies a lake known as Benaco.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A thousand springs and more, I think, must flow</l>
		<l>out of the waters of that lake to bathe</l>
		<l>Pennino, Garda, Val Camonica.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And at its middle is a place where three-</l>
		<l>the bishops of Verona, Brescia, Trento-</l>
		<l>may bless if they should chance to come that way.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Peschiera, strong and handsome fortress, built</l>
		<l>to face the Brescians and the Bergamasques</l>
		<l>stands where the circling shore is at its lowest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, all the waters that cannot be held</l>
		<l>within the bosom of Benaco fall,</l>
		<l>to form a river running through green meadows.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No sooner has that stream begun to flow</l>
		<l>than it is called the Mincio, not Benaco-</l>
		<l>until Governolo, where it joins the Po.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It&apos;s not flowed far before it finds flat land;</l>
		<l>and there it stretches out to form a fen</l>
		<l>that in the summer can at times be fetid.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when she passed that way, the savage virgin</l>
		<l>saw land along the middle of the swamp,</l>
		<l>untilled and stripped of its inhabitants.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there, to flee all human intercourse,</l>
		<l>she halted with her slaves to ply her arts;</l>
		<l>and there she lived, there left her empty body.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And afterward, the people of those parts</l>
		<l>collected at that place, because the marsh-</l>
		<l>surrounding it on all sides-made it strong.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They built a city over her dead bones;</l>
		<l>and after her who first had picked that spot,</l>
		<l>they called it Mantua-they cast no lots.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There once were far more people in its walls,</l>
		<l>before the foolishness of Casalodi</l>
		<l>was tricked by the deceit of Pinamonte.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, I charge you, if you ever hear</l>
		<l>a different tale of my town&apos;s origin,</l>
		<l>do not let any falsehood gull the truth.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;O master, that which you have spoken</l>
		<l>convinces me and so compels my trust</l>
		<l>that others&apos; words would only be spent coals.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But tell me if among the passing souls</l>
		<l>you see some spirits worthy of our notice,</l>
		<l>because my mind is bent on that alone.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he to me: &quot;That shade who spreads his beard</l>
		<l>down from his cheeks across his swarthy shoulders-</l>
		<l>when Greece had been so emptied of its males</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that hardly any cradle held a son,</l>
		<l>he was an augur; and at Aulis, he</l>
		<l>and Calchas set the time to cut the cables.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His name&apos;s Eurypylus; a certain passage</l>
		<l>of my high tragedy has sung it so;</l>
		<l>you  know that well enough, who know the whole.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That other there, his flanks extremely spare,</l>
		<l>was Michael Scot, a man who certainly</l>
		<l>knew how the game of magic fraud was played.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>See there Guido Bonatti; see Asdente,</l>
		<l>who now would wish he had attended to</l>
		<l>his cord and leather, but repents too late.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>See those sad women who had left their needle,</l>
		<l>shuttle, and spindle to become diviners;</l>
		<l>they cast their spells with herbs and effigies</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But let us go; Cain with his thorns already</l>
		<l>is at the border of both hemispheres</l>
		<l>and there, below Seville, touches the sea.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Last night the moon was at its full; you should</l>
		<l>be well aware of this, for there were times</l>
		<l>when it did you no harm in the deep wood.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These were his words to me; meanwhile we journeyed</l>
	</p>
</page>
