<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>THROUGH ME THE WAY INTO THE SUFFERING CITY,</l>
		<l>THROUGH ME THE WAY TO THE ETERNAL PAIN,</l>
		<l>THROUGH ME THE WAY THAT RUNS AMONG THE LOST.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>JUSTICE URGED ON MY HIGH ARTIFICER;</l>
		<l>MY MAKER WAS DIVINE AUTHORITY,</l>
		<l>THE HIGHEST WISDOM, AND THE PRIMAL LOVE.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>BEFORE ME NOTHING BUT ETERNAL THINGS</l>
		<l>WERE MADE, AND I ENDURE ETERNALLY.</l>
		<l>ABANDON EVERY HOPE, WHO ENTER HERE.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These words-their aspect was obscure-I read</l>
		<l>inscribed above a gateway, and I said:</l>
		<l>&quot;Master, their meaning is difficult for me.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me, as one who comprehends:</l>
		<l>&quot;Here one must leave behind all hesitation;</l>
		<l>here every cowardice must meet its death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For we have reached the place of which I spoke,</l>
		<l>where you will see the miserable people,</l>
		<l>those who have lost the good of the intellect.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when, with gladness in his face, he placed</l>
		<l>his hand upon my own, to comfort me,</l>
		<l>he drew me in among the hidden things.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here sighs and lamentations and loud cries</l>
		<l>were echoing across the starless air,</l>
		<l>so that, as soon as I set out, I wept.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Strange utterances, horrible pronouncements,</l>
		<l>accents of anger, words of suffering,</l>
		<l>and voices shrill and faint, and beating hands-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>all went to make a tumult that will whirl</l>
		<l>forever through that turbid, timeless air,</l>
		<l>like sand that eddies when a whirlwind swirls.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I-my head oppressed by horror-said:</l>
		<l>&quot;Master, what is it that I hear? Who are</l>
		<l>those people so defeated by their pain?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;This miserable way</l>
		<l>is taken by the sorry souls of those</l>
		<l>who lived without disgrace and without praise.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They now commingle with the coward angels,</l>
		<l>the company of those who were not rebels</l>
		<l>nor faithful to their God, but stood apart.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The heavens, that their beauty not be lessened,</l>
		<l>have cast them out, nor will deep Hell receive the</l>
		<l>even the wicked cannot glory in them.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;What is it, master, that oppresses</l>
		<l>these souls, compelling them to wail so loud?&quot;</l>
		<l>He answered: &quot;I shall tell you in few words.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those who are here can place no hope in death,</l>
		<l>and their blind life is so abject that they</l>
		<l>are envious of every other fate.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The world will let no fame of theirs endure;</l>
		<l>both justice and compassion must disdain them;</l>
		<l>let us not talk of them, but look and pass.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I, looking more closely, saw a banner</l>
		<l>that, as it wheeled about, raced on-so quick</l>
		<l>that any respite seemed unsuited to it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Behind that banner trailed so long a file</l>
		<l>of people-I should never have believed</l>
		<l>that death could have unmade so many souls.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After I had identified a few,</l>
		<l>I saw and recognized the shade of him</l>
		<l>who made, through cowardice, the great refusal.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At once I understood with certainty:</l>
		<l>this company contained the cowardly,</l>
		<l>hateful to God and to His enemies.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These wretched ones, who never were alive,</l>
		<l>went naked and were stung again, again</l>
		<l>by horseflies and by wasps that circled them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The insects streaked their faces with their blood,</l>
		<l>which, mingled with their tears, fell at their fee</l>
		<l>where it was gathered up by sickening worms.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And then, looking beyond them, I could see</l>
		<l>a crowd along the bank of a great river;</l>
		<l>at which I said: &quot;Allow me now to know</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who are these people-master-and what law</l>
		<l>has made them seem so eager for the crossing,</l>
		<l>as I can see despite the feeble light.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;When we have stopped along</l>
		<l>the melancholy shore of Acheron,</l>
		<l>then all these matters will be plain to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At that, with eyes ashamed, downcast, and fearing</l>
		<l>that what I said had given him offense,</l>
		<l>I did not speak until we reached the river.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And here, advancing toward us, in a boat,</l>
		<l>an aged man-his hair was white with years-</l>
		<l>was shouting: &quot;Woe to you, corrupted souls!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Forget your hope of ever seeing Heaven:</l>
		<l>I come to lead you to the other shore,</l>
		<l>to the eternal dark, to fire and frost.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And you approaching there, you living soul,</l>
		<l>keep well away from these-they are the dead.&quot;</l>
		<l>But when he saw I made no move to go,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he said: &quot;Another way and other harbors-</l>
		<l>not here-will bring you passage to your shore:</l>
		<l>a lighter craft will have to carry you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide then: &quot;Charon, don&apos;t torment yourself:</l>
		<l>our passage has been willed above, where One</l>
		<l>can do what He has willed; and ask no more.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now silence fell upon the wooly cheeks</l>
		<l>of Charon, pilot of the livid marsh,</l>
		<l>whose eyes were ringed about with wheels of flame.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But all those spirits, naked and exhausted,</l>
		<l>had lost their color, and they gnashed their teeth</l>
		<l>as soon as they heard Charon&apos;s cruel words;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>they execrated God and their own parents	</l>
		<l>and humankind, and then the place and time</l>
		<l>of their conception&apos;s seed and of their birth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then they forgathered, huddled in one throng,</l>
		<l>weeping aloud along that wretched shore</l>
		<l>which waits for all who have no fear of God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The demon Charon, with his eyes like embers,</l>
		<l>by signaling to them, has all embark;</l>
		<l>his oar strikes anyone who stretches out.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As, in the autumn, leaves detach themselves,</l>
		<l>first one and then the other, till the bough</l>
		<l>sees all its fallen garments on the ground,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>similarly, the evil seed of Adam</l>
		<l>descended from the shoreline one by one,</l>
		<l>when signaled, as a falcon-called-will come.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So do they move across the darkened waters;</l>
		<l>even before they reach the farther shore,</l>
		<l>new ranks already gather on this bank.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;My son,&quot; the gracious master said to me,</l>
		<l>&quot;those who have died beneath the wrath of God,</l>
		<l>all these assemble here from every country;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and they are eager for the river crossing</l>
		<l>because celestial justice spurs them on,</l>
		<l>so that their fear is turned into desire.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No good soul ever takes its passage here;</l>
		<l>therefore, if Charon has complained of you,</l>
		<l>by now you can be sure what his words mean.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And after this was said, the darkened plain</l>
		<l>quaked so tremendously-the memory</l>
		<l>of terror then, bathes me in sweat again.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A whirlwind burst out of the tear-drenched earth,</l>
		<l>a wind that crackled with a bloodred light,</l>
		<l>a light that overcame all of my senses;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and like a man whom sleep has seized, I fell.</l>
	</p>
</page>
