<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Be joyous, Florence, you are great indeed,</l>
		<l>for over sea and land you beat your wings;</l>
		<l>through every part of Hell your name extends!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Among the thieves I found five citizens</l>
		<l>of yours-and such, that shame has taken me;</l>
		<l>with them, you can ascend to no high honor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But if the dreams dreamt close to dawn are true,</l>
		<l>then little time will pass before you feel</l>
		<l>what Prato and the others crave for you.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Were that already come, it would not be</l>
		<l>too soon-and let it come, since it must be!</l>
		<l>As I grow older, it will be more heavy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We left that deep and, by protruding stones</l>
		<l>that served as stairs for our descent before,</l>
		<l>my guide climbed up again and drew me forward;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and as we took our solitary path</l>
		<l>among the ridge&apos;s jagged spurs and rocks,</l>
		<l>our feet could not make way without our hands.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It grieved me then and now grieves me again</l>
		<l>when I direct my mind to what I saw;</l>
		<l>and more than usual, I curb my talent,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that it not run where virtue does not guide;</l>
		<l>so that, if my kind star or something better</l>
		<l>has given me that gift, I not abuse it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As many as the fireflies the peasant</l>
		<l>(while resting on a hillside in the season</l>
		<l>when he who lights the world least hides his face)</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just when the fly gives way to the mosquito,</l>
		<l>sees glimmering below, down in the valley,</l>
		<l>there where perhaps he gathers grapes and tills-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so many were the flames that glittered in</l>
		<l>the eighth abyss; I made this out as soon</l>
		<l>as I had come to where one sees the bottom.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even as he who was avenged by bears</l>
		<l>saw, as it left, Elijah&apos;s chariot-</l>
		<l>its horses rearing, rising right to heaven-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when he could not keep track of it except</l>
		<l>by watching one lone flame in its ascent,</l>
		<l>just like a little cloud that climbs on high:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, through the gullet of that ditch, each flame</l>
		<l>must make its way; no flame displays its prey,</l>
		<l>though every flame has carried off a sinner.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I stood upon the bridge and leaned straight out</l>
		<l>to see; and if I had not gripped a rock,</l>
		<l>I should have fallen off-without a push.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide, who noted how intent I was,</l>
		<l>told me: &quot;Within those fires there are souls;</l>
		<l>each one is swathed in that which scorches him.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;My master,&quot; I replied, &quot;on hearing you,</l>
		<l>I am more sure; but I&apos;d already thought</l>
		<l>that it was so, and I had meant to ask:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Who is within the flame that comes so twinned</l>
		<l>above that it would seem to rise out of</l>
		<l>the pyre Eteocles shared with his brother?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He answered me: &quot;Within that flame, Ulysses</l>
		<l>and Diomedes suffer; they, who went</l>
		<l>as one to rage, now share one punishment.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there, together in their flame, they grieve</l>
		<l>over the horse&apos;s fraud that caused a breach-</l>
		<l>the gate that let Rome&apos;s noble seed escape.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There they regret the guile that makes the dead</l>
		<l>Deidamia still lament Achilles;</l>
		<l>and there, for the Palladium, they pay.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;If they can speak within those sparks,&quot; I said,</l>
		<l>&quot;I pray you and repray and, master, may</l>
		<l>my prayer be worth a thousand pleas, do not</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>forbid my waiting here until the flame</l>
		<l>with horns approaches us; for you can see</l>
		<l>how, out of my desire, I bend toward it.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;What you have asked is worthy</l>
		<l>of every praise; therefore, I favor it.</l>
		<l>I only ask you this: refrain from talking.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Let me address them-I have understood</l>
		<l>what you desire of them. Since they were Greek,</l>
		<l>perhaps they&apos;d be disdainful of your speech.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when my guide adjudged the flame had reached</l>
		<l>a point where time and place were opportune,</l>
		<l>this was the form I heard his words assume:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;You two who move as one within the flame,</l>
		<l>if I deserved of you while I still lived,</l>
		<l>if I deserved of you much or a little</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when in the world I wrote my noble lines,</l>
		<l>do not move on; let one of you retell</l>
		<l>where, having gone astray, he found his death.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The greater horn within that ancient flame</l>
		<l>began to sway and tremble, murmuring</l>
		<l>just like a fire that struggles in the wind;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and then he waved his flame-tip back and forth</l>
		<l>as if it were a tongue that tried to speak,</l>
		<l>and flung toward us a voice that answered: &quot;When</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I sailed away from Circe, who&apos;d beguiled me</l>
		<l>to stay more than a year there, near Gaeta-</l>
		<l>before Aeneas gave that place a name-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>neither my fondness for my son nor pity</l>
		<l>for my old father nor the love I owed</l>
		<l>Penelope, which would have gladdened her,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was able to defeat in me the longing</l>
		<l>I had to gain experience of the world</l>
		<l>and of the vices and the worth of men.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, I set out on the open sea</l>
		<l>with but one ship and that small company</l>
		<l>of those who never had deserted me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw as far as Spain, far as Morocco,</l>
		<l>along both shores; I saw Sardinia</l>
		<l>and saw the other islands that sea bathes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I and my companions were already</l>
		<l>old and slow, when we approached the narrows</l>
		<l>where Hercules set up his boundary stones</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that men might heed and never reach beyond:</l>
		<l>upon my right, I had gone past Seville,</l>
		<l>and on the left, already passed Ceuta.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&apos;Brothers,&apos; I said, &apos;o you, who having crossed</l>
		<l>a hundred thousand dangers, reach the west,</l>
		<l>to this brief waking-time that still is left</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>unto your senses, you must not deny</l>
		<l>experience of that which lies beyond</l>
		<l>the sun, and of the world that is unpeopled.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Consider well the seed that gave you birth:</l>
		<l>you were not made to live your lives as brutes,</l>
		<l>but to be followers of worth and knowledge.&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I spurred my comrades with this brief address</l>
		<l>to meet the journey with such eagerness</l>
		<l>that I could hardly, then, have held them back;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and having turned our stern toward morning, we</l>
		<l>made wings out of our oars in a wild flight</l>
		<l>and always gained upon our left-hand side.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At night I now could see the other pole</l>
		<l>and all its stars; the star of ours had fallen</l>
		<l>and never rose above the plain of the ocean.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Five times the light beneath the moon had been</l>
		<l>rekindled, and, as many times, was spent,</l>
		<l>since that hard passage faced our first attempt,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when there before us rose a mountain, dark</l>
		<l>because of distance, and it seemed to me</l>
		<l>the highest mountain I had ever seen.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And we were glad, but this soon turned to sorrow,</l>
		<l>for out of that new land a whirlwind rose</l>
		<l>and hammered at our ship, against her bow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Three times it turned her round with all the water</l>
		<l>and at the fourth, it lifted up the stern</l>
		<l>so that our prow plunged deep, as pleased an Other</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>until the sea again closed-over us.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
