<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The color cowardice displayed in me</l>
		<l>when I saw that my guide was driven back,</l>
		<l>made him more quickly mask his own new pallor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He stood alert, like an attentive listener,</l>
		<l>because his eye could hardly journey far</l>
		<l>across the black air and the heavy fog.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;We have to win this battle,&quot; he began,</l>
		<l>&quot;if not. . . But one so great had offered help.</l>
		<l>How slow that someone&apos;s coming to see me!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But I saw well enough how he had covered</l>
		<l>his first words with the words that followed after</l>
		<l>so different from what he had said before;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>nevertheless, his speech made me afraid,</l>
		<l>because I drew out from his broken phrase</l>
		<l>a meaning worse-perhaps-than he&apos;d intended.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Does anyone from the first circle, one</l>
		<l>whose only punishment is crippled hope,</l>
		<l>ever descend so deep in this sad hollow?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That was my question. And he answered so:</l>
		<l>&quot;It is quite rare for one of us to go</l>
		<l>along the way that I have taken now.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But I, in truth, have been here once before:</l>
		<l>that savage witch Erichtho, she who called</l>
		<l>the shades back to their bodies, summoned me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My flesh had not been long stripped off when she</l>
		<l>had me descend through all the rings of Hell,</l>
		<l>to draw a spirit back from Judas&apos; circle.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That is the deepest and the darkest place,</l>
		<l>the farthest from the heaven that girds all:</l>
		<l>so rest assured, I know the pathway well.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This swamp that breeds and breathes the giant sten</l>
		<l>surrounds the city of the sorrowing,</l>
		<l>which now we cannot enter without anger.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he said more, but I cannot remember</l>
		<l>because my eyes had wholly taken me</l>
		<l>to that high tower with the glowing summit</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>where, at one single point, there suddenly</l>
		<l>stood three infernal Furies flecked with blood,</l>
		<l>who had the limbs of women and their ways</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but wore, as girdles, snakes of deepest green;</l>
		<l>small serpents and horned vipers formed their hair</l>
		<l>and these were used to bind their bestial temples.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he, who knew these handmaids well-they served</l>
		<l>the Queen of never-ending lamentation-</l>
		<l>said: &quot;Look at the ferocious Erinyes!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That is Megaera on the left, and she</l>
		<l>who weeps upon the right, that is Allecto;</l>
		<l>Tisiphone&apos;s between them.&quot; He was done.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Each Fury tore her breast with taloned nails;</l>
		<l>each, with her palms, beat on herself and wailed</l>
		<l>so loud that I, in fear, drew near the poet.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Just let Medusa come; then we shall turn</l>
		<l>him into stone,&quot; they all cried, looking down;</l>
		<l>&quot;we should have punished Theseus&apos; assault.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Turn round and keep your eyes shut fast, for shou</l>
		<l>the Gorgon show herself and you behold her,</l>
		<l>never again would you return above,&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my master said; and he himself turned me</l>
		<l>around and, not content with just my hands,</l>
		<l>used his as well to cover up my eyes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O you possessed of sturdy intellects,</l>
		<l>observe the teaching that is hidden here</l>
		<l>beneath the veil of verses so obscure.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And now, across the turbid waves, there passed</l>
		<l>a reboantic fracas-horrid sound,</l>
		<l>enough to make both of the shorelines quake:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a sound not other than a wind&apos;s when, wild</l>
		<l>because it must contend with warmer currents,</l>
		<l>it strikes against the forest without let,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>shattering, beating down, bearing off branches,</l>
		<l>as it moves proudly, clouds of dust before it,</l>
		<l>and puts to flight both animals and shepherds.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He freed my eyes and said: &quot;Now let your optic</l>
		<l>nerve turn directly toward that ancient foam,</l>
		<l>there where the mist is thickest and most acrid.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As frogs confronted by their enemy,</l>
		<l>the snake, will scatter underwater till</l>
		<l>each hunches in a heap along the bottom,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did the thousand ruined souls I saw</l>
		<l>take flight before a figure crossing Styx</l>
		<l>who walked as if on land and with dry soles.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He thrust away the thick air from his face,</l>
		<l>waving his left hand frequently before him;</l>
		<l>that seemed the only task that wearied him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I knew well he was Heaven&apos;s messenger,</l>
		<l>and I turned toward my master; and he made</l>
		<l>a sign that I be still and bow before him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>How full of high disdain he seemed to me!</l>
		<l>He came up to the gate, and with a wand,</l>
		<l>he opened it, for there was no resistance.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O you cast out of Heaven, hated crowd,&quot;</l>
		<l>were his first words upon that horrid threshold,</l>
		<l>&quot;why do you harbor this presumptuousness?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Why are you so reluctant to endure</l>
		<l>that Will whose aim can never be cut short,</l>
		<l>and which so often added to your hurts?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What good is it to thrust against the fates?</l>
		<l>Your Cerberus, if you remember well,</l>
		<l>for that, had both his throat and chin stripped cl</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At that he turned and took the filthy road,</l>
		<l>and did not speak to us, but had the look</l>
		<l>of one who is obsessed by other cares</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>than those that press and gnaw at those before him</l>
		<l>and we moved forward, on into the city,</l>
		<l>in safety, having heard his holy words.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We made our way inside without a struggle;</l>
		<l>and I, who wanted so much to observe</l>
		<l>the state of things that such a fortress guarded,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as soon as I had entered, looked about.</l>
		<l>I saw, on every side, a spreading plain</l>
		<l>of lamentation and atrocious pain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as at Arles, where Rhone becomes a marsh,</l>
		<l>just as at Pola, near Quarnero&apos;s gulf,</l>
		<l>that closes Italy and bathes its borders,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the sepulchers make all the plain uneven,</l>
		<l>so they did here on every side, except</l>
		<l>that here the sepulchers were much more harsh;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for flames were scattered through the tombs, and t</l>
		<l>had kindled all of them to glowing heat;</l>
		<l>no artisan could ask for hotter iron.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The lid of every tomb was lifted up,</l>
		<l>and from each tomb such sorry cries arose</l>
		<l>as could come only from the sad and hurt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;Master, who can these people be</l>
		<l>who, buried in great chests of stone like these,</l>
		<l>must speak by way of sighs in agony?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;Here are arch-heretics</l>
		<l>and those who followed them, from every sect;</l>
		<l>those tombs are much more crowded than you think.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here, like has been ensepulchered with like;</l>
		<l>some monuments are heated more, some less.&quot;</l>
		<l>And then he turned around and to his right;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>we passed between the torments and high walls.</l>
	</p>
</page>
