<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>We came along from one bridge to another,</l>
		<l>talking of things my Comedy is not</l>
		<l>concerned to sing. We held fast to the summit,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then stayed our steps to spy the other cleft</l>
		<l>of Malebolge and other vain laments.</l>
		<l>I saw that it was wonderfully dark.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As in the arsenal of the Venetians,</l>
		<l>all winter long a stew of sticky pitch</l>
		<l>boils up to patch their sick and tattered ships</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that cannot sail (instead of voyaging,</l>
		<l>some build new keels, some tow and tar the ribs</l>
		<l>of hulls worn out by too much journeying;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>some hammer at the prow, some at the stern,</l>
		<l>and some make oars, and some braid ropes and cords</l>
		<l>one mends the jib, another, the mainsail);</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, not by fire but by the art of God,</l>
		<l>below there boiled a thick and tarry mass</l>
		<l>that covered all the banks with clamminess.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw it, but I could not see within it;</l>
		<l>no thing was visible but boiling bubbles,</l>
		<l>the swelling of the pitch; and then it settled.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And while I watched below attentively,</l>
		<l>my guide called out to me: &quot;Take care! Take care!&quot;</l>
		<l>And then, from where I stood, he drew me near.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I turned around as one who is impatient</l>
		<l>to see what he should shun but is dashed down</l>
		<l>beneath the terror he has undergone,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who does not stop his flight and yet would look.</l>
		<l>And then in back of us I saw a black</l>
		<l>demon as he came racing up the crags.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Ah, he was surely barbarous to see!</l>
		<l>And how relentless seemed to me his acts!</l>
		<l>His wings were open and his feet were lithe;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>across his shoulder, which was sharp and high,</l>
		<l>he had slung a sinner, upward from the thighs;</l>
		<l>in front, the demon gripped him by the ankles.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then from our bridge, he called: &quot;O Malebranche,</l>
		<l>I&apos;ve got an elder of Saint Zita for you!</l>
		<l>Shove this one under-I&apos;ll go back for more-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>his city is well furnished with such stores;</l>
		<l>there, everyone&apos;s a grafter but Bonturo;</l>
		<l>and there-for cash-they&apos;ll change a no to yes.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He threw the sinner down, then wheeled along</l>
		<l>The stony cliff: no mastiff&apos;s ever been</l>
		<l>unleashed with so much haste to chase a thief.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The sinner plunged, then surfaced, black with pitch</l>
		<l>but now the demons, from beneath the bridge,</l>
		<l>shouted: &quot;The Sacred Face has no place here;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>here we swim differently than in the Serchio;</l>
		<l>if you don&apos;t want to feel our grappling hooks,</l>
		<l>don&apos;t try to lift yourself above that ditch.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They pricked him with a hundred prongs and more,</l>
		<l>then taunted: &quot;Here one dances under cover,</l>
		<l>so try to grab your secret graft below.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The demons did the same as any cook</l>
		<l>who has his urchins force the meat with hooks</l>
		<l>deep down into the pot, that it not float.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then my good master said to me: &quot;Don&apos;t let</l>
		<l>those demons see that you are here; take care</l>
		<l>to crouch behind the cover of a crag.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No matter what offense they offer me,</l>
		<l>don&apos;t be afraid; I know how these things go-</l>
		<l>I&apos;ve had to face such fracases before.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When this was said, he moved beyond the bridgehead</l>
		<l>And on the sixth embankment, he had need</l>
		<l>to show his imperturbability.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>With the same frenzy, with the brouhaha</l>
		<l>of dogs, when they beset a poor wretch who</l>
		<l>then stops dead in his tracks as if to beg,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, from beneath the bridge, the demons rushed</l>
		<l>against my guide with all their prongs, but he</l>
		<l>called out: &quot;Can&apos;t you forget your savagery!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Before you try to maul me, just let one</l>
		<l>of all your troop step forward. Hear me out,</l>
		<l>and then decide if I am to be hooked.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this they howled, &quot;Let Malacoda go!&quot;</l>
		<l>And one of them moved up-the others stayed-</l>
		<l>and as he came, he asked: &quot;How can he win?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O Malacoda, do you think I&apos;ve come,&quot;</l>
		<l>my master answered him, &quot;already armed-</l>
		<l>as you can see-against your obstacles,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>without the will of God and helpful fate?</l>
		<l>Let us move on; it is the will of Heaven</l>
		<l>for me to show this wild way to another.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this the pride of Malacoda fell;</l>
		<l>his prong dropped to his feet. He told his fellows</l>
		<l>&quot;Since that&apos;s the way things stand, let us not wou</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide then spoke to me: &quot;O you, who crouch,</l>
		<l>bent low among the bridge&apos;s splintered rocks,</l>
		<l>you can feel safe-and now return to me.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this I moved and quickly came to him.</l>
		<l>The devils had edged forward, all of them;</l>
		<l>I feared that they might fail to keep their word:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just so, I saw the infantry when they</l>
		<l>marched out, under safe conduct, from Caprona;</l>
		<l>they trembled when they passed their enemies.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My body huddled closer to my guide;</l>
		<l>I did not let the demons out of sight;</l>
		<l>the looks they cast at us were less than kind.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They bent their hooks and shouted to each other:</l>
		<l>&quot;And shall I give it to him on the rump?&quot;</l>
		<l>And all of them replied, &quot;Yes, let him have it!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But Malacoda, still in conversation</l>
		<l>with my good guide, turned quickly to his squadron</l>
		<l>and said: &quot;Be still, Scarmiglione, still!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To us he said: &quot;There is no use in going</l>
		<l>much farther on this ridge, because the sixth</l>
		<l>bridge-at the bottom there-is smashed to bits.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Yet if you two still want to go ahead,</l>
		<l>move up and walk along this rocky edge;</l>
		<l>nearby, another ridge will form a path.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Five hours from this hour yesterday,</l>
		<l>one thousand and two hundred sixty-six</l>
		<l>years passed since that roadway was shattered here</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I&apos;m sending ten of mine out there to see</l>
		<l>if any sinner lifts his head for air;</l>
		<l>go with my men-there is no malice in them.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Step forward, Alichino and Calcabrina,&quot;</l>
		<l>he then began to say, &quot;and you, Cagnazzo;</l>
		<l>and Barbariccia, who can lead the ten.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Let Libicocco go, and Draghignazzo</l>
		<l>and tusky Ciriatto and Graffiacane</l>
		<l>and Farfarello and mad Rubicante.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Search all around the clammy stew of pitch;</l>
		<l>keep these two safe and sound till the next ridge</l>
		<l>that rises without break across the dens.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Ah me! What is this, master, that I see?&quot;</l>
		<l>I said. &quot;Can&apos;t we do without company?</l>
		<l>If you know how to go, I want no escort.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If you are just as keen as usual,</l>
		<l>can&apos;t you see how those demons grind their teeth?</l>
		<l>Their brows are menacing, they promise trouble.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;I do not want you frightened:</l>
		<l>just let them gnash away as they may wish;</l>
		<l>they do it for the wretches boiled in pitch.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They turned around along the left hand bank:</l>
		<l>but first each pressed his tongue between his teeth</l>
		<l>as signal for their leader, Barbariccia.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he had made a trumpet of his ass.</l>
	</p>
</page>
