<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The place that we had reached for our descent</l>
		<l>along the bank was alpine; what reclined</l>
		<l>upon that bank would, too, repel all eyes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just like the toppled mass of rock that struck-</l>
		<l>because of earthquake or eroded props-</l>
		<l>the Adige on its flank, this side of Trent,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>where from the mountain top from which it thrust</l>
		<l>down to the plain, the rock is shattered so</l>
		<l>that it permits a path for those above:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>such was the passage down to that ravine.</l>
		<l>And at the edge above the cracked abyss,</l>
		<l>there lay outstretched the infamy of Crete,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>conceived within the counterfeited cow;</l>
		<l>and, catching sight of us, he bit himself</l>
		<l>like one whom fury devastates within.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Turning to him, my sage cried out: &quot;Perhaps</l>
		<l>you think this is the Duke of Athens here,</l>
		<l>who, in the world above, brought you your death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Be off, you beast; this man who comes has not</l>
		<l>been tutored by your sister; all he wants</l>
		<l>in coming here is to observe your torments.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as the bull that breaks loose from its halter</l>
		<l>the moment it receives the fatal stroke,</l>
		<l>and cannot run but plunges back and forth,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did I see the Minotaur respond;</l>
		<l>and my alert guide cried: &quot;Run toward the pass;</l>
		<l>it&apos;s better to descend while he&apos;s berserk.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And so we made our way across that heap</l>
		<l>of stones, which often moved beneath my feet</l>
		<l>because my weight was somewhat strange for them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>While climbing down, I thought. He said: &quot;You wonder,</l>
		<l>perhaps, about that fallen mass, watched over</l>
		<l>by the inhuman rage I have just quenched.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now I would have you know: the other time</l>
		<l>that I descended into lower Hell,</l>
		<l>this mass of boulders had not yet collapsed;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but if I reason rightly, it was just</l>
		<l>before the coming of the One who took</l>
		<l>from Dis the highest circle&apos;s splendid spoils</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that, on all sides, the steep and filthy valley</l>
		<l>had trembled so, I thought the universe</l>
		<l>felt love (by which, as some believe, the world</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>has often been converted into chaos);</l>
		<l>and at that moment, here as well as elsewhere,</l>
		<l>these ancient boulders toppled, in this way.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But fix your eyes below, upon the valley,</l>
		<l>for now we near the stream of blood, where those</l>
		<l>who injure others violently, boil.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O blind cupidity and insane anger,</l>
		<l>which goad us on so much in our short life,</l>
		<l>then steep us in such grief eternally!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw a broad ditch bent into an arc</l>
		<l>so that it could embrace all of that plain,</l>
		<l>precisely as my guide had said before;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>between it and the base of the embankment</l>
		<l>raced files of Centaurs who were armed with arrows</l>
		<l>as, in the world above, they used to hunt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>On seeing us descend, they all reined in;</l>
		<l>and, after they had chosen bows and shafts,</l>
		<l>three of their number moved out from their ranks;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and still far off, one cried: &quot;What punishment</l>
		<l>do you approach as you descend the slope?</l>
		<l>But speak from there; if not, I draw my bow.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My master told him: &quot;We shall make reply</l>
		<l>only to Chiron, when we reach his side;</l>
		<l>your hasty will has never served you well.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he nudged me and said: &quot;That one is Nessus,</l>
		<l>who died because of lovely Deianira</l>
		<l>and of himself wrought vengeance for himself.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And in the middle, gazing at his chest,</l>
		<l>is mighty Chiron, tutor of Achilles;</l>
		<l>the third is Pholus, he who was so frenzied.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And many thousands wheel around the moat,</l>
		<l>their arrows aimed at any soul that thrusts</l>
		<l>above the blood more than its guilt allots.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By now we had drawn near those agile beasts;</l>
		<l>Chiron drew out an arrow; with the notch,</l>
		<l>he parted his beard back upon his jaws.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When he&apos;d uncovered his enormous mouth,</l>
		<l>he said to his companions: &quot;Have you noticed</l>
		<l>how he who walks behind moves what he touches?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Dead soles are not accustomed to do that.&quot;</l>
		<l>And my good guide-now near the Centaur&apos;s chest,</l>
		<l>the place where his two natures met-replied:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;He is indeed alive, and so alone</l>
		<l>it falls to me to show him the dark valley.</l>
		<l>Necessity has brought him here, not pleasure.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For she who gave me this new task was one</l>
		<l>who had just come from singing halleluiah:</l>
		<l>he is no robber; I am not a thief.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But by the Power that permits my steps</l>
		<l>to journey on so wild a path, give us</l>
		<l>one of your band, to serve as our companion;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and let him show us where to ford the ditch,</l>
		<l>and let him bear this man upon his back,</l>
		<l>for he&apos;s no spirit who can fly through air.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then Chiron wheeled about and right and said</l>
		<l>to Nessus: &quot;Then, return and be their guide;</l>
		<l>if other troops disturb you, fend them off.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now, with our faithful escort, we advanced</l>
		<l>along the bloodred, boiling ditch&apos;s banks,</l>
		<l>beside the piercing cries of those who boiled.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw some who were sunk up to their brows,</l>
		<l>and that huge Centaur said: &quot;These are the tyrants</l>
		<l>who plunged their hands in blood and plundering.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here they lament their ruthless crimes; here are</l>
		<l>both Alexander and the fierce Dionysius,</l>
		<l>who brought such years of grief to Sicily.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That brow with hair so black is Ezzelino;</l>
		<l>that other there, the blonde one, is Obizzo</l>
		<l>of Este, he who was indeed undone,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>within the world above, by his fierce son.&quot;</l>
		<l>Then I turned to the poet, and he said:</l>
		<l>&quot;Now let him be your first guide, me your second.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A little farther on, the Centaur stopped</l>
		<l>above a group that seemed to rise above</l>
		<l>the boiling blood as far up as their throats.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He pointed out one shade, alone, apart,</l>
		<l>and said: &quot;Within God&apos;s bosom, he impaled</l>
		<l>the heart that still drips blood upon the Thames.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I caught sight of some who kept their heads</l>
		<l>and even their full chests above the tide;</l>
		<l>among them-many whom I recognized.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And so the blood grew always shallower</l>
		<l>until it only scorched the feet; and here</l>
		<l>we found a place where we could ford the ditch.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Just as you see that, on this side, the brook</l>
		<l>continually thins,&quot; the Centaur said,</l>
		<l>&quot;so I should have you know the rivulet,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>along the other side, will slowly deepen</l>
		<l>its bed, until it reaches once again</l>
		<l>the depth where tyranny must make lament.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there divine justice torments Attila</l>
		<l>he who was such a scourge upon the earth,</l>
		<l>and Pyrrhus, Sextus; to eternity</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>it milks the tears that boiling brook unlocks</l>
		<l>from Rinier of Corneto, Rinier Pazzo,</l>
		<l>those two who waged such war upon the highroads.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he turned round and crossed the ford again.</l>
	</p>
</page>
