<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>In that part of the young year when the sun</l>
		<l>begins to warm its locks beneath Aquarius</l>
		<l>and nights grow shorter, equaling the days,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when hoarfrost mimes the image of his white</l>
		<l>sister upon the ground-but not for long,</l>
		<l>because the pen he uses is not sharp-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the farmer who is short of fodder rises</l>
		<l>and looks and sees the fields all white, at which</l>
		<l>he slaps his thigh, turns back into the house,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and here and there complains like some poor wretch</l>
		<l>who doesn&apos;t know what can be done, and then</l>
		<l>goes out again and gathers up new hope</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>on seeing that the world has changed its face</l>
		<l>in so few hours, and he takes his staff</l>
		<l>and hurries out his flock of sheep to pasture.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So did my master fill me with dismay</l>
		<l>when I saw how his brow was deeply troubled,</l>
		<l>yet then the plaster soothed the sore as quickly:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for soon as we were on the broken bridge,</l>
		<l>my guide turned back to me with that sweet manner</l>
		<l>I first had seen along the mountain&apos;s base.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he examined carefully the ruin;</l>
		<l>then having picked the way we would ascend,</l>
		<l>he opened up his arms and thrust me forward.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as he who ponders as he labors,</l>
		<l>who&apos;s always ready for the step ahead,</l>
		<l>so, as he lifted me up toward the summit</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of one great crag, he&apos;d see another spur,</l>
		<l>saying: &quot;That is the one you will grip next,</l>
		<l>but try it first to see if it is firm.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That was no path for those with cloaks of lead,</l>
		<l>for he and I-he, light; I, with support-</l>
		<l>could hardly make it up from spur to spur.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And were it not that, down from this enclosure,</l>
		<l>the slope was shorter than the bank before,</l>
		<l>I cannot speak for him, but I should surely</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>have been defeated. But since Malebolge</l>
		<l>runs right into the mouth of its last well,</l>
		<l>the placement of each valley means it must</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>have one bank high and have the other short;</l>
		<l>and so we reached, at length, the jutting where</l>
		<l>the last stone of the ruined bridge breaks off.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The breath within my lungs was so exhausted</l>
		<l>from climbing, I could not go on; in fact,</l>
		<l>as soon as I had reached that stone, I sat.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Now you must cast aside your laziness,&quot;</l>
		<l>my master said, &quot;for he who rests on down</l>
		<l>or under covers cannot come to fame;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and he who spends his life without renown</l>
		<l>leaves such a vestige of himself on earth</l>
		<l>as smoke bequeaths to air or foam to water.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, get up; defeat your breathlessness</l>
		<l>with spirit that can win all battles if</l>
		<l>the body&apos;s heaviness does not deter it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A longer ladder still is to be climbed;</l>
		<l>it&apos;s not enough to have left them behind;</l>
		<l>if you have understood, now profit from it.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I arose and showed myself far better</l>
		<l>equipped with breath than I had been before:</l>
		<l>&quot;Go on, for I am strong and confident.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We took our upward way upon the ridge,</l>
		<l>with crags more jagged, narrow, difficult,</l>
		<l>and much more steep than we had crossed before.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I spoke as we went on, not to seem weak;</l>
		<l>at this, a voice came from the ditch beyond-</l>
		<l>a voice that was not suited to form words.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I know not what he said, although I was</l>
		<l>already at the summit of the bridge</l>
		<l>that crosses there; and yet he seemed to move.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I had bent downward, but my living eyes</l>
		<l>could not see to the bottom through that dark;</l>
		<l>at which I said: &quot;O master, can we reach</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the other belt? Let us descend the wall,</l>
		<l>for as I hear and cannot understand,</l>
		<l>so I see down but can distinguish nothing.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The only answer that I give to you</l>
		<l>is doing it,&quot; he said. &quot;A just request</l>
		<l>is to be met in silence, by the act.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We then climbed down the bridge, just at the end</l>
		<l>where it runs right into the eighth embankment,</l>
		<l>and now the moat was plain enough to me;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and there within I saw a dreadful swarm</l>
		<l>of serpents so extravagant in form-</l>
		<l>remembering them still drains my blood from me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Let Libya boast no more about her sands;</l>
		<l>for if she breeds chelydri, jaculi,</l>
		<l>cenchres with amphisbaena, pareae,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>she never showed-with all of Ethiopia</l>
		<l>or all the land that borders the Red Sea-</l>
		<l>so many, such malignant, pestilences.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Among this cruel and depressing swarm,</l>
		<l>ran people who were naked, terrified,</l>
		<l>with no hope of a hole or heliotrope.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Their hands were tied behind by serpents; these</l>
		<l>had thrust their head and tail right through the l</l>
		<l>and then were knotted on the other side.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And-there!-a serpent sprang with force at one</l>
		<l>who stood upon our shore, transfixing him</l>
		<l>just where the neck and shoulders form a knot.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No o or i has ever been transcribed</l>
		<l>so quickly as that soul caught fire and burned</l>
		<l>and, as he fell, completely turned to ashes;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and when he lay, undone, upon the ground,</l>
		<l>the dust of him collected by itself</l>
		<l>and instantly returned to what it was:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just so, it is asserted by great sages,</l>
		<l>that, when it reaches its five-hundredth year,</l>
		<l>the phoenix dies and then is born again;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>lifelong it never feeds on grass or grain,</l>
		<l>only on drops of incense and amomum;</l>
		<l>its final winding sheets are nard and myrrh.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as he who falls, and knows not how-</l>
		<l>by demon&apos;s force that drags him to the ground</l>
		<l>or by some other hindrance that binds man-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who, when he rises, stares about him, all</l>
		<l>bewildered by the heavy anguish he</l>
		<l>has suffered, sighing as he looks around;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did this sinner stare when he arose.</l>
		<l>Oh, how severe it is, the power of God</l>
		<l>that, as its vengeance, showers down such blows!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide then asked that sinner who he was;</l>
		<l>to this he answered: &quot;Not long since, I rained</l>
		<l>from Tuscany into this savage maw.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Mule that I was, the bestial life pleased me</l>
		<l>and not the human; I am Vanni Fucci,</l>
		<l>beast; and the den that suited me-Pistoia.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I to Virgil: &quot;Tell him not to slip</l>
		<l>away, and ask what sin has thrust him here;</l>
		<l>I knew him as a man of blood and anger.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The sinner heard and did not try to feign</l>
		<l>but turned his mind and face, intent, toward me;</l>
		<l>and coloring with miserable shame,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he said: &quot;I suffer more because you&apos;ve caught me</l>
		<l>in this, the misery you see, than I</l>
		<l>suffered when taken from the other life.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I can&apos;t refuse to answer what you ask:</l>
		<l>I am set down so far because I robbed</l>
		<l>the sacristy of its fair ornaments,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and someone else was falsely blamed for that.</l>
		<l>But lest this sight give you too much delight,</l>
		<l>if you can ever leave these lands of darkness,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>open your ears to my announcement, hear:</l>
		<l>Pistoia first will strip herself of Blacks,</l>
		<l>then Florence will renew her men and manners.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From Val di Magra, Mars will draw a vapor</l>
		<l>which turbid clouds will try to wrap; the clash</l>
		<l>between them will be fierce, impetuous,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a tempest, fought upon Campo Piceno,</l>
		<l>until that vapor, vigorous, shall crack</l>
		<l>the mist, and every White be struck by it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I have told you this to make you grieve.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
