<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The very tongue that first had wounded me,</l>
		<l>sending the color up in both my cheeks,</l>
		<l>was then to cure me with its medicine-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as did Achilles&apos; and his father&apos;s lance,</l>
		<l>even as I have heard, when it dispensed</l>
		<l>a sad stroke first and then a healing one.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We turned our backs upon that dismal valley</l>
		<l>by climbing up the bank that girdles it;</l>
		<l>we made our way across without a word.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here it was less than night and less than day,</l>
		<l>so that my sight could only move ahead</l>
		<l>slightly, but then I heard a bugle blast</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so strong, it would have made a thunder clap</l>
		<l>seem faint; at this, my eyes-which doubled back</l>
		<l>upon their path-turned fully toward one place.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Not even Roland&apos;s horn, which followed on</l>
		<l>the sad defeat when Charlemagne had lost</l>
		<l>his holy army, was as dread as this.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I&apos;d only turned my head there briefly when</l>
		<l>I seemed to make out many high towers; then</l>
		<l>I asked him: &quot;Master, tell me, what&apos;s this city?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;It is because you try</l>
		<l>to penetrate from far into these shadows</l>
		<l>that you have formed such faulty images.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When you have reached that place, you shall see clearly</l>
		<l>how much the distance has deceived your sense;</l>
		<l>and, therefore, let this spur you on your way.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then lovingly he took me by the hand</l>
		<l>and said: &quot;Before we have moved farther on,</l>
		<l>so that the fact may seem less strange to you,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I&apos;d have you know they are not towers, but giants,</l>
		<l>and from the navel downward, all of them</l>
		<l>are in the central pit, at the embankment</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as, whenever mists begin to thin,</l>
		<l>when, gradually, vision finds the form</l>
		<l>that in the vapor-thickened air was hidden,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so I pierced through the dense and darkened fog;</l>
		<l>as I drew always nearer to the shore,</l>
		<l>my error fled from me, my terror grew;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for as, on its round wall, Montereggioni</l>
		<l>is crowned with towers, so there towered here,</l>
		<l>above the bank that runs around the pit,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>with half their bulk, the terrifying giants,</l>
		<l>whom Jove still menaces from Heaven when</l>
		<l>he sends his bolts of thunder down upon them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I could now make out the face of one,</l>
		<l>his shoulders and his chest, much of his belly,</l>
		<l>and both his arms that hung along his sides.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Surely when she gave up the art of making</l>
		<l>such creatures, Nature acted well indeed,</l>
		<l>depriving Mars of instruments like these.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And if she still produces elephants</l>
		<l>and whales, whoever sees with subtlety</l>
		<l>holds her-for this- to be more just and prudent;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for where the mind&apos;s acutest reasoning</l>
		<l>is joined to evil will and evil power,</l>
		<l>there human beings can&apos;t defend themselves.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His face appeared to me as broad and long</l>
		<l>as Rome can claim for its St. Peter&apos;s pine cone;</l>
		<l>his other bones shared in that same proportion;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that the bank, which served him as an apron</l>
		<l>down from his middle, showed so much of him</l>
		<l>above, that three Frieslanders would in vain</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>have boasted of their reaching to his hair;</l>
		<l>for downward from the place where one would buckle</l>
		<l>a mantle, I saw thirty spans of him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Raphel mai amecche zabi almi,&quot;</l>
		<l>began to bellow that brute mouth, for which</l>
		<l>no sweeter psalms would be appropriate.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And my guide turned to him: &quot;O stupid soul,</l>
		<l>keep to your horn and use that as an outlet</l>
		<l>when rage or other passion touches you!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Look at your neck, and you will find the strap</l>
		<l>that holds it fast; and see, bewildered spirit,</l>
		<l>how it lies straight across your massive chest.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And then to me: &quot;He is his own accuser;</l>
		<l>for this is Nimrod, through whose wicked thought</l>
		<l>one single language cannot serve the world.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Leave him alone-let&apos;s not waste time in talk;</l>
		<l>for every language is to him the same</l>
		<l>as his to others-no one knows his tongue.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, turning to the left, we journeyed on</l>
		<l>and, at the distance of a bow-shot, found</l>
		<l>another giant, far more huge and fierce.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Who was the master who had tied him so,</l>
		<l>I cannot say, but his left arm was bent</l>
		<l>behind him and his right was bent in front,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>both pinioned by a chain that held him tight</l>
		<l>down from the neck; and round the part of him</l>
		<l>that was exposed, it had been wound five times.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;This giant in his arrogance had tested</l>
		<l>his force against the force of highest Jove,&quot;</l>
		<l>my guide said, &quot;so he merits this reward.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His name is Ephialtes; and he showed</l>
		<l>tremendous power when the giants frightened</l>
		<l>the gods; the arms he moved now move no more.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I to him: &quot;If it is possible,</l>
		<l>I&apos;d like my eyes to have experience</l>
		<l>of the enormous one, Briareus.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At which he answered: &quot;You shall see Antaeus</l>
		<l>nearby. He is unfettered and can speak;</l>
		<l>he&apos;ll take us to the bottom of all evil.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The one you wish to see lies far beyond</l>
		<l>and is bound up and just as huge as this one,</l>
		<l>and even more ferocious in his gaze.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No earthquake ever was so violent</l>
		<l>when called to shake a tower so robust,</l>
		<l>as Ephialtes quick to shake himself.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I was more afraid of death than ever;</l>
		<l>that fear would have been quite enough to kill me,</l>
		<l>had I not seen how he was held by chains.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And we continued on until we reached</l>
		<l>Antaeus, who, not reckoning his head,</l>
		<l>stood out out above the rock wall full five ells.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O you, who lived within the famous valley</l>
		<l>(where Scipio became the heir of glory</l>
		<l>when Hannibal retreated with his men),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who took a thousand lions as your prey-</l>
		<l>and had you been together with your brothers</l>
		<l>in their high war, it seems some still believe</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the sons of earth would have become the victors-</l>
		<l>do set us down below, where cold shuts in</l>
		<l>Cocytus, and do not disdain that task.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Don&apos;t send us on to Tityus or Typhon;</l>
		<l>this man can give you what is longed for here;</l>
		<l>therefore bend down and do not curl your lip.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He still can bring you fame within the world,</l>
		<l>for he&apos;s alive and still expects long life,</l>
		<l>unless grace summon him before his time.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So said my master; and in haste Antaeus</l>
		<l>stretched out his hands, whose massive grip had on</l>
		<l>been felt by Hercules, and grasped my guide.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And Virgil, when he felt himself caught up,</l>
		<l>called out to me: &quot;Come here, so l can hold you,&quot;</l>
		<l>then made one bundle of himself and me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as the Garisenda seems when seen</l>
		<l>beneath the leaning side, when clouds run past</l>
		<l>and it hangs down as if about to crash,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did Antaeus seem to me as I</l>
		<l>watched him bend over me-a moment when</l>
		<l>I&apos;d have preferred to take some other road.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But gently-on the deep that swallows up</l>
		<l>both Lucifer and Judas-he placed us;</l>
		<l>nor did he, so bent over, stay there long,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but, like a mast above a ship, he rose.</l>
	</p>
</page>
