<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Love of our native city overcame me;</l>
		<l>I gathered up the scattered boughs and gave</l>
		<l>them back to him whose voice was spent already.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From there we reached the boundary that divides</l>
		<l>the second from the third ring-and the sight</l>
		<l>of a dread work that justice had devised.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To make these strange things clear, I must explain</l>
		<l>that we had come upon an open plain</l>
		<l>that banishes all green things from its bed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The wood of sorrow is a garland round it,</l>
		<l>just as that wood is ringed by a sad channel;</l>
		<l>here, at the very edge, we stayed our steps.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The ground was made of sand, dry and compact,</l>
		<l>a sand not different in kind from that</l>
		<l>on which the feet of Cato had once tramped.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O vengeance of the Lord, how you should be</l>
		<l>dreaded by everyone who now can read</l>
		<l>whatever was made manifest to me!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw so many flocks of naked souls,</l>
		<l>all weeping miserably, and it seemed that</l>
		<l>they were ruled by different decrees.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Some lay upon the ground, flat on their backs;</l>
		<l>some huddled in a crouch, and there they sat;</l>
		<l>and others moved about incessantly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The largest group was those who walked about,</l>
		<l>the smallest, those supine in punishment;</l>
		<l>but these had looser tongues to tell their torment</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Above that plain of sand, distended flakes</l>
		<l>of fire showered down; their fall was slow-</l>
		<l>as snow descends on alps when no wind blows.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just like the flames that Alexander saw</l>
		<l>in India&apos;s hot zones, when fires fell,</l>
		<l>intact and to the ground, on his battalions,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for which-wisely-he had his soldiers tramp</l>
		<l>the soil to see that every fire was spent</l>
		<l>before new flames were added to the old;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did the never-ending heat descend;</l>
		<l>with this, the sand was kindled just as tinder</l>
		<l>on meeting flint will flame-doubling the pain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The dance of wretched hands was never done;</l>
		<l>now here, now there, they tried to beat aside</l>
		<l>the fresh flames as they fell. And I began</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to speak: &quot;My master, you who can defeat</l>
		<l>all things except for those tenacious demons</l>
		<l>who tried to block us at the entryway,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who is that giant there, who does not seem</l>
		<l>to heed the singeing-he who lies and scorns</l>
		<l>and scowls, he whom the rains can&apos;t seem to soften</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he himself, on noticing that I</l>
		<l>was querying my guide about him, cried:</l>
		<l>&quot;That which I was in life, I am in death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Though Jove wear out the smith from whom he took,</l>
		<l>in wrath, the keen-edged thunderbolt with which</l>
		<l>on my last day I was to be transfixed;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>or if he tire the others, one by one,</l>
		<l>in Mongibello, at the sooty forge,</l>
		<l>while bellowing: &apos;O help, good Vulcan, help!&apos;-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just as he did when there was war at Phlegra-</l>
		<l>and casts his shafts at me with all his force,</l>
		<l>not even then would he have happy vengeance.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then did my guide speak with such vehemence</l>
		<l>as I had never heard him use before:</l>
		<l>&quot;O Capaneus, for your arrogance</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that is not quenched, you&apos;re punished all the more</l>
		<l>no torture other than your own madness</l>
		<l>could offer pain enough to match your wrath.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But then, with gentler face he turned to me</l>
		<l>and said: &quot;That man was one of seven kings</l>
		<l>besieging Thebes; he held-and still, it seems,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>holds-God in great disdain, disprizing Him;</l>
		<l>but as I told him now, his maledictions</l>
		<l>sit well as ornaments upon his chest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now follow me and-take care-do not set</l>
		<l>your feet upon the sand that&apos;s burning hot,</l>
		<l>but always keep them back, close to the forest.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In silence we had reached a place where flowed</l>
		<l>a slender watercourse out of the wood-</l>
		<l>a stream whose redness makes me shudder still.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As from the Bulicame pours a brook</l>
		<l>whose waters then are shared by prostitutes,</l>
		<l>so did this stream run down across the sand.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Its bed and both its banks were made of stone,</l>
		<l>together with the slopes along its shores,</l>
		<l>so that I saw our passageway lay there.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Among all other things that I have shown you</l>
		<l>since we first made our way across the gate</l>
		<l>whose threshold is forbidden to no one,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>no thing has yet been witnessed by your eyes</l>
		<l>as notable as this red rivulet,</l>
		<l>which quenches every flame that burns above it.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These words were spoken by my guide; at this,</l>
		<l>I begged him to bestow the food for which</l>
		<l>he had already given me the craving.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;A devastated land lies in midsea,</l>
		<l>a land that is called Crete,&quot; he answered me.</l>
		<l>&quot;Under its king the world once lived chastely.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within that land there was a mountain blessed</l>
		<l>with leaves and waters, and they called it Ida;</l>
		<l>but it is withered now like some old thing.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It once was chosen as a trusted cradle</l>
		<l>by Rhea for her son; to hide him better,</l>
		<l>when he cried out, she had her servants clamor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within the mountain is a huge Old Man,</l>
		<l>who stands erect-his back turned toward Damietta-</l>
		<l>and looks at Rome as if it were his mirror.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The Old Man&apos;s head is fashioned of fine gold,</l>
		<l>the purest silver forms his arms and chest,</l>
		<l>but he is made of brass down to the cleft;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>below that point he is of choicest iron</l>
		<l>except for his right foot, made of baked clay;</l>
		<l>and he rests more on this than on the left.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Each part of him, except the gold, is cracked;</l>
		<l>and down that fissure there are tears that drip;</l>
		<l>when gathered, they pierce through that cavern&apos;s floor</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and, crossing rocks into this valley, form</l>
		<l>the Acheron and Styx and Phlegethon;</l>
		<l>and then they make their way down this tight channel</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and at the point past which there&apos;s no descent,</l>
		<l>they form Cocytus; since you are to see</l>
		<l>what that pool is, I&apos;ll not describe it here.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I asked him: &quot;But if the rivulet</l>
		<l>must follow such a course down from our world,</l>
		<l>why can we see it only at this boundary?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;You know this place is round;</l>
		<l>and though the way that you have come is long,</l>
		<l>and always toward the left and toward the bottom,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you still have not completed all the circle:</l>
		<l>so that, if something new appears to us,</l>
		<l>it need not bring such wonder to your face.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I again: &quot;Master, where&apos;s Phlegethon</l>
		<l>and where is Lethe? You omit the second</l>
		<l>and say this rain of tears has formed the first.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;I&apos;m pleased indeed,&quot; he said, &quot;with all your questions;</l>
		<l>yet one of them might well have found its answer</l>
		<l>already-when you saw the red stream boiling.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You shall see Lethe, but past this abyss,</l>
		<l>there where the spirits go to cleanse themselves</l>
		<l>when their repented guilt is set aside.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he declared: &quot;The time has come to quit</l>
		<l>this wood; see that you follow close behind me;</l>
		<l>these margins form a path that does not scorch,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and over them, all flaming vapor is quenched.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
