<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Pape Satan, Pape Satan, Aleppe!&quot;</l>
    <l>Thus Plutus with his clucking voice began;</l>
    <l>And that benignant Sage, who all things knew,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Said, to encourage me: &quot;Let not thy fear</l>
    <l>Harm thee; for any power that he may have</l>
    <l>Shall not prevent thy going down this crag.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he turned round unto that bloated lip,</l>
    <l>And said: &quot;Be silent, thou accursed wolf;</l>
    <l>Consume within thyself with thine own rage.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not causeless is this journey to the abyss;</l>
    <l>Thus is it willed on high, where Michael wrought</l>
    <l>Vengeance upon the proud adultery.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the sails inflated by the wind</l>
    <l>Involved together fall when snaps the mast,</l>
    <l>So fell the cruel monster to the earth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus we descended into the fourth chasm,</l>
    <l>Gaining still farther on the dolesome shore</l>
    <l>Which all the woe of the universe insacks.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Justice of God, ah! who heaps up so many</l>
    <l>New toils and sufferings as I beheld?</l>
    <l>And why doth our transgression waste us so?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As doth the billow there upon Charybdis,</l>
    <l>That breaks itself on that which it encounters,</l>
    <l>So here the folk must dance their roundelay.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here saw I people, more than elsewhere, many,</l>
    <l>On one side and the other, with great howls,</l>
    <l>Rolling weights forward by main force of chest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They clashed together, and then at that point</l>
    <l>Each one turned backward, rolling retrograde,</l>
    <l>Crying, &quot;Why keepest?&quot; and, &quot;Why squanderest thou?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus they returned along the lurid circle</l>
    <l>On either hand unto the opposite point,</l>
    <l>Shouting their shameful metre evermore.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then each, when he arrived there, wheeled about</l>
    <l>Through his half-circle to another joust;</l>
    <l>And I, who had my heart pierced as it were,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Exclaimed: &quot;My Master, now declare to me</l>
    <l>What people these are, and if all were clerks,</l>
    <l>These shaven crowns upon the left of us.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;All of them were asquint</l>
    <l>In intellect in the first life, so much</l>
    <l>That there with measure they no spending made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Clearly enough their voices bark it forth,</l>
    <l>Whene'er they reach the two points of the circle,</l>
    <l>Where sunders them the opposite defect.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Clerks those were who no hairy covering</l>
    <l>Have on the head, and Popes and Cardinals,</l>
    <l>In whom doth Avarice practise its excess.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;My Master, among such as these</l>
    <l>I ought forsooth to recognise some few,</l>
    <l>Who were infected with these maladies.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Vain thought thou entertainest;</l>
    <l>The undiscerning life which made them sordid</l>
    <l>Now makes them unto all discernment dim.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Forever shall they come to these two buttings;</l>
    <l>These from the sepulchre shall rise again</l>
    <l>With the fist closed, and these with tresses shorn.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ill giving and ill keeping the fair world</l>
    <l>Have ta'en from them, and placed them in this scuffle;</l>
    <l>Whate'er it be, no words adorn I for it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now canst thou, Son, behold the transient farce</l>
    <l>Of goods that are committed unto Fortune,</l>
    <l>For which the human race each other buffet;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For all the gold that is beneath the moon,</l>
    <l>Or ever has been, of these weary souls</l>
    <l>Could never make a single one repose.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Master,&quot; I said to him, &quot;now tell me also</l>
    <l>What is this Fortune which thou speakest of,</l>
    <l>That has the world's goods so within its clutches?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;O creatures imbecile,</l>
    <l>What ignorance is this which doth beset you?</l>
    <l>Now will I have thee learn my judgment of her.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He whose omniscience everything transcends</l>
    <l>The heavens created, and gave who should guide them,</l>
    <l>That every part to every part may shine,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Distributing the light in equal measure;</l>
    <l>He in like manner to the mundane splendours</l>
    <l>Ordained a general ministress and guide,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That she might change at times the empty treasures</l>
    <l>From race to race, from one blood to another,</l>
    <l>Beyond resistance of all human wisdom.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore one people triumphs, and another</l>
    <l>Languishes, in pursuance of her judgment,</l>
    <l>Which hidden is, as in the grass a serpent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Your knowledge has no counterstand against her;</l>
    <l>She makes provision, judges, and pursues</l>
    <l>Her governance, as theirs the other gods.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Her permutations have not any truce;</l>
    <l>Necessity makes her precipitate,</l>
    <l>So often cometh who his turn obtains.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And this is she who is so crucified</l>
    <l>Even by those who ought to give her praise,</l>
    <l>Giving her blame amiss, and bad repute.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But she is blissful, and she hears it not;</l>
    <l>Among the other primal creatures gladsome</l>
    <l>She turns her sphere, and blissful she rejoices.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Let us descend now unto greater woe;</l>
    <l>Already sinks each star that was ascending</l>
    <l>When I set out, and loitering is forbidden.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We crossed the circle to the other bank,</l>
    <l>Near to a fount that boils, and pours itself</l>
    <l>Along a gully that runs out of it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The water was more sombre far than perse;</l>
    <l>And we, in company with the dusky waves,</l>
    <l>Made entrance downward by a path uncouth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A marsh it makes, which has the name of Styx,</l>
    <l>This tristful brooklet, when it has descended</l>
    <l>Down to the foot of the malign gray shores.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I, who stood intent upon beholding,</l>
    <l>Saw people mud-besprent in that lagoon,</l>
    <l>All of them naked and with angry look.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They smote each other not alone with hands,</l>
    <l>But with the head and with the breast and feet,</l>
    <l>Tearing each other piecemeal with their teeth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Said the good Master: &quot;Son, thou now beholdest</l>
    <l>The souls of those whom anger overcame;</l>
    <l>And likewise I would have thee know for certain</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Beneath the water people are who sigh</l>
    <l>And make this water bubble at the surface,</l>
    <l>As the eye tells thee wheresoe'er it turns.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Fixed in the mire they say, 'We sullen were</l>
    <l>In the sweet air, which by the sun is gladdened,</l>
    <l>Bearing within ourselves the sluggish reek;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now we are sullen in this sable mire.'</l>
    <l>This hymn do they keep gurgling in their throats,</l>
    <l>For with unbroken words they cannot say it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus we went circling round the filthy fen</l>
    <l>A great arc 'twixt the dry bank and the swamp,</l>
    <l>With eyes turned unto those who gorge the mire;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unto the foot of a tower we came at last.</l>
  </p>
</page>