<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>At the return of consciousness, that closed</l>
    <l>Before the pity of those two relations,</l>
    <l>Which utterly with sadness had confused me,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>New torments I behold, and new tormented</l>
    <l>Around me, whichsoever way I move,</l>
    <l>And whichsoever way I turn, and gaze.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In the third circle am I of the rain</l>
    <l>Eternal, maledict, and cold, and heavy;</l>
    <l>Its law and quality are never new.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Huge hail, and water sombre-hued, and snow,</l>
    <l>Athwart the tenebrous air pour down amain;</l>
    <l>Noisome the earth is, that receiveth this.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Cerberus, monster cruel and uncouth,</l>
    <l>With his three gullets like a dog is barking</l>
    <l>Over the people that are there submerged.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Red eyes he has, and unctuous beard and black,</l>
    <l>And belly large, and armed with claws his hands;</l>
    <l>He rends the spirits, flays, and quarters them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Howl the rain maketh them like unto dogs;</l>
    <l>One side they make a shelter for the other;</l>
    <l>Oft turn themselves the wretched reprobates.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When Cerberus perceived us, the great worm!</l>
    <l>His mouths he opened, and displayed his tusks;</l>
    <l>Not a limb had he that was motionless.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And my Conductor, with his spans extended,</l>
    <l>Took of the earth, and with his fists well filled,</l>
    <l>He threw it into those rapacious gullets.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Such as that dog is, who by barking craves,</l>
    <l>And quiet grows soon as his food he gnaws,</l>
    <l>For to devour it he but thinks and struggles,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The like became those muzzles filth-begrimed</l>
    <l>Of Cerberus the demon, who so thunders</l>
    <l>Over the souls that they would fain be deaf.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We passed across the shadows, which subdues</l>
    <l>The heavy rain-storm, and we placed our feet</l>
    <l>Upon their vanity that person seems.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They all were lying prone upon the earth,</l>
    <l>Excepting one, who sat upright as soon</l>
    <l>As he beheld us passing on before him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O thou that art conducted through this Hell,&quot;</l>
    <l>He said to me, &quot;recall me, if thou canst;</l>
    <l>Thyself wast made before I was unmade.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;The anguish which thou hast</l>
    <l>Perhaps doth draw thee out of my remembrance,</l>
    <l>So that it seems not I have ever seen thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me who thou art, that in so doleful</l>
    <l>A place art put, and in such punishment,</l>
    <l>If some are greater, none is so displeasing.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Thy city, which is full</l>
    <l>Of envy so that now the sack runs over,</l>
    <l>Held me within it in the life serene.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>You citizens were wont to call me Ciacco;</l>
    <l>For the pernicious sin of gluttony</l>
    <l>I, as thou seest, am battered by this rain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I, sad soul, am not the only one,</l>
    <l>For all these suffer the like penalty</l>
    <l>For the like sin;&quot; and word no more spake he.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I answered him: &quot;Ciacco, thy wretchedness</l>
    <l>Weighs on me so that it to weep invites me;</l>
    <l>But tell me, if thou knowest, to what shall come</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The citizens of the divided city;</l>
    <l>If any there be just; and the occasion</l>
    <l>Tell me why so much discord has assailed it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;They, after long contention,</l>
    <l>Will come to bloodshed; and the rustic party</l>
    <l>Will drive the other out with much offence.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then afterwards behoves it this one fall</l>
    <l>Within three suns, and rise again the other</l>
    <l>By force of him who now is on the coast.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>High will it hold its forehead a long while,</l>
    <l>Keeping the other under heavy burdens,</l>
    <l>Howe'er it weeps thereat and is indignant.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The just are two, and are not understood there;</l>
    <l>Envy and Arrogance and Avarice</l>
    <l>Are the three sparks that have all hearts enkindled.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here ended he his tearful utterance;</l>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;I wish thee still to teach me,</l>
    <l>And make a gift to me of further speech.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Farinata and Tegghiaio, once so worthy,</l>
    <l>Jacopo Rusticucci, Arrigo, and Mosca,</l>
    <l>And others who on good deeds set their thoughts,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Say where they are, and cause that I may know them;</l>
    <l>For great desire constraineth me to learn</l>
    <l>If Heaven doth sweeten them, or Hell envenom.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he: &quot;They are among the blacker souls;</l>
    <l>A different sin downweighs them to the bottom;</l>
    <l>If thou so far descendest, thou canst see them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But when thou art again in the sweet world,</l>
    <l>I pray thee to the mind of others bring me;</l>
    <l>No more I tell thee and no more I answer.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then his straightforward eyes he turned askance,</l>
    <l>Eyed me a little, and then bowed his head;</l>
    <l>He fell therewith prone like the other blind.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the Guide said to me: &quot;He wakes no more</l>
    <l>This side the sound of the angelic trumpet;</l>
    <l>When shall approach the hostile Potentate,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Each one shall find again his dismal tomb,</l>
    <l>Shall reassume his flesh and his own figure,</l>
    <l>Shall hear what through eternity re-echoes.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So we passed onward o'er the filthy mixture</l>
    <l>Of shadows and of rain with footsteps slow,</l>
    <l>Touching a little on the future life.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wherefore I said: &quot;Master, these torments here,</l>
    <l>Will they increase after the mighty sentence,</l>
    <l>Or lesser be, or will they be as burning?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Return unto thy science,</l>
    <l>Which wills, that as the thing more perfect is,</l>
    <l>The more it feels of pleasure and of pain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Albeit that this people maledict</l>
    <l>To true perfection never can attain,</l>
    <l>Hereafter more than now they look to be.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Round in a circle by that road we went,</l>
    <l>Speaking much more, which I do not repeat;</l>
    <l>We came unto the point where the descent is;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There we found Plutus the great enemy.</l>
  </p>
</page>