<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>One and the selfsame tongue first wounded me,</l>
    <l>So that it tinged the one cheek and the other,</l>
    <l>And then held out to me the medicine;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus do I hear that once Achilles' spear,</l>
    <l>His and his father's, used to be the cause</l>
    <l>First of a sad and then a gracious boon.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We turned our backs upon the wretched valley,</l>
    <l>Upon the bank that girds it round about,</l>
    <l>Going across it without any speech.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There it was less than night, and less than day,</l>
    <l>So that my sight went little in advance;</l>
    <l>But I could hear the blare of a loud horn,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So loud it would have made each thunder faint,</l>
    <l>Which, counter to it following its way,</l>
    <l>Mine eyes directed wholly to one place.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After the dolorous discomfiture</l>
    <l>When Charlemagne the holy emprise lost,</l>
    <l>So terribly Orlando sounded not.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Short while my head turned thitherward I held</l>
    <l>When many lofty towers I seemed to see,</l>
    <l>Whereat I: &quot;Master, say, what town is this?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Because thou peerest forth</l>
    <l>Athwart the darkness at too great a distance,</l>
    <l>It happens that thou errest in thy fancy.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well shalt thou see, if thou arrivest there,</l>
    <l>How much the sense deceives itself by distance;</l>
    <l>Therefore a little faster spur thee on.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then tenderly he took me by the hand,</l>
    <l>And said: &quot;Before we farther have advanced,</l>
    <l>That the reality may seem to thee</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Less strange, know that these are not towers, but giants,</l>
    <l>And they are in the well, around the bank,</l>
    <l>From navel downward, one and all of them.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As, when the fog is vanishing away,</l>
    <l>Little by little doth the sight refigure</l>
    <l>Whate'er the mist that crowds the air conceals,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So, piercing through the dense and darksome air,</l>
    <l>More and more near approaching tow'rd the verge,</l>
    <l>My error fled, and fear came over me;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because as on its circular parapets</l>
    <l>Montereggione crowns itself with towers,</l>
    <l>E'en thus the margin which surrounds the well</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With one half of their bodies turreted</l>
    <l>The horrible giants, whom Jove menaces</l>
    <l>E'en now from out the heavens when he thunders.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I of one already saw the face,</l>
    <l>Shoulders, and breast, and great part of the belly,</l>
    <l>And down along his sides both of the arms.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Certainly Nature, when she left the making</l>
    <l>Of animals like these, did well indeed,</l>
    <l>By taking such executors from Mars;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if of elephants and whales she doth not</l>
    <l>Repent her, whosoever looketh subtly</l>
    <l>More just and more discreet will hold her for it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For where the argument of intellect</l>
    <l>Is added unto evil will and power,</l>
    <l>No rampart can the people make against it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>His face appeared to me as long and large</l>
    <l>As is at Rome the pine-cone of Saint Peter's,</l>
    <l>And in proportion were the other bones;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that the margin, which an apron was</l>
    <l>Down from the middle, showed so much of him</l>
    <l>Above it, that to reach up to his hair</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Three Frieslanders in vain had vaunted them;</l>
    <l>For I beheld thirty great palms of him</l>
    <l>Down from the place where man his mantle buckles.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Raphael mai amech izabi almi,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began to clamour the ferocious mouth,</l>
    <l>To which were not befitting sweeter psalms.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And unto him my Guide: &quot;Soul idiotic,</l>
    <l>Keep to thy horn, and vent thyself with that,</l>
    <l>When wrath or other passion touches thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Search round thy neck, and thou wilt find the belt</l>
    <l>Which keeps it fastened, O bewildered soul,</l>
    <l>And see it, where it bars thy mighty breast.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then said to me: &quot;He doth himself accuse;</l>
    <l>This one is Nimrod, by whose evil thought</l>
    <l>One language in the world is not still used.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here let us leave him and not speak in vain;</l>
    <l>For even such to him is every language</l>
    <l>As his to others, which to none is known.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore a longer journey did we make,</l>
    <l>Turned to the left, and a crossbow-shot oft</l>
    <l>We found another far more fierce and large.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In binding him, who might the master be</l>
    <l>I cannot say; but he had pinioned close</l>
    <l>Behind the right arm, and in front the other,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With chains, that held him so begirt about</l>
    <l>From the neck down, that on the part uncovered</l>
    <l>It wound itself as far as the fifth gyre.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;This proud one wished to make experiment</l>
    <l>Of his own power against the Supreme Jove,&quot;</l>
    <l>My Leader said, &quot;whence he has such a guerdon.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ephialtes is his name; he showed great prowess.</l>
    <l>What time the giants terrified the gods;</l>
    <l>The arms he wielded never more he moves.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;If possible, I should wish</l>
    <l>That of the measureless Briareus</l>
    <l>These eyes of mine might have experience.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence he replied: &quot;Thou shalt behold Antaeus</l>
    <l>Close by here, who can speak and is unbound,</l>
    <l>Who at the bottom of all crime shall place us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Much farther yon is he whom thou wouldst see,</l>
    <l>And he is bound, and fashioned like to this one,</l>
    <l>Save that he seems in aspect more ferocious.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There never was an earthquake of such might</l>
    <l>That it could shake a tower so violently,</l>
    <l>As Ephialtes suddenly shook himself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then was I more afraid of death than ever,</l>
    <l>For nothing more was needful than the fear,</l>
    <l>If I had not beheld the manacles.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then we proceeded farther in advance,</l>
    <l>And to Antaeus came, who, full five ells</l>
    <l>Without the head, forth issued from the cavern.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O thou, who in the valley fortunate,</l>
    <l>Which Scipio the heir of glory made,</l>
    <l>When Hannibal turned back with all his hosts,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Once brought'st a thousand lions for thy prey,</l>
    <l>And who, hadst thou been at the mighty war</l>
    <l>Among thy brothers, some it seems still think</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The sons of Earth the victory would have gained:</l>
    <l>Place us below, nor be disdainful of it,</l>
    <l>There where the cold doth lock Cocytus up.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Make us not go to Tityus nor Typhoeus;</l>
    <l>This one can give of that which here is longed for;</l>
    <l>Therefore stoop down, and do not curl thy lip.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Still in the world can he restore thy fame;</l>
    <l>Because he lives, and still expects long life,</l>
    <l>If to itself Grace call him not untimely.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So said the Master; and in haste the other</l>
    <l>His hands extended and took up my Guide,--</l>
    <l>Hands whose great pressure Hercules once felt.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Virgilius, when he felt himself embraced,</l>
    <l>Said unto me: &quot;Draw nigh, that I may take thee;&quot;</l>
    <l>Then of himself and me one bundle made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As seems the Carisenda, to behold</l>
    <l>Beneath the leaning side, when goes a cloud</l>
    <l>Above it so that opposite it hangs;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Such did Antaeus seem to me, who stood</l>
    <l>Watching to see him stoop, and then it was</l>
    <l>I could have wished to go some other way.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But lightly in the abyss, which swallows up</l>
    <l>Judas with Lucifer, he put us down;</l>
    <l>Nor thus bowed downward made he there delay,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But, as a mast does in a ship, uprose.</l>
  </p>
</page>