<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Now was I where was heard the reverberation</l>
    <l>Of water falling into the next round,</l>
    <l>Like to that humming which the beehives make,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When shadows three together started forth,</l>
    <l>Running, from out a company that passed</l>
    <l>Beneath the rain of the sharp martyrdom.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Towards us came they, and each one cried out:</l>
    <l>&quot;Stop, thou; for by thy garb to us thou seemest</l>
    <l>To be some one of our depraved city.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah me! what wounds I saw upon their limbs,</l>
    <l>Recent and ancient by the flames burnt in!</l>
    <l>It pains me still but to remember it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unto their cries my Teacher paused attentive;</l>
    <l>He turned his face towards me, and &quot;Now wait,&quot;</l>
    <l>He said; &quot;to these we should be courteous.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if it were not for the fire that darts</l>
    <l>The nature of this region, I should say</l>
    <l>That haste were more becoming thee than them.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as we stood still, they recommenced</l>
    <l>The old refrain, and when they overtook us,</l>
    <l>Formed of themselves a wheel, all three of them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As champions stripped and oiled are wont to do,</l>
    <l>Watching for their advantage and their hold,</l>
    <l>Before they come to blows and thrusts between them,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus, wheeling round, did every one his visage</l>
    <l>Direct to me, so that in opposite wise</l>
    <l>His neck and feet continual journey made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And, &quot;If the misery of this soft place</l>
    <l>Bring in disdain ourselves and our entreaties,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began one, &quot;and our aspect black and blistered,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Let the renown of us thy mind incline</l>
    <l>To tell us who thou art, who thus securely</l>
    <l>Thy living feet dost move along through Hell.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He in whose footprints thou dost see me treading,</l>
    <l>Naked and skinless though he now may go,</l>
    <l>Was of a greater rank than thou dost think;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He was the grandson of the good Gualdrada;</l>
    <l>His name was Guidoguerra, and in life</l>
    <l>Much did he with his wisdom and his sword.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other, who close by me treads the sand,</l>
    <l>Tegghiaio Aldobrandi is, whose fame</l>
    <l>Above there in the world should welcome be.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I, who with them on the cross am placed,</l>
    <l>Jacopo Rusticucci was; and truly</l>
    <l>My savage wife, more than aught else, doth harm me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Could I have been protected from the fire,</l>
    <l>Below I should have thrown myself among them,</l>
    <l>And think the Teacher would have suffered it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But as I should have burned and baked myself,</l>
    <l>My terror overmastered my good will,</l>
    <l>Which made me greedy of embracing them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then I began: &quot;Sorrow and not disdain</l>
    <l>Did your condition fix within me so,</l>
    <l>That tardily it wholly is stripped off,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as this my Lord said unto me</l>
    <l>Words, on account of which I thought within me</l>
    <l>That people such as you are were approaching.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I of your city am; and evermore</l>
    <l>Your labours and your honourable names</l>
    <l>I with affection have retraced and heard.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I leave the gall, and go for the sweet fruits</l>
    <l>Promised to me by the veracious Leader;</l>
    <l>But to the centre first I needs must plunge.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;So may the soul for a long while conduct</l>
    <l>Those limbs of thine,&quot; did he make answer then,</l>
    <l>&quot;And so may thy renown shine after thee,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Valour and courtesy, say if they dwell</l>
    <l>Within our city, as they used to do,</l>
    <l>Or if they wholly have gone out of it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For Guglielmo Borsier, who is in torment</l>
    <l>With us of late, and goes there with his comrades,</l>
    <l>Doth greatly mortify us with his words.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;The new inhabitants and the sudden gains,</l>
    <l>Pride and extravagance have in thee engendered,</l>
    <l>Florence, so that thou weep'st thereat already!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In this wise I exclaimed with face uplifted;</l>
    <l>And the three, taking that for my reply,</l>
    <l>Looked at each other, as one looks at truth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;If other times so little it doth cost thee,&quot;</l>
    <l>Replied they all, &quot;to satisfy another,</l>
    <l>Happy art thou, thus speaking at thy will!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore, if thou escape from these dark places,</l>
    <l>And come to rebehold the beauteous stars,</l>
    <l>When it shall pleasure thee to say, 'I was,'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>See that thou speak of us unto the people.&quot;</l>
    <l>Then they broke up the wheel, and in their flight</l>
    <l>It seemed as if their agile legs were wings.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not an Amen could possibly be said</l>
    <l>So rapidly as they had disappeared;</l>
    <l>Wherefore the Master deemed best to depart.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I followed him, and little had we gone,</l>
    <l>Before the sound of water was so near us,</l>
    <l>That speaking we should hardly have been heard.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as that stream which holdeth its own course</l>
    <l>The first from Monte Veso tow'rds the East,</l>
    <l>Upon the left-hand slope of Apennine,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Which is above called Acquacheta, ere</l>
    <l>It down descendeth into its low bed,</l>
    <l>And at Forli is vacant of that name,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Reverberates there above San Benedetto</l>
    <l>From Alps, by falling at a single leap,</l>
    <l>Where for a thousand there were room enough;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus downward from a bank precipitate,</l>
    <l>We found resounding that dark-tinted water,</l>
    <l>So that it soon the ear would have offended.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I had a cord around about me girt,</l>
    <l>And therewithal I whilom had designed</l>
    <l>To take the panther with the painted skin.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After I this had all from me unloosed,</l>
    <l>As my Conductor had commanded me,</l>
    <l>I reached it to him, gathered up and coiled,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whereat he turned himself to the right side,</l>
    <l>And at a little distance from the verge,</l>
    <l>He cast it down into that deep abyss.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;It must needs be some novelty respond,&quot;</l>
    <l>I said within myself, &quot;to the new signal</l>
    <l>The Master with his eye is following so.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah me! how very cautious men should be</l>
    <l>With those who not alone behold the act,</l>
    <l>But with their wisdom look into the thoughts!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He said to me: &quot;Soon there will upward come</l>
    <l>What I await; and what thy thought is dreaming</l>
    <l>Must soon reveal itself unto thy sight.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Aye to that truth which has the face of falsehood,</l>
    <l>A man should close his lips as far as may be,</l>
    <l>Because without his fault it causes shame;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But here I cannot; and, Reader, by the notes</l>
    <l>Of this my Comedy to thee I swear,</l>
    <l>So may they not be void of lasting favour,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Athwart that dense and darksome atmosphere</l>
    <l>I saw a figure swimming upward come,</l>
    <l>Marvellous unto every steadfast heart,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as he returns who goeth down</l>
    <l>Sometimes to clear an anchor, which has grappled</l>
    <l>Reef, or aught else that in the sea is hidden,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Who upward stretches, and draws in his feet.</l>
  </p>
</page>