<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Now bears us onward one of the hard margins,</l>
    <l>And so the brooklet's mist o'ershadows it,</l>
    <l>From fire it saves the water and the dikes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the Flemings, 'twixt Cadsand and Bruges,</l>
    <l>Fearing the flood that tow'rds them hurls itself,</l>
    <l>Their bulwarks build to put the sea to flight;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as the Paduans along the Brenta,</l>
    <l>To guard their villas and their villages,</l>
    <l>Or ever Chiarentana feel the heat;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In such similitude had those been made,</l>
    <l>Albeit not so lofty nor so thick,</l>
    <l>Whoever he might be, the master made them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now were we from the forest so remote,</l>
    <l>I could not have discovered where it was,</l>
    <l>Even if backward I had turned myself,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When we a company of souls encountered,</l>
    <l>Who came beside the dike, and every one</l>
    <l>Gazed at us, as at evening we are wont</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To eye each other under a new moon,</l>
    <l>And so towards us sharpened they their brows</l>
    <l>As an old tailor at the needle's eye.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus scrutinised by such a family,</l>
    <l>By some one I was recognised, who seized</l>
    <l>My garment's hem, and cried out, &quot;What a marvel!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I, when he stretched forth his arm to me,</l>
    <l>On his baked aspect fastened so mine eyes,</l>
    <l>That the scorched countenance prevented not</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>His recognition by my intellect;</l>
    <l>And bowing down my face unto his own,</l>
    <l>I made reply, &quot;Are you here, Ser Brunetto?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he: &quot;May't not displease thee, O my son,</l>
    <l>If a brief space with thee Brunetto Latini</l>
    <l>Backward return and let the trail go on.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I said to him: &quot;With all my power I ask it;</l>
    <l>And if you wish me to sit down with you,</l>
    <l>I will, if he please, for I go with him.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O son,&quot; he said, &quot;whoever of this herd</l>
    <l>A moment stops, lies then a hundred years,</l>
    <l>Nor fans himself when smiteth him the fire.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore go on; I at thy skirts will come,</l>
    <l>And afterward will I rejoin my band,</l>
    <l>Which goes lamenting its eternal doom.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I did not dare to go down from the road</l>
    <l>Level to walk with him; but my head bowed</l>
    <l>I held as one who goeth reverently.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he began: &quot;What fortune or what fate</l>
    <l>Before the last day leadeth thee down here?</l>
    <l>And who is this that showeth thee the way?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Up there above us in the life serene,&quot;</l>
    <l>I answered him, &quot;I lost me in a valley,</l>
    <l>Or ever yet my age had been completed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But yestermorn I turned my back upon it;</l>
    <l>This one appeared to me, returning thither,</l>
    <l>And homeward leadeth me along this road.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;If thou thy star do follow,</l>
    <l>Thou canst not fail thee of a glorious port,</l>
    <l>If well I judged in the life beautiful.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if I had not died so prematurely,</l>
    <l>Seeing Heaven thus benignant unto thee,</l>
    <l>I would have given thee comfort in the work.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But that ungrateful and malignant people,</l>
    <l>Which of old time from Fesole descended,</l>
    <l>And smacks still of the mountain and the granite,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Will make itself, for thy good deeds, thy foe;</l>
    <l>And it is right; for among crabbed sorbs</l>
    <l>It ill befits the sweet fig to bear fruit.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Old rumour in the world proclaims them blind;</l>
    <l>A people avaricious, envious, proud;</l>
    <l>Take heed that of their customs thou do cleanse thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thy fortune so much honour doth reserve thee,</l>
    <l>One party and the other shall be hungry</l>
    <l>For thee; but far from goat shall be the grass.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Their litter let the beasts of Fesole</l>
    <l>Make of themselves, nor let them touch the plant,</l>
    <l>If any still upon their dunghill rise,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In which may yet revive the consecrated</l>
    <l>Seed of those Romans, who remained there when</l>
    <l>The nest of such great malice it became.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;If my entreaty wholly were fulfilled,&quot;</l>
    <l>Replied I to him, &quot;not yet would you be</l>
    <l>In banishment from human nature placed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For in my mind is fixed, and touches now</l>
    <l>My heart the dear and good paternal image</l>
    <l>Of you, when in the world from hour to hour</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>You taught me how a man becomes eternal;</l>
    <l>And how much I am grateful, while I live</l>
    <l>Behoves that in my language be discerned.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What you narrate of my career I write,</l>
    <l>And keep it to be glossed with other text</l>
    <l>By a Lady who can do it, if I reach her.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This much will I have manifest to you;</l>
    <l>Provided that my conscience do not chide me,</l>
    <l>For whatsoever Fortune I am ready.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Such handsel is not new unto mine ears;</l>
    <l>Therefore let Fortune turn her wheel around</l>
    <l>As it may please her, and the churl his mattock.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Master thereupon on his right cheek</l>
    <l>Did backward turn himself, and looked at me;</l>
    <l>Then said: &quot;He listeneth well who noteth it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor speaking less on that account, I go</l>
    <l>With Ser Brunetto, and I ask who are</l>
    <l>His most known and most eminent companions.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;To know of some is well;</l>
    <l>Of others it were laudable to be silent,</l>
    <l>For short would be the time for so much speech.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Know them in sum, that all of them were clerks,</l>
    <l>And men of letters great and of great fame,</l>
    <l>In the world tainted with the selfsame sin.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Priscian goes yonder with that wretched crowd,</l>
    <l>And Francis of Accorso; and thou hadst seen there</l>
    <l>If thou hadst had a hankering for such scurf,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That one, who by the Servant of the Servants</l>
    <l>From Arno was transferred to Bacchiglione,</l>
    <l>Where he has left his sin-excited nerves.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>More would I say, but coming and discoursing</l>
    <l>Can be no longer; for that I behold</l>
    <l>New smoke uprising yonder from the sand.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A people comes with whom I may not be;</l>
    <l>Commended unto thee be my Tesoro,</l>
    <l>In which I still live, and no more I ask.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he turned round, and seemed to be of those</l>
    <l>Who at Verona run for the Green Mantle</l>
    <l>Across the plain; and seemed to be among them</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The one who wins, and not the one who loses.</l>
  </p>
</page>