<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Silent, alone, and without company</l>
    <l>We went, the one in front, the other after,</l>
    <l>As go the Minor Friars along their way.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Upon the fable of Aesop was directed</l>
    <l>My thought, by reason of the present quarrel,</l>
    <l>Where he has spoken of the frog and mouse;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For 'mo' and 'issa' are not more alike</l>
    <l>Than this one is to that, if well we couple</l>
    <l>End and beginning with a steadfast mind.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as one thought from another springs,</l>
    <l>So afterward from that was born another,</l>
    <l>Which the first fear within me double made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus did I ponder: &quot;These on our account</l>
    <l>Are laughed to scorn, with injury and scoff</l>
    <l>So great, that much I think it must annoy them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If anger be engrafted on ill-will,</l>
    <l>They will come after us more merciless</l>
    <l>Than dog upon the leveret which he seizes,&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I felt my hair stand all on end already</l>
    <l>With terror, and stood backwardly intent,</l>
    <l>When said I: &quot;Master, if thou hidest not</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thyself and me forthwith, of Malebranche</l>
    <l>I am in dread; we have them now behind us;</l>
    <l>I so imagine them, I already feel them.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he: &quot;If I were made of leaded glass,</l>
    <l>Thine outward image I should not attract</l>
    <l>Sooner to me than I imprint the inner.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Just now thy thoughts came in among my own,</l>
    <l>With similar attitude and similar face,</l>
    <l>So that of both one counsel sole I made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If peradventure the right bank so slope</l>
    <l>That we to the next Bolgia can descend,</l>
    <l>We shall escape from the imagined chase.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not yet he finished rendering such opinion,</l>
    <l>When I beheld them come with outstretched wings,</l>
    <l>Not far remote, with will to seize upon us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Leader on a sudden seized me up,</l>
    <l>Even as a mother who by noise is wakened,</l>
    <l>And close beside her sees the enkindled flames,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Who takes her son, and flies, and does not stop,</l>
    <l>Having more care of him than of herself,</l>
    <l>So that she clothes her only with a shift;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And downward from the top of the hard bank</l>
    <l>Supine he gave him to the pendent rock,</l>
    <l>That one side of the other Bolgia walls.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ne'er ran so swiftly water through a sluice</l>
    <l>To turn the wheel of any land-built mill,</l>
    <l>When nearest to the paddles it approaches,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As did my Master down along that border,</l>
    <l>Bearing me with him on his breast away,</l>
    <l>As his own son, and not as a companion.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hardly the bed of the ravine below</l>
    <l>His feet had reached, ere they had reached the hill</l>
    <l>Right over us; but he was not afraid;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For the high Providence, which had ordained</l>
    <l>To place them ministers of the fifth moat,</l>
    <l>The power of thence departing took from all.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A painted people there below we found,</l>
    <l>Who went about with footsteps very slow,</l>
    <l>Weeping and in their semblance tired and vanquished.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They had on mantles with the hoods low down</l>
    <l>Before their eyes, and fashioned of the cut</l>
    <l>That in Cologne they for the monks are made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Without, they gilded are so that it dazzles;</l>
    <l>But inwardly all leaden and so heavy</l>
    <l>That Frederick used to put them on of straw.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O everlastingly fatiguing mantle!</l>
    <l>Again we turned us, still to the left hand</l>
    <l>Along with them, intent on their sad plaint;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But owing to the weight, that weary folk</l>
    <l>Came on so tardily, that we were new</l>
    <l>In company at each motion of the haunch.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence I unto my Leader: &quot;See thou find</l>
    <l>Some one who may by deed or name be known,</l>
    <l>And thus in going move thine eye about.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one, who understood the Tuscan speech,</l>
    <l>Cried to us from behind: &quot;Stay ye your feet,</l>
    <l>Ye, who so run athwart the dusky air!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Perhaps thou'lt have from me what thou demandest.&quot;</l>
    <l>Whereat the Leader turned him, and said: &quot;Wait,</l>
    <l>And then according to his pace proceed.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I stopped, and two beheld I show great haste</l>
    <l>Of spirit, in their faces, to be with me;</l>
    <l>But the burden and the narrow way delayed them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When they came up, long with an eye askance</l>
    <l>They scanned me without uttering a word.</l>
    <l>Then to each other turned, and said together:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;He by the action of his throat seems living;</l>
    <l>And if they dead are, by what privilege</l>
    <l>Go they uncovered by the heavy stole?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then said to me: &quot;Tuscan, who to the college</l>
    <l>Of miserable hypocrites art come,</l>
    <l>Do not disdain to tell us who thou art.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to them: &quot;Born was I, and grew up</l>
    <l>In the great town on the fair river of Arno,</l>
    <l>And with the body am I've always had.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But who are ye, in whom there trickles down</l>
    <l>Along your cheeks such grief as I behold?</l>
    <l>And what pain is upon you, that so sparkles?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one replied to me: &quot;These orange cloaks</l>
    <l>Are made of lead so heavy, that the weights</l>
    <l>Cause in this way their balances to creak.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Frati Gaudenti were we, and Bolognese;</l>
    <l>I Catalano, and he Loderingo</l>
    <l>Named, and together taken by thy city,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As the wont is to take one man alone,</l>
    <l>For maintenance of its peace; and we were such</l>
    <l>That still it is apparent round Gardingo.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O Friars,&quot; began I, &quot;your iniquitous. . .&quot;</l>
    <l>But said no more; for to mine eyes there rushed</l>
    <l>One crucified with three stakes on the ground.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When me he saw, he writhed himself all over,</l>
    <l>Blowing into his beard with suspirations;</l>
    <l>And the Friar Catalan, who noticed this,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Said to me: &quot;This transfixed one, whom thou seest,</l>
    <l>Counselled the Pharisees that it was meet</l>
    <l>To put one man to torture for the people.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Crosswise and naked is he on the path,</l>
    <l>As thou perceivest; and he needs must feel,</l>
    <l>Whoever passes, first how much he weighs;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in like mode his father-in-law is punished</l>
    <l>Within this moat, and the others of the council,</l>
    <l>Which for the Jews was a malignant seed.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And thereupon I saw Virgilius marvel</l>
    <l>O'er him who was extended on the cross</l>
    <l>So vilely in eternal banishment.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he directed to the Friar this voice:</l>
    <l>&quot;Be not displeased, if granted thee, to tell us</l>
    <l>If to the right hand any pass slope down</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By which we two may issue forth from here,</l>
    <l>Without constraining some of the black angels</l>
    <l>To come and extricate us from this deep.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he made answer: &quot;Nearer than thou hopest</l>
    <l>There is a rock, that forth from the great circle</l>
    <l>Proceeds, and crosses all the cruel valleys,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Save that at this 'tis broken, and does not bridge it;</l>
    <l>You will be able to mount up the ruin,</l>
    <l>That sidelong slopes and at the bottom rises.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Leader stood awhile with head bowed down;</l>
    <l>Then said: &quot;The business badly he recounted</l>
    <l>Who grapples with his hook the sinners yonder.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the Friar: &quot;Many of the Devil's vices</l>
    <l>Once heard I at Bologna, and among them,</l>
    <l>That he's a liar and the father of lies.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereat my Leader with great strides went on,</l>
    <l>Somewhat disturbed with anger in his looks;</l>
    <l>Whence from the heavy-laden I departed</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After the prints of his beloved feet.</l>
  </p>
</page>