<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Who ever could, e'en with untrammelled words,</l>
    <l>Tell of the blood and of the wounds in full</l>
    <l>Which now I saw, by many times narrating?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Each tongue would for a certainty fall short</l>
    <l>By reason of our speech and memory,</l>
    <l>That have small room to comprehend so much.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If were again assembled all the people</l>
    <l>Which formerly upon the fateful land</l>
    <l>Of Puglia were lamenting for their blood</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Shed by the Romans and the lingering war</l>
    <l>That of the rings made such illustrious spoils,</l>
    <l>As Livy has recorded, who errs not,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With those who felt the agony of blows</l>
    <l>By making counterstand to Robert Guiscard,</l>
    <l>And all the rest, whose bones are gathered still</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>At Ceperano, where a renegade</l>
    <l>Was each Apulian, and at Tagliacozzo,</l>
    <l>Where without arms the old Alardo conquered,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one his limb transpierced, and one lopped off,</l>
    <l>Should show, it would be nothing to compare</l>
    <l>With the disgusting mode of the ninth Bolgia.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A cask by losing centre-piece or cant</l>
    <l>Was never shattered so, as I saw one</l>
    <l>Rent from the chin to where one breaketh wind.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Between his legs were hanging down his entrails;</l>
    <l>His heart was visible, and the dismal sack</l>
    <l>That maketh excrement of what is eaten.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>While I was all absorbed in seeing him,</l>
    <l>He looked at me, and opened with his hands</l>
    <l>His bosom, saying: &quot;See now how I rend me;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How mutilated, see, is Mahomet;</l>
    <l>In front of me doth Ali weeping go,</l>
    <l>Cleft in the face from forelock unto chin;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And all the others whom thou here beholdest,</l>
    <l>Disseminators of scandal and of schism</l>
    <l>While living were, and therefore are cleft thus.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A devil is behind here, who doth cleave us</l>
    <l>Thus cruelly, unto the falchion's edge</l>
    <l>Putting again each one of all this ream,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When we have gone around the doleful road;</l>
    <l>By reason that our wounds are closed again</l>
    <l>Ere any one in front of him repass.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But who art thou, that musest on the crag,</l>
    <l>Perchance to postpone going to the pain</l>
    <l>That is adjudged upon thine accusations?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Nor death hath reached him yet, nor guilt doth bring him,&quot;</l>
    <l>My Master made reply, &quot;to be tormented;</l>
    <l>But to procure him full experience,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Me, who am dead, behoves it to conduct him</l>
    <l>Down here through Hell, from circle unto circle;</l>
    <l>And this is true as that I speak to thee.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>More than a hundred were there when they heard him,</l>
    <l>Who in the moat stood still to look at me,</l>
    <l>Through wonderment oblivious of their torture.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Now say to Fra Dolcino, then, to arm him,</l>
    <l>Thou, who perhaps wilt shortly see the sun,</l>
    <l>If soon he wish not here to follow me,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So with provisions, that no stress of snow</l>
    <l>May give the victory to the Novarese,</l>
    <l>Which otherwise to gain would not be easy.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After one foot to go away he lifted,</l>
    <l>This word did Mahomet say unto me,</l>
    <l>Then to depart upon the ground he stretched it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Another one, who had his throat pierced through,</l>
    <l>And nose cut off close underneath the brows,</l>
    <l>And had no longer but a single ear,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Staying to look in wonder with the others,</l>
    <l>Before the others did his gullet open,</l>
    <l>Which outwardly was red in every part,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And said: &quot;O thou, whom guilt doth not condemn,</l>
    <l>And whom I once saw up in Latian land,</l>
    <l>Unless too great similitude deceive me,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Call to remembrance Pier da Medicina,</l>
    <l>If e'er thou see again the lovely plain</l>
    <l>That from Vercelli slopes to Marcabo,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And make it known to the best two of Fano,</l>
    <l>To Messer Guido and Angiolello likewise,</l>
    <l>That if foreseeing here be not in vain,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Cast over from their vessel shall they be,</l>
    <l>And drowned near unto the Cattolica,</l>
    <l>By the betrayal of a tyrant fell.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Between the isles of Cyprus and Majorca</l>
    <l>Neptune ne'er yet beheld so great a crime,</l>
    <l>Neither of pirates nor Argolic people.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That traitor, who sees only with one eye,</l>
    <l>And holds the land, which some one here with me</l>
    <l>Would fain be fasting from the vision of,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Will make them come unto a parley with him;</l>
    <l>Then will do so, that to Focara's wind</l>
    <l>They will not stand in need of vow or prayer.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;Show to me and declare,</l>
    <l>If thou wouldst have me bear up news of thee,</l>
    <l>Who is this person of the bitter vision.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then did he lay his hand upon the jaw</l>
    <l>Of one of his companions, and his mouth</l>
    <l>Oped, crying: &quot;This is he, and he speaks not.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This one, being banished, every doubt submerged</l>
    <l>In Caesar by affirming the forearmed</l>
    <l>Always with detriment allowed delay.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O how bewildered unto me appeared,</l>
    <l>With tongue asunder in his windpipe slit,</l>
    <l>Curio, who in speaking was so bold!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one, who both his hands dissevered had,</l>
    <l>The stumps uplifting through the murky air,</l>
    <l>So that the blood made horrible his face,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Cried out: &quot;Thou shalt remember Mosca also,</l>
    <l>Who said, alas! 'A thing done has an end!'</l>
    <l>Which was an ill seed for the Tuscan people.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;And death unto thy race,&quot; thereto I added;</l>
    <l>Whence he, accumulating woe on woe,</l>
    <l>Departed, like a person sad and crazed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But I remained to look upon the crowd;</l>
    <l>And saw a thing which I should be afraid,</l>
    <l>Without some further proof, even to recount,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If it were not that conscience reassures me,</l>
    <l>That good companion which emboldens man</l>
    <l>Beneath the hauberk of its feeling pure.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I truly saw, and still I seem to see it,</l>
    <l>A trunk without a head walk in like manner</l>
    <l>As walked the others of the mournful herd.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And by the hair it held the head dissevered,</l>
    <l>Hung from the hand in fashion of a lantern,</l>
    <l>And that upon us gazed and said: &quot;O me!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>It of itself made to itself a lamp,</l>
    <l>And they were two in one, and one in two;</l>
    <l>How that can be, He knows who so ordains it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When it was come close to the bridge's foot,</l>
    <l>It lifted high its arm with all the head,</l>
    <l>To bring more closely unto us its words,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Which were: &quot;Behold now the sore penalty,</l>
    <l>Thou, who dost breathing go the dead beholding;</l>
    <l>Behold if any be as great as this.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And so that thou may carry news of me,</l>
    <l>Know that Bertram de Born am I, the same</l>
    <l>Who gave to the Young King the evil comfort.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I made the father and the son rebellious;</l>
    <l>Achitophel not more with Absalom</l>
    <l>And David did with his accursed goadings.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because I parted persons so united,</l>
    <l>Parted do I now bear my brain, alas!</l>
    <l>From its beginning, which is in this trunk.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus is observed in me the counterpoise.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>