<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Upon the margin of a lofty bank</l>
    <l>Which great rocks broken in a circle made,</l>
    <l>We came upon a still more cruel throng;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And there, by reason of the horrible</l>
    <l>Excess of stench the deep abyss throws out,</l>
    <l>We drew ourselves aside behind the cover</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Of a great tomb, whereon I saw a writing,</l>
    <l>Which said: &quot;Pope Anastasius I hold,</l>
    <l>Whom out of the right way Photinus drew.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Slow it behoveth our descent to be,</l>
    <l>So that the sense be first a little used</l>
    <l>To the sad blast, and then we shall not heed it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Master thus; and unto him I said,</l>
    <l>&quot;Some compensation find, that the time pass not</l>
    <l>Idly;&quot; and he: &quot;Thou seest I think of that.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My son, upon the inside of these rocks,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began he then to say, &quot;are three small circles,</l>
    <l>From grade to grade, like those which thou art leaving.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They all are full of spirits maledict;</l>
    <l>But that hereafter sight alone suffice thee,</l>
    <l>Hear how and wherefore they are in constraint.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Of every malice that wins hate in Heaven,</l>
    <l>Injury is the end; and all such end</l>
    <l>Either by force or fraud afflicteth others.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But because fraud is man's peculiar vice,</l>
    <l>More it displeases God; and so stand lowest</l>
    <l>The fraudulent, and greater dole assails them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>All the first circle of the Violent is;</l>
    <l>But since force may be used against three persons,</l>
    <l>In three rounds 'tis divided and constructed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To God, to ourselves, and to our neighbour can we</l>
    <l>Use force; I say on them and on their things,</l>
    <l>As thou shalt hear with reason manifest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A death by violence, and painful wounds,</l>
    <l>Are to our neighbour given; and in his substance</l>
    <l>Ruin, and arson, and injurious levies;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence homicides, and he who smites unjustly,</l>
    <l>Marauders, and freebooters, the first round</l>
    <l>Tormenteth all in companies diverse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Man may lay violent hands upon himself</l>
    <l>And his own goods; and therefore in the second</l>
    <l>Round must perforce without avail repent</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whoever of your world deprives himself,</l>
    <l>Who games, and dissipates his property,</l>
    <l>And weepeth there, where he should jocund be.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Violence can be done the Deity,</l>
    <l>In heart denying and blaspheming Him,</l>
    <l>And by disdaining Nature and her bounty.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And for this reason doth the smallest round</l>
    <l>Seal with its signet Sodom and Cahors,</l>
    <l>And who, disdaining God, speaks from the heart.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Fraud, wherewithal is every conscience stung,</l>
    <l>A man may practise upon him who trusts,</l>
    <l>And him who doth no confidence imburse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This latter mode, it would appear, dissevers</l>
    <l>Only the bond of love which Nature makes;</l>
    <l>Wherefore within the second circle nestle</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hypocrisy, flattery, and who deals in magic,</l>
    <l>Falsification, theft, and simony,</l>
    <l>Panders, and barrators, and the like filth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By the other mode, forgotten is that love</l>
    <l>Which Nature makes, and what is after added,</l>
    <l>From which there is a special faith engendered.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hence in the smallest circle, where the point is</l>
    <l>Of the Universe, upon which Dis is seated,</l>
    <l>Whoe'er betrays for ever is consumed.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;My Master, clear enough proceeds</l>
    <l>Thy reasoning, and full well distinguishes</l>
    <l>This cavern and the people who possess it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me, those within the fat lagoon,</l>
    <l>Whom the wind drives, and whom the rain doth beat,</l>
    <l>And who encounter with such bitter tongues,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wherefore are they inside of the red city</l>
    <l>Not punished, if God has them in his wrath,</l>
    <l>And if he has not, wherefore in such fashion?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And unto me he said: &quot;Why wanders so</l>
    <l>Thine intellect from that which it is wont?</l>
    <l>Or, sooth, thy mind where is it elsewhere looking?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hast thou no recollection of those words</l>
    <l>With which thine Ethics thoroughly discusses</l>
    <l>The dispositions three, that Heaven abides not,--</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Incontinence, and Malice, and insane</l>
    <l>Bestiality? and how Incontinence</l>
    <l>Less God offendeth, and less blame attracts?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If thou regardest this conclusion well,</l>
    <l>And to thy mind recallest who they are</l>
    <l>That up outside are undergoing penance,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Clearly wilt thou perceive why from these felons</l>
    <l>They separated are, and why less wroth</l>
    <l>Justice divine doth smite them with its hammer.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O Sun, that healest all distempered vision,</l>
    <l>Thou dost content me so, when thou resolvest,</l>
    <l>That doubting pleases me no less than knowing!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Once more a little backward turn thee,&quot; said I,</l>
    <l>&quot;There where thou sayest that usury offends</l>
    <l>Goodness divine, and disengage the knot.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Philosophy,&quot; he said, &quot;to him who heeds it,</l>
    <l>Noteth, not only in one place alone,</l>
    <l>After what manner Nature takes her course</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From Intellect Divine, and from its art;</l>
    <l>And if thy Physics carefully thou notest,</l>
    <l>After not many pages shalt thou find,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That this your art as far as possible</l>
    <l>Follows, as the disciple doth the master;</l>
    <l>So that your art is, as it were, God's grandchild.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From these two, if thou bringest to thy mind</l>
    <l>Genesis at the beginning, it behoves</l>
    <l>Mankind to gain their life and to advance;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And since the usurer takes another way,</l>
    <l>Nature herself and in her follower</l>
    <l>Disdains he, for elsewhere he puts his hope.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But follow, now, as I would fain go on,</l>
    <l>For quivering are the Fishes on the horizon,</l>
    <l>And the Wain wholly over Caurus lies,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And far beyond there we descend the crag.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>