<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>At the conclusion of his words, the thief</l>
    <l>Lifted his hands aloft with both the figs,</l>
    <l>Crying: &quot;Take that, God, for at thee I aim them.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From that time forth the serpents were my friends;</l>
    <l>For one entwined itself about his neck</l>
    <l>As if it said: &quot;I will not thou speak more;&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And round his arms another, and rebound him,</l>
    <l>Clinching itself together so in front,</l>
    <l>That with them he could not a motion make.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Pistoia, ah, Pistoia! why resolve not</l>
    <l>To burn thyself to ashes and so perish,</l>
    <l>Since in ill-doing thou thy seed excellest?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Through all the sombre circles of this Hell,</l>
    <l>Spirit I saw not against God so proud,</l>
    <l>Not he who fell at Thebes down from the walls!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He fled away, and spake no further word;</l>
    <l>And I beheld a Centaur full of rage</l>
    <l>Come crying out: &quot;Where is, where is the scoffer?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I do not think Maremma has so many</l>
    <l>Serpents as he had all along his back,</l>
    <l>As far as where our countenance begins.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Upon the shoulders, just behind the nape,</l>
    <l>With wings wide open was a dragon lying,</l>
    <l>And he sets fire to all that he encounters.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Master said: &quot;That one is Cacus, who</l>
    <l>Beneath the rock upon Mount Aventine</l>
    <l>Created oftentimes a lake of blood.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He goes not on the same road with his brothers,</l>
    <l>By reason of the fraudulent theft he made</l>
    <l>Of the great herd, which he had near to him;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whereat his tortuous actions ceased beneath</l>
    <l>The mace of Hercules, who peradventure</l>
    <l>Gave him a hundred, and he felt not ten.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>While he was speaking thus, he had passed by,</l>
    <l>And spirits three had underneath us come,</l>
    <l>Of which nor I aware was, nor my Leader,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Until what time they shouted: &quot;Who are you?&quot;</l>
    <l>On which account our story made a halt,</l>
    <l>And then we were intent on them alone.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I did not know them; but it came to pass,</l>
    <l>As it is wont to happen by some chance,</l>
    <l>That one to name the other was compelled,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Exclaiming: &quot;Where can Cianfa have remained?&quot;</l>
    <l>Whence I, so that the Leader might attend,</l>
    <l>Upward from chin to nose my finger laid.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If thou art, Reader, slow now to believe</l>
    <l>What I shall say, it will no marvel be,</l>
    <l>For I who saw it hardly can admit it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As I was holding raised on them my brows,</l>
    <l>Behold! a serpent with six feet darts forth</l>
    <l>In front of one, and fastens wholly on him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With middle feet it bound him round the paunch,</l>
    <l>And with the forward ones his arms it seized;</l>
    <l>Then thrust its teeth through one cheek and the other;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The hindermost it stretched upon his thighs,</l>
    <l>And put its tail through in between the two,</l>
    <l>And up behind along the reins outspread it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ivy was never fastened by its barbs</l>
    <l>Unto a tree so, as this horrible reptile</l>
    <l>Upon the other's limbs entwined its own.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then they stuck close, as if of heated wax</l>
    <l>They had been made, and intermixed their colour;</l>
    <l>Nor one nor other seemed now what he was;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>E'en as proceedeth on before the flame</l>
    <l>Upward along the paper a brown colour,</l>
    <l>Which is not black as yet, and the white dies.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other two looked on, and each of them</l>
    <l>Cried out: &quot;O me, Agnello, how thou changest!</l>
    <l>Behold, thou now art neither two nor one.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Already the two heads had one become,</l>
    <l>When there appeared to us two figures mingled</l>
    <l>Into one face, wherein the two were lost.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Of the four lists were fashioned the two arms,</l>
    <l>The thighs and legs, the belly and the chest</l>
    <l>Members became that never yet were seen.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Every original aspect there was cancelled;</l>
    <l>Two and yet none did the perverted image</l>
    <l>Appear, and such departed with slow pace.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as a lizard, under the great scourge</l>
    <l>Of days canicular, exchanging hedge,</l>
    <l>Lightning appeareth if the road it cross;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus did appear, coming towards the bellies</l>
    <l>Of the two others, a small fiery serpent,</l>
    <l>Livid and black as is a peppercorn.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in that part whereat is first received</l>
    <l>Our aliment, it one of them transfixed;</l>
    <l>Then downward fell in front of him extended.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The one transfixed looked at it, but said naught;</l>
    <l>Nay, rather with feet motionless he yawned,</l>
    <l>Just as if sleep or fever had assailed him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He at the serpent gazed, and it at him;</l>
    <l>One through the wound, the other through the mouth</l>
    <l>Smoked violently, and the smoke commingled.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Henceforth be silent Lucan, where he mentions</l>
    <l>Wretched Sabellus and Nassidius,</l>
    <l>And wait to hear what now shall be shot forth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Be silent Ovid, of Cadmus and Arethusa;</l>
    <l>For if him to a snake, her to fountain,</l>
    <l>Converts he fabling, that I grudge him not;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because two natures never front to front</l>
    <l>Has he transmuted, so that both the forms</l>
    <l>To interchange their matter ready were.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Together they responded in such wise,</l>
    <l>That to a fork the serpent cleft his tail,</l>
    <l>And eke the wounded drew his feet together.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The legs together with the thighs themselves</l>
    <l>Adhered so, that in little time the juncture</l>
    <l>No sign whatever made that was apparent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He with the cloven tail assumed the figure</l>
    <l>The other one was losing, and his skin</l>
    <l>Became elastic, and the other's hard.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw the arms draw inward at the armpits,</l>
    <l>And both feet of the reptile, that were short,</l>
    <l>Lengthen as much as those contracted were.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafter the hind feet, together twisted,</l>
    <l>Became the member that a man conceals,</l>
    <l>And of his own the wretch had two created.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>While both of them the exhalation veils</l>
    <l>With a new colour, and engenders hair</l>
    <l>On one of them and depilates the other,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The one uprose and down the other fell,</l>
    <l>Though turning not away their impious lamps,</l>
    <l>Underneath which each one his muzzle changed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who was standing drew it tow'rds the temples,</l>
    <l>And from excess of matter, which came thither,</l>
    <l>Issued the ears from out the hollow cheeks;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What did not backward run and was retained</l>
    <l>Of that excess made to the face a nose,</l>
    <l>And the lips thickened far as was befitting.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who lay prostrate thrusts his muzzle forward,</l>
    <l>And backward draws the ears into his head,</l>
    <l>In the same manner as the snail its horns;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And so the tongue, which was entire and apt</l>
    <l>For speech before, is cleft, and the bi-forked</l>
    <l>In the other closes up, and the smoke ceases.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The soul, which to a reptile had been changed,</l>
    <l>Along the valley hissing takes to flight,</l>
    <l>And after him the other speaking sputters.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then did he turn upon him his new shoulders,</l>
    <l>And said to the other: &quot;I'll have Buoso run,</l>
    <l>Crawling as I have done, along this road.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In this way I beheld the seventh ballast</l>
    <l>Shift and reshift, and here be my excuse</l>
    <l>The novelty, if aught my pen transgress.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And notwithstanding that mine eyes might be</l>
    <l>Somewhat bewildered, and my mind dismayed,</l>
    <l>They could not flee away so secretly</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But that I plainly saw Puccio Sciancato;</l>
    <l>And he it was who sole of three companions,</l>
    <l>Which came in the beginning, was not changed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other was he whom thou, Gaville, weepest.</l>
  </p>
</page>