<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Midway upon the journey of our life</l>
    <l>I found myself within a forest dark,</l>
    <l>For the straightforward pathway had been lost.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah me! how hard a thing it is to say</l>
    <l>What was this forest savage, rough, and stern,</l>
    <l>Which in the very thought renews the fear.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So bitter is it, death is little more;</l>
    <l>But of the good to treat, which there I found,</l>
    <l>Speak will I of the other things I saw there.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I cannot well repeat how there I entered,</l>
    <l>So full was I of slumber at the moment</l>
    <l>In which I had abandoned the true way.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But after I had reached a mountain's foot,</l>
    <l>At that point where the valley terminated,</l>
    <l>Which had with consternation pierced my heart,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Upward I looked, and I beheld its shoulders,</l>
    <l>Vested already with that planet's rays</l>
    <l>Which leadeth others right by every road.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then was the fear a little quieted</l>
    <l>That in my heart's lake had endured throughout</l>
    <l>The night, which I had passed so piteously.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as he, who, with distressful breath,</l>
    <l>Forth issued from the sea upon the shore,</l>
    <l>Turns to the water perilous and gazes;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So did my soul, that still was fleeing onward,</l>
    <l>Turn itself back to re-behold the pass</l>
    <l>Which never yet a living person left.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After my weary body I had rested,</l>
    <l>The way resumed I on the desert slope,</l>
    <l>So that the firm foot ever was the lower.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And lo! almost where the ascent began,</l>
    <l>A panther light and swift exceedingly,</l>
    <l>Which with a spotted skin was covered o'er!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And never moved she from before my face,</l>
    <l>Nay, rather did impede so much my way,</l>
    <l>That many times I to return had turned.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The time was the beginning of the morning,</l>
    <l>And up the sun was mounting with those stars</l>
    <l>That with him were, what time the Love Divine</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>At first in motion set those beauteous things;</l>
    <l>So were to me occasion of good hope,</l>
    <l>The variegated skin of that wild beast,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The hour of time, and the delicious season;</l>
    <l>But not so much, that did not give me fear</l>
    <l>A lion's aspect which appeared to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He seemed as if against me he were coming</l>
    <l>With head uplifted, and with ravenous hunger,</l>
    <l>So that it seemed the air was afraid of him;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And a she-wolf, that with all hungerings</l>
    <l>Seemed to be laden in her meagreness,</l>
    <l>And many folk has caused to live forlorn!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>She brought upon me so much heaviness,</l>
    <l>With the affright that from her aspect came,</l>
    <l>That I the hope relinquished of the height.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as he is who willingly acquires,</l>
    <l>And the time comes that causes him to lose,</l>
    <l>Who weeps in all his thoughts and is despondent,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>E'en such made me that beast withouten peace,</l>
    <l>Which, coming on against me by degrees</l>
    <l>Thrust me back thither where the sun is silent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>While I was rushing downward to the lowland,</l>
    <l>Before mine eyes did one present himself,</l>
    <l>Who seemed from long-continued silence hoarse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When I beheld him in the desert vast,</l>
    <l>&quot;Have pity on me,&quot; unto him I cried,</l>
    <l>&quot;Whiche'er thou art, or shade or real man!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He answered me: &quot;Not man; man once I was,</l>
    <l>And both my parents were of Lombardy,</l>
    <l>And Mantuans by country both of them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Sub Julio' was I born, though it was late,</l>
    <l>And lived at Rome under the good Augustus,</l>
    <l>During the time of false and lying gods.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A poet was I, and I sang that just</l>
    <l>Son of Anchises, who came forth from Troy,</l>
    <l>After that Ilion the superb was burned.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But thou, why goest thou back to such annoyance?</l>
    <l>Why climb'st thou not the Mount Delectable,</l>
    <l>Which is the source and cause of every joy?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Now, art thou that Virgilius and that fountain</l>
    <l>Which spreads abroad so wide a river of speech?&quot;</l>
    <l>I made response to him with bashful forehead.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O, of the other poets honour and light,</l>
    <l>Avail me the long study and great love</l>
    <l>That have impelled me to explore thy volume!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou art my master, and my author thou,</l>
    <l>Thou art alone the one from whom I took</l>
    <l>The beautiful style that has done honour to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold the beast, for which I have turned back;</l>
    <l>Do thou protect me from her, famous Sage,</l>
    <l>For she doth make my veins and pulses tremble.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Thee it behoves to take another road,&quot;</l>
    <l>Responded he, when he beheld me weeping,</l>
    <l>&quot;If from this savage place thou wouldst escape;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because this beast, at which thou criest out,</l>
    <l>Suffers not any one to pass her way,</l>
    <l>But so doth harass him, that she destroys him;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And has a nature so malign and ruthless,</l>
    <l>That never doth she glut her greedy will,</l>
    <l>And after food is hungrier than before.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Many the animals with whom she weds,</l>
    <l>And more they shall be still, until the Greyhound</l>
    <l>Comes, who shall make her perish in her pain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He shall not feed on either earth or pelf,</l>
    <l>But upon wisdom, and on love and virtue;</l>
    <l>'Twixt Feltro and Feltro shall his nation be;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Of that low Italy shall he be the saviour,</l>
    <l>On whose account the maid Camilla died,</l>
    <l>Euryalus, Turnus, Nisus, of their wounds;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Through every city shall he hunt her down,</l>
    <l>Until he shall have driven her back to Hell,</l>
    <l>There from whence envy first did let her loose.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore I think and judge it for thy best</l>
    <l>Thou follow me, and I will be thy guide,</l>
    <l>And lead thee hence through the eternal place,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Where thou shalt hear the desperate lamentations,</l>
    <l>Shalt see the ancient spirits disconsolate,</l>
    <l>Who cry out each one for the second death;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And thou shalt see those who contented are</l>
    <l>Within the fire, because they hope to come,</l>
    <l>Whene'er it may be, to the blessed people;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To whom, then, if thou wishest to ascend,</l>
    <l>A soul shall be for that than I more worthy;</l>
    <l>With her at my departure I will leave thee;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because that Emperor, who reigns above,</l>
    <l>In that I was rebellious to his law,</l>
    <l>Wills that through me none come into his city.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He governs everywhere, and there he reigns;</l>
    <l>There is his city and his lofty throne;</l>
    <l>O happy he whom thereto he elects!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;Poet, I thee entreat,</l>
    <l>By that same God whom thou didst never know,</l>
    <l>So that I may escape this woe and worse,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou wouldst conduct me there where thou hast said,</l>
    <l>That I may see the portal of Saint Peter,</l>
    <l>And those thou makest so disconsolate.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he moved on, and I behind him followed.</l>
  </p>
</page>