<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>If I had rhymes both rough and stridulous,</l>
    <l>As were appropriate to the dismal hole</l>
    <l>Down upon which thrust all the other rocks,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I would press out the juice of my conception</l>
    <l>More fully; but because I have them not,</l>
    <l>Not without fear I bring myself to speak;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For 'tis no enterprise to take in jest,</l>
    <l>To sketch the bottom of all the universe,</l>
    <l>Nor for a tongue that cries Mamma and Babbo.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But may those Ladies help this verse of mine,</l>
    <l>Who helped Amphion in enclosing Thebes,</l>
    <l>That from the fact the word be not diverse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O rabble ill-begotten above all,</l>
    <l>Who're in the place to speak of which is hard,</l>
    <l>'Twere better ye had here been sheep or goats!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When we were down within the darksome well,</l>
    <l>Beneath the giant's feet, but lower far,</l>
    <l>And I was scanning still the lofty wall,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I heard it said to me: &quot;Look how thou steppest!</l>
    <l>Take heed thou do not trample with thy feet</l>
    <l>The heads of the tired, miserable brothers!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whereat I turned me round, and saw before me</l>
    <l>And underfoot a lake, that from the frost</l>
    <l>The semblance had of glass, and not of water.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So thick a veil ne'er made upon its current</l>
    <l>In winter-time Danube in Austria,</l>
    <l>Nor there beneath the frigid sky the Don,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As there was here; so that if Tambernich</l>
    <l>Had fallen upon it, or Pietrapana,</l>
    <l>E'en at the edge 'twould not have given a creak.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as to croak the frog doth place himself</l>
    <l>With muzzle out of water,--when is dreaming</l>
    <l>Of gleaning oftentimes the peasant-girl,--</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Livid, as far down as where shame appears,</l>
    <l>Were the disconsolate shades within the ice,</l>
    <l>Setting their teeth unto the note of storks.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Each one his countenance held downward bent;</l>
    <l>From mouth the cold, from eyes the doleful heart</l>
    <l>Among them witness of itself procures.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When round about me somewhat I had looked,</l>
    <l>I downward turned me, and saw two so close,</l>
    <l>The hair upon their heads together mingled.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Ye who so strain your breasts together, tell me,&quot;</l>
    <l>I said, &quot;who are you;&quot; and they bent their necks,</l>
    <l>And when to me their faces they had lifted,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Their eyes, which first were only moist within,</l>
    <l>Gushed o'er the eyelids, and the frost congealed</l>
    <l>The tears between, and locked them up again.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Clamp never bound together wood with wood</l>
    <l>So strongly; whereat they, like two he-goats,</l>
    <l>Butted together, so much wrath o'ercame them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one, who had by reason of the cold</l>
    <l>Lost both his ears, still with his visage downward,</l>
    <l>Said: &quot;Why dost thou so mirror thyself in us?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If thou desire to know who these two are,</l>
    <l>The valley whence Bisenzio descends</l>
    <l>Belonged to them and to their father Albert.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They from one body came, and all Caina</l>
    <l>Thou shalt search through, and shalt not find a shade</l>
    <l>More worthy to be fixed in gelatine;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not he in whom were broken breast and shadow</l>
    <l>At one and the same blow by Arthur's hand;</l>
    <l>Focaccia not; not he who me encumbers</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So with his head I see no farther forward,</l>
    <l>And bore the name of Sassol Mascheroni;</l>
    <l>Well knowest thou who he was, if thou art Tuscan.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And that thou put me not to further speech,</l>
    <l>Know that I Camicion de' Pazzi was,</l>
    <l>And wait Carlino to exonerate me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then I beheld a thousand faces, made</l>
    <l>Purple with cold; whence o'er me comes a shudder,</l>
    <l>And evermore will come, at frozen ponds.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And while we were advancing tow'rds the middle,</l>
    <l>Where everything of weight unites together,</l>
    <l>And I was shivering in the eternal shade,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whether 'twere will, or destiny, or chance,</l>
    <l>I know not; but in walking 'mong the heads</l>
    <l>I struck my foot hard in the face of one.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Weeping he growled: &quot;Why dost thou trample me?</l>
    <l>Unless thou comest to increase the vengeance</l>
    <l>of Montaperti, why dost thou molest me?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;My Master, now wait here for me,</l>
    <l>That I through him may issue from a doubt;</l>
    <l>Then thou mayst hurry me, as thou shalt wish.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Leader stopped; and to that one I said</l>
    <l>Who was blaspheming vehemently still:</l>
    <l>&quot;Who art thou, that thus reprehendest others?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Now who art thou, that goest through Antenora</l>
    <l>Smiting,&quot; replied he, &quot;other people's cheeks,</l>
    <l>So that, if thou wert living, 'twere too much?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Living I am, and dear to thee it may be,&quot;</l>
    <l>Was my response, &quot;if thou demandest fame,</l>
    <l>That 'mid the other notes thy name I place.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;For the reverse I long;</l>
    <l>Take thyself hence, and give me no more trouble;</l>
    <l>For ill thou knowest to flatter in this hollow.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then by the scalp behind I seized upon him,</l>
    <l>And said: &quot;It must needs be thou name thyself,</l>
    <l>Or not a hair remain upon thee here.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence he to me: &quot;Though thou strip off my hair,</l>
    <l>I will not tell thee who I am, nor show thee,</l>
    <l>If on my head a thousand times thou fall.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I had his hair in hand already twisted,</l>
    <l>And more than one shock of it had pulled out,</l>
    <l>He barking, with his eyes held firmly down,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When cried another: &quot;What doth ail thee, Bocca?</l>
    <l>Is't not enough to clatter with thy jaws,</l>
    <l>But thou must bark? what devil touches thee?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Now,&quot; said I, &quot;I care not to have thee speak,</l>
    <l>Accursed traitor; for unto thy shame</l>
    <l>I will report of thee veracious news.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Begone,&quot; replied he, &quot;and tell what thou wilt,</l>
    <l>But be not silent, if thou issue hence,</l>
    <l>Of him who had just now his tongue so prompt;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He weepeth here the silver of the French;</l>
    <l>'I saw,' thus canst thou phrase it, 'him of Duera</l>
    <l>There where the sinners stand out in the cold.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If thou shouldst questioned be who else was there,</l>
    <l>Thou hast beside thee him of Beccaria,</l>
    <l>Of whom the gorget Florence slit asunder;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Gianni del Soldanier, I think, may be</l>
    <l>Yonder with Ganellon, and Tebaldello</l>
    <l>Who oped Faenza when the people slep.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Already we had gone away from him,</l>
    <l>When I beheld two frozen in one hole,</l>
    <l>So that one head a hood was to the other;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as bread through hunger is devoured,</l>
    <l>The uppermost on the other set his teeth,</l>
    <l>There where the brain is to the nape united.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not in another fashion Tydeus gnawed</l>
    <l>The temples of Menalippus in disdain,</l>
    <l>Than that one did the skull and the other things.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O thou, who showest by such bestial sign</l>
    <l>Thy hatred against him whom thou art eating,</l>
    <l>Tell me the wherefore,&quot; said I, &quot;with this compact,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That if thou rightfully of him complain,</l>
    <l>In knowing who ye are, and his transgression,</l>
    <l>I in the world above repay thee for it,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If that wherewith I speak be not dried up.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>