<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>That hue which cowardice brought out on me,</l>
    <l>Beholding my Conductor backward turn,</l>
    <l>Sooner repressed within him his new colour.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He stopped attentive, like a man who listens,</l>
    <l>Because the eye could not conduct him far</l>
    <l>Through the black air, and through the heavy fog.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Still it behoveth us to win the fight,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began he; &quot;Else. . .Such offered us herself. . .</l>
    <l>O how I long that some one here arrive!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well I perceived, as soon as the beginning</l>
    <l>He covered up with what came afterward,</l>
    <l>That they were words quite different from the first;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But none the less his saying gave me fear,</l>
    <l>Because I carried out the broken phrase,</l>
    <l>Perhaps to a worse meaning than he had.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Into this bottom of the doleful conch</l>
    <l>Doth any e'er descend from the first grade,</l>
    <l>Which for its pain has only hope cut off?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This question put I; and he answered me:</l>
    <l>&quot;Seldom it comes to pass that one of us</l>
    <l>Maketh the journey upon which I go.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>True is it, once before I here below</l>
    <l>Was conjured by that pitiless Erictho,</l>
    <l>Who summoned back the shades unto their bodies.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Naked of me short while the flesh had been,</l>
    <l>Before within that wall she made me enter,</l>
    <l>To bring a spirit from the circle of Judas;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That is the lowest region and the darkest,</l>
    <l>And farthest from the heaven which circles all.</l>
    <l>Well know I the way; therefore be reassured.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This fen, which a prodigious stench exhales,</l>
    <l>Encompasses about the city dolent,</l>
    <l>Where now we cannot enter without anger.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And more he said, but not in mind I have it;</l>
    <l>Because mine eye had altogether drawn me</l>
    <l>Tow'rds the high tower with the red-flaming summit,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Where in a moment saw I swift uprisen</l>
    <l>The three infernal Furies stained with blood,</l>
    <l>Who had the limbs of women and their mien,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And with the greenest hydras were begirt;</l>
    <l>Small serpents and cerastes were their tresses,</l>
    <l>Wherewith their horrid temples were entwined.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he who well the handmaids of the Queen</l>
    <l>Of everlasting lamentation knew,</l>
    <l>Said unto me: &quot;Behold the fierce Erinnys.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This is Megaera, on the left-hand side;</l>
    <l>She who is weeping on the right, Alecto;</l>
    <l>Tisiphone is between;&quot; and then was silent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Each one her breast was rending with her nails;</l>
    <l>They beat them with their palms, and cried so loud,</l>
    <l>That I for dread pressed close unto the Poet.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Medusa come, so we to stone will change him!&quot;</l>
    <l>All shouted looking down; &quot;in evil hour</l>
    <l>Avenged we not on Theseus his assault!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Turn thyself round, and keep thine eyes close shut,</l>
    <l>For if the Gorgon appear, and thou shouldst see it,</l>
    <l>No more returning upward would there be.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus said the Master; and he turned me round</l>
    <l>Himself, and trusted not unto my hands</l>
    <l>So far as not to blind me with his own.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O ye who have undistempered intellects,</l>
    <l>Observe the doctrine that conceals itself</l>
    <l>Beneath the veil of the mysterious verses!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And now there came across the turbid waves</l>
    <l>The clangour of a sound with terror fraught,</l>
    <l>Because of which both of the margins trembled;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not otherwise it was than of a wind</l>
    <l>Impetuous on account of adverse heats,</l>
    <l>That smites the forest, and, without restraint,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The branches rends, beats down, and bears away;</l>
    <l>Right onward, laden with dust, it goes superb,</l>
    <l>And puts to flight the wild beasts and the shepherds.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Mine eyes he loosed, and said: &quot;Direct the nerve</l>
    <l>Of vision now along that ancient foam,</l>
    <l>There yonder where that smoke is most intense.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the frogs before the hostile serpent</l>
    <l>Across the water scatter all abroad,</l>
    <l>Until each one is huddled in the earth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>More than a thousand ruined souls I saw,</l>
    <l>Thus fleeing from before one who on foot</l>
    <l>Was passing o'er the Styx with soles unwet.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From off his face he fanned that unctuous air,</l>
    <l>Waving his left hand oft in front of him,</l>
    <l>And only with that anguish seemed he weary.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well I perceived one sent from Heaven was he,</l>
    <l>And to the Master turned; and he made sign</l>
    <l>That I should quiet stand, and bow before him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah! how disdainful he appeared to me!</l>
    <l>He reached the gate, and with a little rod</l>
    <l>He opened it, for there was no resistance.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O banished out of Heaven, people despised!&quot;</l>
    <l>Thus he began upon the horrid threshold;</l>
    <l>&quot;Whence is this arrogance within you couched?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wherefore recalcitrate against that will,</l>
    <l>From which the end can never be cut off,</l>
    <l>And which has many times increased your pain?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What helpeth it to butt against the fates?</l>
    <l>Your Cerberus, if you remember well,</l>
    <l>For that still bears his chin and gullet peeled.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he returned along the miry road,</l>
    <l>And spake no word to us, but had the look</l>
    <l>Of one whom other care constrains and goads</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Than that of him who in his presence is;</l>
    <l>And we our feet directed tow'rds the city,</l>
    <l>After those holy words all confident.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Within we entered without any contest;</l>
    <l>And I, who inclination had to see</l>
    <l>What the condition such a fortress holds,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Soon as I was within, cast round mine eye,</l>
    <l>And see on every hand an ample plain,</l>
    <l>Full of distress and torment terrible.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as at Arles, where stagnant grows the Rhone,</l>
    <l>Even as at Pola near to the Quarnaro,</l>
    <l>That shuts in Italy and bathes its borders,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The sepulchres make all the place uneven;</l>
    <l>So likewise did they there on every side,</l>
    <l>Saving that there the manner was more bitter;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For flames between the sepulchres were scattered,</l>
    <l>By which they so intensely heated were,</l>
    <l>That iron more so asks not any art.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>All of their coverings uplifted were,</l>
    <l>And from them issued forth such dire laments,</l>
    <l>Sooth seemed they of the wretched and tormented.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;My Master, what are all those people</l>
    <l>Who, having sepulture within those tombs,</l>
    <l>Make themselves audible by doleful sighs?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Here are the Heresiarchs,</l>
    <l>With their disciples of all sects, and much</l>
    <l>More than thou thinkest laden are the tombs.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here like together with its like is buried;</l>
    <l>And more and less the monuments are heated.&quot;</l>
    <l>And when he to the right had turned, we passed</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Between the torments and high parapets.</l>
  </p>
</page>