<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Of a new pain behoves me to make verses</l>
    <l>And give material to the twentieth canto</l>
    <l>Of the first song, which is of the submerged.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I was already thoroughly disposed</l>
    <l>To peer down into the uncovered depth,</l>
    <l>Which bathed itself with tears of agony;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And people saw I through the circular valley,</l>
    <l>Silent and weeping, coming at the pace</l>
    <l>Which in this world the Litanies assume.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As lower down my sight descended on them,</l>
    <l>Wondrously each one seemed to be distorted</l>
    <l>From chin to the beginning of the chest;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For tow'rds the reins the countenance was turned,</l>
    <l>And backward it behoved them to advance,</l>
    <l>As to look forward had been taken from them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Perchance indeed by violence of palsy</l>
    <l>Some one has been thus wholly turned awry;</l>
    <l>But I ne'er saw it, nor believe it can be.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As God may let thee, Reader, gather fruit</l>
    <l>From this thy reading, think now for thyself</l>
    <l>How I could ever keep my face unmoistened,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When our own image near me I beheld</l>
    <l>Distorted so, the weeping of the eyes</l>
    <l>Along the fissure bathed the hinder parts.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Truly I wept, leaning upon a peak</l>
    <l>Of the hard crag, so that my Escort said</l>
    <l>To me: &quot;Art thou, too, of the other fools?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here pity lives when it is wholly dead;</l>
    <l>Who is a greater reprobate than he</l>
    <l>Who feels compassion at the doom divine?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Lift up, lift up thy head, and see for whom</l>
    <l>Opened the earth before the Thebans' eyes;</l>
    <l>Wherefore they all cried: 'Whither rushest thou,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Amphiaraus?  Why dost leave the war?'</l>
    <l>And downward ceased he not to fall amain</l>
    <l>As far as Minos, who lays hold on all.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>See, he has made a bosom of his shoulders!</l>
    <l>Because he wished to see too far before him</l>
    <l>Behind he looks, and backward goes his way:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold Tiresias, who his semblance changed,</l>
    <l>When from a male a female he became,</l>
    <l>His members being all of them transformed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And afterwards was forced to strike once more</l>
    <l>The two entangled serpents with his rod,</l>
    <l>Ere he could have again his manly plumes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That Aruns is, who backs the other's belly,</l>
    <l>Who in the hills of Luni, there where grubs</l>
    <l>The Carrarese who houses underneath,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Among the marbles white a cavern had</l>
    <l>For his abode; whence to behold the stars</l>
    <l>And sea, the view was not cut off from him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And she there, who is covering up her breasts,</l>
    <l>Which thou beholdest not, with loosened tresses,</l>
    <l>And on that side has all the hairy skin,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Was Manto, who made quest through many lands,</l>
    <l>Afterwards tarried there where I was born;</l>
    <l>Whereof I would thou list to me a little.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After her father had from life departed,</l>
    <l>And the city of Bacchus had become enslaved,</l>
    <l>She a long season wandered through the world.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Above in beauteous Italy lies a lake</l>
    <l>At the Alp's foot that shuts in Germany</l>
    <l>Over Tyrol, and has the name Benaco.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By a thousand springs, I think, and more, is bathed,</l>
    <l>'Twixt Garda and Val Camonica, Pennino,</l>
    <l>With water that grows stagnant in that lake.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Midway a place is where the Trentine Pastor,</l>
    <l>And he of Brescia, and the Veronese</l>
    <l>Might give his blessing, if he passed that way.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Sitteth Peschiera, fortress fair and strong,</l>
    <l>To front the Brescians and the Bergamasks,</l>
    <l>Where round about the bank descendeth lowest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There of necessity must fall whatever</l>
    <l>In bosom of Benaco cannot stay,</l>
    <l>And grows a river down through verdant pastures.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Soon as the water doth begin to run,</l>
    <l>No more Benaco is it called, but Mincio,</l>
    <l>Far as Governo, where it falls in Po.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not far it runs before it finds a plain</l>
    <l>In which it spreads itself, and makes it marshy,</l>
    <l>And oft 'tis wont in summer to be sickly.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Passing that way the virgin pitiless</l>
    <l>Land in the middle of the fen descried,</l>
    <l>Untilled and naked of inhabitants;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There to escape all human intercourse,</l>
    <l>She with her servants stayed, her arts to practise</l>
    <l>And lived, and left her empty body there.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The men, thereafter, who were scattered round,</l>
    <l>Collected in that place, which was made strong</l>
    <l>By the lagoon it had on every side;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They built their city over those dead bones,</l>
    <l>And, after her who first the place selected,</l>
    <l>Mantua named it, without other omen.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Its people once within more crowded were,</l>
    <l>Ere the stupidity of Casalodi</l>
    <l>From Pinamonte had received deceit.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore I caution thee, if e'er thou hearest</l>
    <l>Originate my city otherwise,</l>
    <l>No falsehood may the verity defraud.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;My Master, thy discourses are</l>
    <l>To me so certain, and so take my faith,</l>
    <l>That unto me the rest would be spent coals.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me of the people who are passing,</l>
    <l>If any one note-worthy thou beholdest,</l>
    <l>For only unto that my mind reverts.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then said he to me: &quot;He who from the cheek</l>
    <l>Thrusts out his beard upon his swarthy shoulders</l>
    <l>Was, at the time when Greece was void of males,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that there scarce remained one in the cradle,</l>
    <l>An augur, and with Calchas gave the moment,</l>
    <l>In Aulis, when to sever the first cable.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Eryphylus his name was, and so sings</l>
    <l>My lofty Tragedy in some part or other;</l>
    <l>That knowest thou well, who knowest the whole of it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The next, who is so slender in the flanks,</l>
    <l>Was Michael Scott, who of a verity</l>
    <l>Of magical illusions knew the game.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold Guido Bonatti, behold Asdente,</l>
    <l>Who now unto his leather and his thread</l>
    <l>Would fain have stuck, but he too late repents.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold the wretched ones, who left the needle,</l>
    <l>The spool and rock, and made them fortune-tellers;</l>
    <l>They wrought their magic spells with herb and image.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But come now, for already holds the confines</l>
    <l>Of both the hemispheres, and under Seville</l>
    <l>Touches the ocean-wave, Cain and the thorns,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And yesternight the moon was round already;</l>
    <l>Thou shouldst remember well it did not harm thee</l>
    <l>From time to time within the forest deep.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus spake he to me, and we walked the while.</l>
  </p>
</page>