<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>From bridge to bridge thus, speaking other things</l>
    <l>Of which my Comedy cares not to sing,</l>
    <l>We came along, and held the summit, when</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We halted to behold another fissure</l>
    <l>Of Malebolge and other vain laments;</l>
    <l>And I beheld it marvellously dark.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As in the Arsenal of the Venetians</l>
    <l>Boils in the winter the tenacious pitch</l>
    <l>To smear their unsound vessels o'er again,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For sail they cannot; and instead thereof</l>
    <l>One makes his vessel new, and one recaulks</l>
    <l>The ribs of that which many a voyage has made;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>One hammers at the prow, one at the stern,</l>
    <l>This one makes oars, and that one cordage twists,</l>
    <l>Another mends the mainsail and the mizzen;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus, not by fire, but by the art divine,</l>
    <l>Was boiling down below there a dense pitch</l>
    <l>Which upon every side the bank belimed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw it, but I did not see within it</l>
    <l>Aught but the bubbles that the boiling raised,</l>
    <l>And all swell up and resubside compressed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The while below there fixedly I gazed,</l>
    <l>My Leader, crying out: &quot;Beware, beware!&quot;</l>
    <l>Drew me unto himself from where I stood.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then I turned round, as one who is impatient</l>
    <l>To see what it behoves him to escape,</l>
    <l>And whom a sudden terror doth unman,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Who, while he looks, delays not his departure;</l>
    <l>And I beheld behind us a black devil,</l>
    <l>Running along upon the crag, approach.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah, how ferocious was he in his aspect!</l>
    <l>And how he seemed to me in action ruthless,</l>
    <l>With open wings and light upon his feet!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>His shoulders, which sharp-pointed were and high,</l>
    <l>A sinner did encumber with both haunches,</l>
    <l>And he held clutched the sinews of the feet.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From off our bridge, he said: &quot;O Malebranche,</l>
    <l>Behold one of the elders of Saint Zita;</l>
    <l>Plunge him beneath, for I return for others</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unto that town, which is well furnished with them.</l>
    <l>All there are barrators, except Bonturo;</l>
    <l>No into Yes for money there is changed.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He hurled him down, and over the hard crag</l>
    <l>Turned round, and never was a mastiff loosened</l>
    <l>In so much hurry to pursue a thief.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other sank, and rose again face downward;</l>
    <l>But the demons, under cover of the bridge,</l>
    <l>Cried: &quot;Here the Santo Volto has no place!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here swims one otherwise than in the Serchio;</l>
    <l>Therefore, if for our gaffs thou wishest not,</l>
    <l>Do not uplift thyself above the pitch.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They seized him then with more than a hundred rakes;</l>
    <l>They said: &quot;It here behoves thee to dance covered,</l>
    <l>That, if thou canst, thou secretly mayest pilfer.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not otherwise the cooks their scullions make</l>
    <l>Immerse into the middle of the caldron</l>
    <l>The meat with hooks, so that it may not float.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Said the good Master to me: &quot;That it be not</l>
    <l>Apparent thou art here, crouch thyself down</l>
    <l>Behind a jag, that thou mayest have some screen;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And for no outrage that is done to me</l>
    <l>Be thou afraid, because these things I know,</l>
    <l>For once before was I in such a scuffle.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then he passed on beyond the bridge's head,</l>
    <l>And as upon the sixth bank he arrived,</l>
    <l>Need was for him to have a steadfast front.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With the same fury, and the same uproar,</l>
    <l>As dogs leap out upon a mendicant,</l>
    <l>Who on a sudden begs, where'er he stops,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They issued from beneath the little bridge,</l>
    <l>And turned against him all their grappling-irons;</l>
    <l>But he cried out: &quot;Be none of you malignant!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Before those hooks of yours lay hold of me,</l>
    <l>Let one of you step forward, who may hear me,</l>
    <l>And then take counsel as to grappling me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They all cried out: &quot;Let Malacoda go;&quot;</l>
    <l>Whereat one started, and the rest stood still,</l>
    <l>And he came to him, saying: &quot;What avails it?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Thinkest thou, Malacoda, to behold me</l>
    <l>Advanced into this place,&quot; my Master said,</l>
    <l>&quot;Safe hitherto from all your skill of fence,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Without the will divine, and fate auspicious?</l>
    <l>Let me go on, for it in Heaven is willed</l>
    <l>That I another show this savage road.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then was his arrogance so humbled in him,</l>
    <l>That he let fall his grapnel at his feet,</l>
    <l>And to the others said: &quot;Now strike him not.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And unto me my Guide: &quot;O thou, who sittest</l>
    <l>Among the splinters of the bridge crouched down,</l>
    <l>Securely now return to me again.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wherefore I started and came swiftly to him;</l>
    <l>And all the devils forward thrust themselves,</l>
    <l>So that I feared they would not keep their compact.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And thus beheld I once afraid the soldiers</l>
    <l>Who issued under safeguard from Caprona,</l>
    <l>Seeing themselves among so many foes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Close did I press myself with all my person</l>
    <l>Beside my Leader, and turned not mine eyes</l>
    <l>From off their countenance, which was not good.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They lowered their rakes, and &quot;Wilt thou have me hit him,&quot;</l>
    <l>They said to one another, &quot;on the rump?&quot;</l>
    <l>And answered: &quot;Yes; see that thou nick him with it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But the same demon who was holding parley</l>
    <l>With my Conductor turned him very quickly,</l>
    <l>And said: &quot;Be quiet, be quiet, Scarmiglione;&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then said to us: &quot;You can no farther go</l>
    <l>Forward upon this crag, because is lying</l>
    <l>All shattered, at the bottom, the sixth arch.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if it still doth please you to go onward,</l>
    <l>Pursue your way along upon this rock;</l>
    <l>Near is another crag that yields a path.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Yesterday, five hours later than this hour,</l>
    <l>One thousand and two hundred sixty-six</l>
    <l>Years were complete, that here the way was broken.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I send in that direction some of mine</l>
    <l>To see if any one doth air himself;</l>
    <l>Go ye with them; for they will not be vicious.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Step forward, Alichino and Calcabrina,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began he to cry out, &quot;and thou, Cagnazzo;</l>
    <l>And Barbariccia, do thou guide the ten.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Come forward, Libicocco and Draghignazzo,</l>
    <l>And tusked Ciriatto and Graffiacane,</l>
    <l>And Farfarello and mad Rubicante;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Search ye all round about the boiling pitch;</l>
    <l>Let these be safe as far as the next crag,</l>
    <l>That all unbroken passes o'er the dens.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O me! what is it, Master, that I see?</l>
    <l>Pray let us go,&quot; I said, &quot;without an escort,</l>
    <l>If thou knowest how, since for myself I ask none.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If thou art as observant as thy wont is,</l>
    <l>Dost thou not see that they do gnash their teeth,</l>
    <l>And with their brows are threatening woe to us?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;I will not have thee fear;</l>
    <l>Let them gnash on, according to their fancy,</l>
    <l>Because they do it for those boiling wretches.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Along the left-hand dike they wheeled about;</l>
    <l>But first had each one thrust his tongue between</l>
    <l>His teeth towards their leader for a signal;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he had made a trumpet of his rump.</l>
  </p>
</page>