<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>When we had crossed the threshold of the door</l>
    <l>Which the perverted love of souls disuses,</l>
    <l>Because it makes the crooked way seem straight,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Re-echoing I heard it closed again;</l>
    <l>And if I had turned back mine eyes upon it,</l>
    <l>What for my failing had been fit excuse?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We mounted upward through a rifted rock,</l>
    <l>Which undulated to this side and that,</l>
    <l>Even as a wave receding and advancing.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Here it behoves us use a little art,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began my Leader, &quot;to adapt ourselves</l>
    <l>Now here, now there, to the receding side.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And this our footsteps so infrequent made,</l>
    <l>That sooner had the moon's decreasing disk</l>
    <l>Regained its bed to sink again to rest,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Than we were forth from out that needle's eye;</l>
    <l>But when we free and in the open were,</l>
    <l>There where the mountain backward piles itself,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I wearied out, and both of us uncertain</l>
    <l>About our way, we stopped upon a plain</l>
    <l>More desolate than roads across the deserts.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From where its margin borders on the void,</l>
    <l>To foot of the high bank that ever rises,</l>
    <l>A human body three times told would measure;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And far as eye of mine could wing its flight,</l>
    <l>Now on the left, and on the right flank now,</l>
    <l>The same this cornice did appear to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereon our feet had not been moved as yet,</l>
    <l>When I perceived the embankment round about,</l>
    <l>Which all right of ascent had interdicted,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To be of marble white, and so adorned</l>
    <l>With sculptures, that not only Polycletus,</l>
    <l>But Nature's self, had there been put to shame.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Angel, who came down to earth with tidings</l>
    <l>Of peace, that had been wept for many a year,</l>
    <l>And opened Heaven from its long interdict,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In front of us appeared so truthfully</l>
    <l>There sculptured in a gracious attitude,</l>
    <l>He did not seem an image that is silent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>One would have sworn that he was saying, &quot;Ave;&quot;</l>
    <l>For she was there in effigy portrayed</l>
    <l>Who turned the key to ope the exalted love,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in her mien this language had impressed,</l>
    <l>&quot;Ecce ancilla Dei,&quot; as distinctly</l>
    <l>As any figure stamps itself in wax.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Keep not thy mind upon one place alone,&quot;</l>
    <l>The gentle Master said, who had me standing</l>
    <l>Upon that side where people have their hearts;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whereat I moved mine eyes, and I beheld</l>
    <l>In rear of Mary, and upon that side</l>
    <l>Where he was standing who conducted me,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Another story on the rock imposed;</l>
    <l>Wherefore I passed Virgilius and drew near,</l>
    <l>So that before mine eyes it might be set.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There sculptured in the self-same marble were</l>
    <l>The cart and oxen, drawing the holy ark,</l>
    <l>Wherefore one dreads an office not appointed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>People appeared in front, and all of them</l>
    <l>In seven choirs divided, of two senses</l>
    <l>Made one say &quot;No,&quot; the other, &quot;Yes, they sing.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Likewise unto the smoke of the frankincense,</l>
    <l>Which there was imaged forth, the eyes and nose</l>
    <l>Were in the yes and no discordant made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Preceded there the vessel benedight,</l>
    <l>Dancing with girded loins, the humble Psalmist,</l>
    <l>And more and less than King was he in this.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Opposite, represented at the window</l>
    <l>Of a great palace, Michal looked upon him,</l>
    <l>Even as a woman scornful and afflicted.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I moved my feet from where I had been standing,</l>
    <l>To examine near at hand another story,</l>
    <l>Which after Michal glimmered white upon me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There the high glory of the Roman Prince</l>
    <l>Was chronicled, whose great beneficence</l>
    <l>Moved Gregory to his great victory;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Tis of the Emperor Trajan I am speaking;</l>
    <l>And a poor widow at his bridle stood,</l>
    <l>In attitude of weeping and of grief.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Around about him seemed it thronged and full</l>
    <l>Of cavaliers, and the eagles in the gold</l>
    <l>Above them visibly in the wind were moving.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The wretched woman in the midst of these</l>
    <l>Seemed to be saying: &quot;Give me vengeance, Lord,</l>
    <l>For my dead son, for whom my heart is breaking.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to answer her: &quot;Now wait until</l>
    <l>I shall return.&quot;  And she: &quot;My Lord,&quot; like one</l>
    <l>In whom grief is impatient, &quot;shouldst thou not</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Return?&quot;  And he: &quot;Who shall be where I am</l>
    <l>Will give it thee.&quot;  And she: &quot;Good deed of others</l>
    <l>What boots it thee, if thou neglect thine own?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence he: &quot;Now comfort thee, for it behoves me</l>
    <l>That I discharge my duty ere I move;</l>
    <l>Justice so wills, and pity doth retain me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who on no new thing has ever looked</l>
    <l>Was the creator of this visible language,</l>
    <l>Novel to us, for here it is not found.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>While I delighted me in contemplating</l>
    <l>The images of such humility,</l>
    <l>And dear to look on for their Maker's sake,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Behold, upon this side, but rare they make</l>
    <l>Their steps,&quot; the Poet murmured, &quot;many people;</l>
    <l>These will direct us to the lofty stairs.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Mine eyes, that in beholding were intent</l>
    <l>To see new things, of which they curious are,</l>
    <l>In turning round towards him were not slow.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But still I wish not, Reader, thou shouldst swerve</l>
    <l>From thy good purposes, because thou hearest</l>
    <l>How God ordaineth that the debt be paid;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Attend not to the fashion of the torment,</l>
    <l>Think of what follows; think that at the worst</l>
    <l>It cannot reach beyond the mighty sentence.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Master,&quot; began I, &quot;that which I behold</l>
    <l>Moving towards us seems to me not persons,</l>
    <l>And what I know not, so in sight I waver.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;The grievous quality</l>
    <l>Of this their torment bows them so to earth,</l>
    <l>That my own eyes at first contended with it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But look there fixedly, and disentangle</l>
    <l>By sight what cometh underneath those stones;</l>
    <l>Already canst thou see how each is stricken.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O ye proud Christians! wretched, weary ones!</l>
    <l>Who, in the vision of the mind infirm</l>
    <l>Confidence have in your backsliding steps,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Do ye not comprehend that we are worms,</l>
    <l>Born to bring forth the angelic butterfly</l>
    <l>That flieth unto judgment without screen?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Why floats aloft your spirit high in air?</l>
    <l>Like are ye unto insects undeveloped,</l>
    <l>Even as the worm in whom formation fails!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As to sustain a ceiling or a roof,</l>
    <l>In place of corbel, oftentimes a figure</l>
    <l>Is seen to join its knees unto its breast,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Which makes of the unreal real anguish</l>
    <l>Arise in him who sees it, fashioned thus</l>
    <l>Beheld I those, when I had ta'en good heed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>True is it, they were more or less bent down,</l>
    <l>According as they more or less were laden;</l>
    <l>And he who had most patience in his looks</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Weeping did seem to say, &quot;I can no more!&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>