<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>To run o'er better waters hoists its sail</l>
    <l>The little vessel of my genius now,</l>
    <l>That leaves behind itself a sea so cruel;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And of that second kingdom will I sing</l>
    <l>Wherein the human spirit doth purge itself,</l>
    <l>And to ascend to heaven becometh worthy.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But let dead Poesy here rise again,</l>
    <l>O holy Muses, since that I am yours,</l>
    <l>And here Calliope somewhat ascend,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My song accompanying with that sound,</l>
    <l>Of which the miserable magpies felt</l>
    <l>The blow so great, that they despaired of pardon.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Sweet colour of the oriental sapphire,</l>
    <l>That was upgathered in the cloudless aspect</l>
    <l>Of the pure air, as far as the first circle,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unto mine eyes did recommence delight</l>
    <l>Soon as I issued forth from the dead air,</l>
    <l>Which had with sadness filled mine eyes and breast.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The beauteous planet, that to love incites,</l>
    <l>Was making all the orient to laugh,</l>
    <l>Veiling the Fishes that were in her escort.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To the right hand I turned, and fixed my mind</l>
    <l>Upon the other pole, and saw four stars</l>
    <l>Ne'er seen before save by the primal people.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Rejoicing in their flamelets seemed the heaven.</l>
    <l>O thou septentrional and widowed site,</l>
    <l>Because thou art deprived of seeing these!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When from regarding them I had withdrawn,</l>
    <l>Turning a little to the other pole,</l>
    <l>There where the Wain had disappeared already,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw beside me an old man alone,</l>
    <l>Worthy of so much reverence in his look,</l>
    <l>That more owes not to father any son.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A long beard and with white hair intermingled</l>
    <l>He wore, in semblance like unto the tresses,</l>
    <l>Of which a double list fell on his breast.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The rays of the four consecrated stars</l>
    <l>Did so adorn his countenance with light,</l>
    <l>That him I saw as were the sun before him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Who are you? ye who, counter the blind river,</l>
    <l>Have fled away from the eternal prison?&quot;</l>
    <l>Moving those venerable plumes, he said:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Who guided you? or who has been your lamp</l>
    <l>In issuing forth out of the night profound,</l>
    <l>That ever black makes the infernal valley?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The laws of the abyss, are they thus broken?</l>
    <l>Or is there changed in heaven some council new,</l>
    <l>That being damned ye come unto my crags?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then did my Leader lay his grasp upon me,</l>
    <l>And with his words, and with his hands and signs,</l>
    <l>Reverent he made in me my knees and brow;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then answered him: &quot;I came not of myself;</l>
    <l>A Lady from Heaven descended, at whose prayers</l>
    <l>I aided this one with my company.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But since it is thy will more be unfolded</l>
    <l>Of our condition, how it truly is,</l>
    <l>Mine cannot be that this should be denied thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This one has never his last evening seen,</l>
    <l>But by his folly was so near to it</l>
    <l>That very little time was there to turn.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As I have said, I unto him was sent</l>
    <l>To rescue him, and other way was none</l>
    <l>Than this to which I have myself betaken.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I've shown him all the people of perdition,</l>
    <l>And now those spirits I intend to show</l>
    <l>Who purge themselves beneath thy guardianship.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How I have brought him would be long to tell thee.</l>
    <l>Virtue descendeth from on high that aids me</l>
    <l>To lead him to behold thee and to hear thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now may it please thee to vouchsafe his coming;</l>
    <l>He seeketh Liberty, which is so dear,</l>
    <l>As knoweth he who life for her refuses.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou know'st it; since, for her, to thee not bitter</l>
    <l>Was death in Utica, where thou didst leave</l>
    <l>The vesture, that will shine so, the great day.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By us the eternal edicts are not broken;</l>
    <l>Since this one lives, and Minos binds not me;</l>
    <l>But of that circle I, where are the chaste</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Eyes of thy Marcia, who in looks still prays thee,</l>
    <l>O holy breast, to hold her as thine own;</l>
    <l>For her love, then, incline thyself to us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Permit us through thy sevenfold realm to go;</l>
    <l>I will take back this grace from thee to her,</l>
    <l>If to be mentioned there below thou deignest.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Marcia so pleasing was unto mine eyes</l>
    <l>While I was on the other side,&quot; then said he,</l>
    <l>&quot;That every grace she wished of me I granted;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now that she dwells beyond the evil river,</l>
    <l>She can no longer move me, by that law</l>
    <l>Which, when I issued forth from there, was made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But if a Lady of Heaven do move and rule thee,</l>
    <l>As thou dost say, no flattery is needful;</l>
    <l>Let it suffice thee that for her thou ask me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Go, then, and see thou gird this one about</l>
    <l>With a smooth rush, and that thou wash his face,</l>
    <l>So that thou cleanse away all stain therefrom,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For 'twere not fitting that the eye o'ercast</l>
    <l>By any mist should go before the first</l>
    <l>Angel, who is of those of Paradise.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This little island round about its base</l>
    <l>Below there, yonder, where the billow beats it,</l>
    <l>Doth rushes bear upon its washy ooze;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>No other plant that putteth forth the leaf,</l>
    <l>Or that doth indurate, can there have life,</l>
    <l>Because it yieldeth not unto the shocks.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafter be not this way your return;</l>
    <l>The sun, which now is rising, will direct you</l>
    <l>To take the mount by easier ascent.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With this he vanished; and I raised me up</l>
    <l>Without a word, and wholly drew myself</l>
    <l>Unto my Guide, and turned mine eyes to him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he began: &quot;Son, follow thou my steps;</l>
    <l>Let us turn back, for on this side declines</l>
    <l>The plain unto its lower boundaries.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The dawn was vanquishing the matin hour</l>
    <l>Which fled before it, so that from afar</l>
    <l>I recognised the trembling of the sea.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Along the solitary plain we went</l>
    <l>As one who unto the lost road returns,</l>
    <l>And till he finds it seems to go in vain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as we were come to where the dew</l>
    <l>Fights with the sun, and, being in a part</l>
    <l>Where shadow falls, little evaporates,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Both of his hands upon the grass outspread</l>
    <l>In gentle manner did my Master place;</l>
    <l>Whence I, who of his action was aware,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Extended unto him my tearful cheeks;</l>
    <l>There did he make in me uncovered wholly</l>
    <l>That hue which Hell had covered up in me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then came we down upon the desert shore</l>
    <l>Which never yet saw navigate its waters</l>
    <l>Any that afterward had known return.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There he begirt me as the other pleased;</l>
    <l>O marvellous! for even as he culled</l>
    <l>The humble plant, such it sprang up again</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Suddenly there where he uprooted it.</l>
  </p>
</page>