<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>We were upon the summit of the stairs,</l>
    <l>Where for the second time is cut away</l>
    <l>The mountain, which ascending shriveth all.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There in like manner doth a cornice bind</l>
    <l>The hill all round about, as does the first,</l>
    <l>Save that its arc more suddenly is curved.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Shade is there none, nor sculpture that appears;</l>
    <l>So seems the bank, and so the road seems smooth,</l>
    <l>With but the livid colour of the stone.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;If to inquire we wait for people here,&quot;</l>
    <l>The Poet said, &quot;I fear that peradventure</l>
    <l>Too much delay will our election have.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then steadfast on the sun his eyes he fixed,</l>
    <l>Made his right side the centre of his motion,</l>
    <l>And turned the left part of himself about.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O thou sweet light! with trust in whom I enter</l>
    <l>Upon this novel journey, do thou lead us,&quot;</l>
    <l>Said he, &quot;as one within here should be led.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou warmest the world, thou shinest over it;</l>
    <l>If other reason prompt not otherwise,</l>
    <l>Thy rays should evermore our leaders be!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As much as here is counted for a mile,</l>
    <l>So much already there had we advanced</l>
    <l>In little time, by dint of ready will;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And tow'rds us there were heard to fly, albeit</l>
    <l>They were not visible, spirits uttering</l>
    <l>Unto Love's table courteous invitations,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The first voice that passed onward in its flight,</l>
    <l>&quot;Vinum non habent,&quot; said in accents loud,</l>
    <l>And went reiterating it behind us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And ere it wholly grew inaudible</l>
    <l>Because of distance, passed another, crying,</l>
    <l>&quot;I am Orestes!&quot; and it also stayed not.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O,&quot; said I, &quot;Father, these, what voices are they?&quot;</l>
    <l>And even as I asked, behold the third,</l>
    <l>Saying: &quot;Love those from whom ye have had evil!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the good Master said: &quot;This circle scourges</l>
    <l>The sin of envy, and on that account</l>
    <l>Are drawn from love the lashes of the scourge.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The bridle of another sound shall be;</l>
    <l>I think that thou wilt hear it, as I judge,</l>
    <l>Before thou comest to the Pass of Pardon.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But fix thine eyes athwart the air right steadfast,</l>
    <l>And people thou wilt see before us sitting,</l>
    <l>And each one close against the cliff is seated.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then wider than at first mine eyes I opened;</l>
    <l>I looked before me, and saw shades with mantles</l>
    <l>Not from the colour of the stone diverse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And when we were a little farther onward,</l>
    <l>I heard a cry of, &quot;Mary, pray for us!&quot;</l>
    <l>A cry of, &quot;Michael, Peter, and all Saints!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I do not think there walketh still on earth</l>
    <l>A man so hard, that he would not be pierced</l>
    <l>With pity at what afterward I saw.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For when I had approached so near to them</l>
    <l>That manifest to me their acts became,</l>
    <l>Drained was I at the eyes by heavy grief.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Covered with sackcloth vile they seemed to me,</l>
    <l>And one sustained the other with his shoulder,</l>
    <l>And all of them were by the bank sustained.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus do the blind, in want of livelihood,</l>
    <l>Stand at the doors of churches asking alms,</l>
    <l>And one upon another leans his head,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that in others pity soon may rise,</l>
    <l>Not only at the accent of their words,</l>
    <l>But at their aspect, which no less implores.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as unto the blind the sun comes not,</l>
    <l>So to the shades, of whom just now I spake,</l>
    <l>Heaven's light will not be bounteous of itself;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For all their lids an iron wire transpierces,</l>
    <l>And sews them up, as to a sparhawk wild</l>
    <l>Is done, because it will not quiet stay.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To me it seemed, in passing, to do outrage,</l>
    <l>Seeing the others without being seen;</l>
    <l>Wherefore I turned me to my counsel sage.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well knew he what the mute one wished to say,</l>
    <l>And therefore waited not for my demand,</l>
    <l>But said: &quot;Speak, and be brief, and to the point.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I had Virgilius upon that side</l>
    <l>Of the embankment from which one may fall,</l>
    <l>Since by no border 'tis engarlanded;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Upon the other side of me I had</l>
    <l>The shades devout, who through the horrible seam</l>
    <l>Pressed out the tears so that they bathed their cheeks.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To them I turned me, and, &quot;O people, certain,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began I, &quot;of beholding the high light,</l>
    <l>Which your desire has solely in its care,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So may grace speedily dissolve the scum</l>
    <l>Upon your consciences, that limpidly</l>
    <l>Through them descend the river of the mind,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Tell me, for dear 'twill be to me and gracious,</l>
    <l>If any soul among you here is Latian,</l>
    <l>And 'twill perchance be good for him I learn it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O brother mine, each one is citizen</l>
    <l>Of one true city; but thy meaning is,</l>
    <l>Who may have lived in Italy a pilgrim.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By way of answer this I seemed to hear</l>
    <l>A little farther on than where I stood,</l>
    <l>Whereat I made myself still nearer heard.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Among the rest I saw a shade that waited</l>
    <l>In aspect, and should any one ask how,</l>
    <l>Its chin it lifted upward like a blind man.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Spirit,&quot; I said, &quot;who stoopest to ascend,</l>
    <l>If thou art he who did reply to me,</l>
    <l>Make thyself known to me by place or name.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Sienese was I,&quot; it replied, &quot;and with</l>
    <l>The others here recleanse my guilty life,</l>
    <l>Weeping to Him to lend himself to us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Sapient I was not, although I Sapia</l>
    <l>Was called, and I was at another's harm</l>
    <l>More happy far than at my own good fortune.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And that thou mayst not think that I deceive thee,</l>
    <l>Hear if I was as foolish as I tell thee.</l>
    <l>The arc already of my years descending,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My fellow-citizens near unto Colle</l>
    <l>Were joined in battle with their adversaries,</l>
    <l>And I was praying God for what he willed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Routed were they, and turned into the bitter</l>
    <l>Passes of flight; and I, the chase beholding,</l>
    <l>A joy received unequalled by all others;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that I lifted upward my bold face</l>
    <l>Crying to God, 'Henceforth I fear thee not,'</l>
    <l>As did the blackbird at the little sunshine.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Peace I desired with God at the extreme</l>
    <l>Of my existence, and as yet would not</l>
    <l>My debt have been by penitence discharged,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Had it not been that in remembrance held me</l>
    <l>Pier Pettignano in his holy prayers,</l>
    <l>Who out of charity was grieved for me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But who art thou, that into our conditions</l>
    <l>Questioning goest, and hast thine eyes unbound</l>
    <l>As I believe, and breathing dost discourse?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Mine eyes,&quot; I said, &quot;will yet be here ta'en from me,</l>
    <l>But for short space; for small is the offence</l>
    <l>Committed by their being turned with envy.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Far greater is the fear, wherein suspended</l>
    <l>My soul is, of the torment underneath,</l>
    <l>For even now the load down there weighs on me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And she to me: &quot;Who led thee, then, among us</l>
    <l>Up here, if to return below thou thinkest?&quot;</l>
    <l>And I: &quot;He who is with me, and speaks not;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And living am I; therefore ask of me,</l>
    <l>Spirit elect, if thou wouldst have me move</l>
    <l>O'er yonder yet my mortal feet for thee.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O, this is such a novel thing to hear,&quot;</l>
    <l>She answered, &quot;that great sign it is God loves thee;</l>
    <l>Therefore with prayer of thine sometimes assist me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I implore, by what thou most desirest,</l>
    <l>If e'er thou treadest the soil of Tuscany,</l>
    <l>Well with my kindred reinstate my fame.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Them wilt thou see among that people vain</l>
    <l>Who hope in Talamone, and will lose there</l>
    <l>More hope than in discovering the Diana;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But there still more the admirals will lose.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>