<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>The while among the verdant leaves mine eyes</l>
    <l>I riveted, as he is wont to do</l>
    <l>Who wastes his life pursuing little birds,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My more than Father said unto me: &quot;Son,</l>
    <l>Come now; because the time that is ordained us</l>
    <l>More usefully should be apportioned out.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I turned my face and no less soon my steps</l>
    <l>Unto the Sages, who were speaking so</l>
    <l>They made the going of no cost to me;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And lo! were heard a song and a lament,</l>
    <l>&quot;Labia mea, Domine,&quot; in fashion</l>
    <l>Such that delight and dolence it brought forth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O my sweet Father, what is this I hear?&quot;</l>
    <l>Began I; and he answered: &quot;Shades that go</l>
    <l>Perhaps the knot unloosing of their debt.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In the same way that thoughtful pilgrims do,</l>
    <l>Who, unknown people on the road o'ertaking,</l>
    <l>Turn themselves round to them, and do not stop,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even thus, behind us with a swifter motion</l>
    <l>Coming and passing onward, gazed upon us</l>
    <l>A crowd of spirits silent and devout.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Each in his eyes was dark and cavernous,</l>
    <l>Pallid in face, and so emaciate</l>
    <l>That from the bones the skin did shape itself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I do not think that so to merest rind</l>
    <l>Could Erisichthon have been withered up</l>
    <l>By famine, when most fear he had of it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thinking within myself I said: &quot;Behold,</l>
    <l>This is the folk who lost Jerusalem,</l>
    <l>When Mary made a prey of her own son.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Their sockets were like rings without the gems;</l>
    <l>Whoever in the face of men reads 'omo'</l>
    <l>Might well in these have recognised the 'm.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Who would believe the odour of an apple,</l>
    <l>Begetting longing, could consume them so,</l>
    <l>And that of water, without knowing how?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I still was wondering what so famished them,</l>
    <l>For the occasion not yet manifest</l>
    <l>Of their emaciation and sad squalor;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And lo! from out the hollow of his head</l>
    <l>His eyes a shade turned on me, and looked keenly;</l>
    <l>Then cried aloud: &quot;What grace to me is this?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Never should I have known him by his look;</l>
    <l>But in his voice was evident to me</l>
    <l>That which his aspect had suppressed within it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This spark within me wholly re-enkindled</l>
    <l>My recognition of his altered face,</l>
    <l>And I recalled the features of Forese.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Ah, do not look at this dry leprosy,&quot;</l>
    <l>Entreated he, &quot;which doth my skin discolour,</l>
    <l>Nor at default of flesh that I may have;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me truth of thee, and who are those</l>
    <l>Two souls, that yonder make for thee an escort;</l>
    <l>Do not delay in speaking unto me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;That face of thine, which dead I once bewept,</l>
    <l>Gives me for weeping now no lesser grief,&quot;</l>
    <l>I answered him, &quot;beholding it so changed!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me, for God's sake, what thus denudes you?</l>
    <l>Make me not speak while I am marvelling,</l>
    <l>For ill speaks he who's full of other longings.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;From the eternal council</l>
    <l>Falls power into the water and the tree</l>
    <l>Behind us left, whereby I grow so thin.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>All of this people who lamenting sing,</l>
    <l>For following beyond measure appetite</l>
    <l>In hunger and thirst are here re-sanctified.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Desire to eat and drink enkindles in us</l>
    <l>The scent that issues from the apple-tree,</l>
    <l>And from the spray that sprinkles o'er the verdure;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And not a single time alone, this ground</l>
    <l>Encompassing, is refreshed our pain,--</l>
    <l>I say our pain, and ought to say our solace,--</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For the same wish doth lead us to the tree</l>
    <l>Which led the Christ rejoicing to say 'Eli,'</l>
    <l>When with his veins he liberated us.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;Forese, from that day</l>
    <l>When for a better life thou changedst worlds,</l>
    <l>Up to this time five years have not rolled round.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If sooner were the power exhausted in thee</l>
    <l>Of sinning more, than thee the hour surprised</l>
    <l>Of that good sorrow which to God reweds us,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How hast thou come up hitherward already?</l>
    <l>I thought to find thee down there underneath,</l>
    <l>Where time for time doth restitution make.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Thus speedily has led me</l>
    <l>To drink of the sweet wormwood of these torments,</l>
    <l>My Nella with her overflowing tears;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>She with her prayers devout and with her sighs</l>
    <l>Has drawn me from the coast where one where one awaits,</l>
    <l>And from the other circles set me free.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So much more dear and pleasing is to God</l>
    <l>My little widow, whom so much I loved,</l>
    <l>As in good works she is the more alone;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For the Barbagia of Sardinia</l>
    <l>By far more modest in its women is</l>
    <l>Than the Barbagia I have left her in.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O brother sweet, what wilt thou have me say?</l>
    <l>A future time is in my sight already,</l>
    <l>To which this hour will not be very old,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When from the pulpit shall be interdicted</l>
    <l>To the unblushing womankind of Florence</l>
    <l>To go about displaying breast and paps.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What savages were e'er, what Saracens,</l>
    <l>Who stood in need, to make them covered go,</l>
    <l>Of spiritual or other discipline?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But if the shameless women were assured</l>
    <l>Of what swift Heaven prepares for them, already</l>
    <l>Wide open would they have their mouths to howl;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For if my foresight here deceive me not,</l>
    <l>They shall be sad ere he has bearded cheeks</l>
    <l>Who now is hushed to sleep with lullaby.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O brother, now no longer hide thee from me;</l>
    <l>See that not only I, but all these people</l>
    <l>Are gazing there, where thou dost veil the sun.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence I to him: &quot;If thou bring back to mind</l>
    <l>What thou with me hast been and I with thee,</l>
    <l>The present memory will be grievous still.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Out of that life he turned me back who goes</l>
    <l>In front of me, two days agone when round</l>
    <l>The sister of him yonder showed herself,&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And to the sun I pointed.  &quot;Through the deep</l>
    <l>Night of the truly dead has this one led me,</l>
    <l>With this true flesh, that follows after him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thence his encouragements have led me up,</l>
    <l>Ascending and still circling round the mount</l>
    <l>That you doth straighten, whom the world made crooked.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He says that he will bear me company,</l>
    <l>Till I shall be where Beatrice will be;</l>
    <l>There it behoves me to remain without him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This is Virgilius, who thus says to me,&quot;</l>
    <l>And him I pointed at; &quot;the other is</l>
    <l>That shade for whom just now shook every slope</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Your realm, that from itself discharges him.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>