<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Whene'er is broken up the game of Zara,</l>
    <l>He who has lost remains behind despondent,</l>
    <l>The throws repeating, and in sadness learns;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The people with the other all depart;</l>
    <l>One goes in front, and one behind doth pluck him,</l>
    <l>And at his side one brings himself to mind;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He pauses not, and this and that one hears;</l>
    <l>They crowd no more to whom his hand he stretches,</l>
    <l>And from the throng he thus defends himself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even such was I in that dense multitude,</l>
    <l>Turning to them this way and that my face,</l>
    <l>And, promising, I freed myself therefrom.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There was the Aretine, who from the arms</l>
    <l>Untamed of Ghin di Tacco had his death,</l>
    <l>And he who fleeing from pursuit was drowned.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There was imploring with his hands outstretched</l>
    <l>Frederick Novello, and that one of Pisa</l>
    <l>Who made the good Marzucco seem so strong.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw Count Orso; and the soul divided</l>
    <l>By hatred and by envy from its body,</l>
    <l>As it declared, and not for crime committed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Pierre de la Brosse I say; and here provide</l>
    <l>While still on earth the Lady of Brabant,</l>
    <l>So that for this she be of no worse flock!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as I was free from all those shades</l>
    <l>Who only prayed that some one else may pray,</l>
    <l>So as to hasten their becoming holy,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Began I: &quot;It appears that thou deniest,</l>
    <l>O light of mine, expressly in some text,</l>
    <l>That orison can bend decree of Heaven;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And ne'ertheless these people pray for this.</l>
    <l>Might then their expectation bootless be?</l>
    <l>Or is to me thy saying not quite clear?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;My writing is explicit,</l>
    <l>And not fallacious is the hope of these,</l>
    <l>If with sane intellect 'tis well regarded;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For top of judgment doth not vail itself,</l>
    <l>Because the fire of love fulfils at once</l>
    <l>What he must satisfy who here installs him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And there, where I affirmed that proposition,</l>
    <l>Defect was not amended by a prayer,</l>
    <l>Because the prayer from God was separate.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Verily, in so deep a questioning</l>
    <l>Do not decide, unless she tell it thee,</l>
    <l>Who light 'twixt truth and intellect shall be.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I know not if thou understand; I speak</l>
    <l>Of Beatrice; her shalt thou see above,</l>
    <l>Smiling and happy, on this mountain's top.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;Good Leader, let us make more haste,</l>
    <l>For I no longer tire me as before;</l>
    <l>And see, e'en now the hill a shadow casts.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;We will go forward with this day&quot; he answered,</l>
    <l>&quot;As far as now is possible for us;</l>
    <l>But otherwise the fact is than thou thinkest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ere thou art up there, thou shalt see return</l>
    <l>Him, who now hides himself behind the hill,</l>
    <l>So that thou dost not interrupt his rays.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But yonder there behold! a soul that stationed</l>
    <l>All, all alone is looking hitherward;</l>
    <l>It will point out to us the quickest way.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We came up unto it; O Lombard soul,</l>
    <l>How lofty and disdainful thou didst bear thee,</l>
    <l>And grand and slow in moving of thine eyes!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nothing whatever did it say to us,</l>
    <l>But let us go our way, eying us only</l>
    <l>After the manner of a couchant lion;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Still near to it Virgilius drew, entreating</l>
    <l>That it would point us out the best ascent;</l>
    <l>And it replied not unto his demand,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But of our native land and of our life</l>
    <l>It questioned us; and the sweet Guide began:</l>
    <l>&quot;Mantua,&quot;--and the shade, all in itself recluse,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Rose tow'rds him from the place where first it was,</l>
    <l>Saying: &quot;O Mantuan, I am Sordello</l>
    <l>Of thine own land!&quot; and one embraced the other.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah! servile Italy, grief's hostelry!</l>
    <l>A ship without a pilot in great tempest!</l>
    <l>No Lady thou of Provinces, but brothel!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That noble soul was so impatient, only</l>
    <l>At the sweet sound of his own native land,</l>
    <l>To make its citizen glad welcome there;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And now within thee are not without war</l>
    <l>Thy living ones, and one doth gnaw the other</l>
    <l>Of those whom one wall and one fosse shut in!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Search, wretched one, all round about the shores</l>
    <l>Thy seaboard, and then look within thy bosom,</l>
    <l>If any part of thee enjoyeth peace!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What boots it, that for thee Justinian</l>
    <l>The bridle mend, if empty be the saddle?</l>
    <l>Withouten this the shame would be the less.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah! people, thou that oughtest to be devout,</l>
    <l>And to let Caesar sit upon the saddle,</l>
    <l>If well thou hearest what God teacheth thee,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold how fell this wild beast has become,</l>
    <l>Being no longer by the spur corrected,</l>
    <l>Since thou hast laid thy hand upon the bridle.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O German Albert! who abandonest</l>
    <l>Her that has grown recalcitrant and savage,</l>
    <l>And oughtest to bestride her saddle-bow,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>May a just judgment from the stars down fall</l>
    <l>Upon thy blood, and be it new and open,</l>
    <l>That thy successor may have fear thereof;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because thy father and thyself have suffered,</l>
    <l>By greed of those transalpine lands distrained,</l>
    <l>The garden of the empire to be waste.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Come and behold Montecchi and Cappelletti,</l>
    <l>Monaldi and Fillippeschi, careless man!</l>
    <l>Those sad already, and these doubt-depressed!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Come, cruel one! come and behold the oppression</l>
    <l>Of thy nobility, and cure their wounds,</l>
    <l>And thou shalt see how safe is Santafiore!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Come and behold thy Rome, that is lamenting,</l>
    <l>Widowed, alone, and day and night exclaims,</l>
    <l>&quot;My Caesar, why hast thou forsaken me?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Come and behold how loving are the people;</l>
    <l>And if for us no pity moveth thee,</l>
    <l>Come and be made ashamed of thy renown!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if it lawful be, O Jove Supreme!</l>
    <l>Who upon earth for us wast crucified,</l>
    <l>Are thy just eyes averted otherwhere?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Or preparation is 't, that, in the abyss</l>
    <l>Of thine own counsel, for some good thou makest</l>
    <l>From our perception utterly cut off?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For all the towns of Italy are full</l>
    <l>Of tyrants, and becometh a Marcellus</l>
    <l>Each peasant churl who plays the partisan!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Florence! well mayst thou contented be</l>
    <l>With this digression, which concerns thee not,</l>
    <l>Thanks to thy people who such forethought take!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Many at heart have justice, but shoot slowly,</l>
    <l>That unadvised they come not to the bow,</l>
    <l>But on their very lips thy people have it!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Many refuse to bear the common burden;</l>
    <l>But thy solicitous people answereth</l>
    <l>Without being asked, and crieth: &quot;I submit.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now be thou joyful, for thou hast good reason;</l>
    <l>Thou affluent, thou in peace, thou full of wisdom!</l>
    <l>If I speak true, the event conceals it not.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Athens and Lacedaemon, they who made</l>
    <l>The ancient laws, and were so civilized,</l>
    <l>Made towards living well a little sign</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Compared with thee, who makest such fine-spun</l>
    <l>Provisions, that to middle of November</l>
    <l>Reaches not what thou in October spinnest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How oft, within the time of thy remembrance,</l>
    <l>Laws, money, offices, and usages</l>
    <l>Hast thou remodelled, and renewed thy members?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if thou mind thee well, and see the light,</l>
    <l>Thou shalt behold thyself like a sick woman,</l>
    <l>Who cannot find repose upon her down,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But by her tossing wardeth off her pain.</l>
  </p>
</page>