<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>An end had put unto his reasoning</l>
    <l>The lofty Teacher, and attent was looking</l>
    <l>Into my face, if I appeared content;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I, whom a new thirst still goaded on,</l>
    <l>Without was mute, and said within: &quot;Perchance</l>
    <l>The too much questioning I make annoys him.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But that true Father, who had comprehended</l>
    <l>The timid wish, that opened not itself,</l>
    <l>By speaking gave me hardihood to speak.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence I: &quot;My sight is, Master, vivified</l>
    <l>So in thy light, that clearly I discern</l>
    <l>Whate'er thy speech importeth or describes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore I thee entreat, sweet Father dear,</l>
    <l>To teach me love, to which thou dost refer</l>
    <l>Every good action and its contrary.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Direct,&quot; he said, &quot;towards me the keen eyes</l>
    <l>Of intellect, and clear will be to thee</l>
    <l>The error of the blind, who would be leaders.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The soul, which is created apt to love,</l>
    <l>Is mobile unto everything that pleases,</l>
    <l>Soon as by pleasure she is waked to action.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Your apprehension from some real thing</l>
    <l>An image draws, and in yourselves displays it</l>
    <l>So that it makes the soul turn unto it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if, when turned, towards it she incline,</l>
    <l>Love is that inclination; it is nature,</l>
    <l>Which is by pleasure bound in you anew</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then even as the fire doth upward move</l>
    <l>By its own form, which to ascend is born,</l>
    <l>Where longest in its matter it endures,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So comes the captive soul into desire,</l>
    <l>Which is a motion spiritual, and ne'er rests</l>
    <l>Until she doth enjoy the thing beloved.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now may apparent be to thee how hidden</l>
    <l>The truth is from those people, who aver</l>
    <l>All love is in itself a laudable thing;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because its matter may perchance appear</l>
    <l>Aye to be good; but yet not each impression</l>
    <l>Is good, albeit good may be the wax.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Thy words, and my sequacious intellect,&quot;</l>
    <l>I answered him, &quot;have love revealed to me;</l>
    <l>But that has made me more impregned with doubt;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For if love from without be offered us,</l>
    <l>And with another foot the soul go not,</l>
    <l>If right or wrong she go, 'tis not her merit.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;What reason seeth here,</l>
    <l>Myself can tell thee; beyond that await</l>
    <l>For Beatrice, since 'tis a work of faith.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Every substantial form, that segregate</l>
    <l>From matter is, and with it is united,</l>
    <l>Specific power has in itself collected,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Which without act is not perceptible,</l>
    <l>Nor shows itself except by its effect,</l>
    <l>As life does in a plant by the green leaves.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But still, whence cometh the intelligence</l>
    <l>Of the first notions, man is ignorant,</l>
    <l>And the affection for the first allurements,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Which are in you as instinct in the bee</l>
    <l>To make its honey; and this first desire</l>
    <l>Merit of praise or blame containeth not.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now, that to this all others may be gathered,</l>
    <l>Innate within you is the power that counsels,</l>
    <l>And it should keep the threshold of assent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This is the principle, from which is taken</l>
    <l>Occasion of desert in you, according</l>
    <l>As good and guilty loves it takes and winnows.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Those who, in reasoning, to the bottom went,</l>
    <l>Were of this innate liberty aware,</l>
    <l>Therefore bequeathed they Ethics to the world.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Supposing, then, that from necessity</l>
    <l>Springs every love that is within you kindled,</l>
    <l>Within yourselves the power is to restrain it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The noble virtue Beatrice understands</l>
    <l>By the free will; and therefore see that thou</l>
    <l>Bear it in mind, if she should speak of it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The moon, belated almost unto midnight,</l>
    <l>Now made the stars appear to us more rare,</l>
    <l>Formed like a bucket, that is all ablaze,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And counter to the heavens ran through those paths</l>
    <l>Which the sun sets aflame, when he of Rome</l>
    <l>Sees it 'twixt Sardes and Corsicans go down;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And that patrician shade, for whom is named</l>
    <l>Pietola more than any Mantuan town,</l>
    <l>Had laid aside the burden of my lading;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence I, who reason manifest and plain</l>
    <l>In answer to my questions had received,</l>
    <l>Stood like a man in drowsy reverie.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But taken from me was this drowsiness</l>
    <l>Suddenly by a people, that behind</l>
    <l>Our backs already had come round to us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as, of old, Ismenus and Asopus</l>
    <l>Beside them saw at night the rush and throng,</l>
    <l>If but the Thebans were in need of Bacchus,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So they along that circle curve their step,</l>
    <l>From what I saw of those approaching us,</l>
    <l>Who by good-will and righteous love are ridden.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Full soon they were upon us, because running</l>
    <l>Moved onward all that mighty multitude,</l>
    <l>And two in the advance cried out, lamenting,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Mary in haste unto the mountain ran,</l>
    <l>And Caesar, that he might subdue Ilerda,</l>
    <l>Thrust at Marseilles, and then ran into Spain.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Quick! quick! so that the time may not be lost</l>
    <l>By little love!&quot; forthwith the others cried,</l>
    <l>&quot;For ardour in well-doing freshens grace!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O folk, in whom an eager fervour now</l>
    <l>Supplies perhaps delay and negligence,</l>
    <l>Put by you in well-doing, through lukewarmness,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This one who lives, and truly I lie not,</l>
    <l>Would fain go up, if but the sun relight us;</l>
    <l>So tell us where the passage nearest is.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>These were the words of him who was my Guide;</l>
    <l>And some one of those spirits said: &quot;Come on</l>
    <l>Behind us, and the opening shalt thou find;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So full of longing are we to move onward,</l>
    <l>That stay we cannot; therefore pardon us,</l>
    <l>If thou for churlishness our justice take.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I was San Zeno's Abbot at Verona,</l>
    <l>Under the empire of good Barbarossa,</l>
    <l>Of whom still sorrowing Milan holds discourse;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he has one foot in the grave already,</l>
    <l>Who shall erelong lament that monastery,</l>
    <l>And sorry be of having there had power,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because his son, in his whole body sick,</l>
    <l>And worse in mind, and who was evil-born,</l>
    <l>He put into the place of its true pastor.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If more he said, or silent was, I know not,</l>
    <l>He had already passed so far beyond us;</l>
    <l>But this I heard, and to retain it pleased me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he who was in every need my succour</l>
    <l>Said: &quot;Turn thee hitherward; see two of them</l>
    <l>Come fastening upon slothfulness their teeth.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In rear of all they shouted: &quot;Sooner were</l>
    <l>The people dead to whom the sea was opened,</l>
    <l>Than their inheritors the Jordan saw;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And those who the fatigue did not endure</l>
    <l>Unto the issue, with Anchises' son,</l>
    <l>Themselves to life withouten glory offered.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then when from us so separated were</l>
    <l>Those shades, that they no longer could be seen,</l>
    <l>Within me a new thought did entrance find,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence others many and diverse were born;</l>
    <l>And so I lapsed from one into another,</l>
    <l>That in a reverie mine eyes I closed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And meditation into dream transmuted.</l>
  </p>
</page>