<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Already was the Angel left behind us,</l>
    <l>The Angel who to the sixth round had turned us,</l>
    <l>Having erased one mark from off my face;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And those who have in justice their desire</l>
    <l>Had said to us, &quot;Beati,&quot; in their voices,</l>
    <l>With &quot;sitio,&quot; and without more ended it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I, more light than through the other passes,</l>
    <l>Went onward so, that without any labour</l>
    <l>I followed upward the swift-footed spirits;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When thus Virgilius began: &quot;The love</l>
    <l>Kindled by virtue aye another kindles,</l>
    <l>Provided outwardly its flame appear.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hence from the hour that Juvenal descended</l>
    <l>Among us into the infernal Limbo,</l>
    <l>Who made apparent to me thy affection,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My kindliness towards thee was as great</l>
    <l>As ever bound one to an unseen person,</l>
    <l>So that these stairs will now seem short to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me, and forgive me as a friend,</l>
    <l>If too great confidence let loose the rein,</l>
    <l>And as a friend now hold discourse with me;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How was it possible within thy breast</l>
    <l>For avarice to find place, 'mid so much wisdom</l>
    <l>As thou wast filled with by thy diligence?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>These words excited Statius at first</l>
    <l>Somewhat to laughter; afterward he answered:</l>
    <l>&quot;Each word of thine is love's dear sign to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Verily oftentimes do things appear</l>
    <l>Which give fallacious matter to our doubts,</l>
    <l>Instead of the true causes which are hidden!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thy question shows me thy belief to be</l>
    <l>That I was niggard in the other life,</l>
    <l>It may be from the circle where I was;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore know thou, that avarice was removed</l>
    <l>Too far from me; and this extravagance</l>
    <l>Thousands of lunar periods have punished.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And were it not that I my thoughts uplifted,</l>
    <l>When I the passage heard where thou exclaimest,</l>
    <l>As if indignant, unto human nature,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'To what impellest thou not, O cursed hunger</l>
    <l>Of gold, the appetite of mortal men?'</l>
    <l>Revolving I should feel the dismal joustings.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then I perceived the hands could spread too wide</l>
    <l>Their wings in spending, and repented me</l>
    <l>As well of that as of my other sins;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How many with shorn hair shall rise again</l>
    <l>Because of ignorance, which from this sin</l>
    <l>Cuts off repentance living and in death!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And know that the transgression which rebuts</l>
    <l>By direct opposition any sin</l>
    <l>Together with it here its verdure dries.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore if I have been among that folk</l>
    <l>Which mourns its avarice, to purify me,</l>
    <l>For its opposite has this befallen me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Now when thou sangest the relentless weapons</l>
    <l>Of the twofold affliction of Jocasta,&quot;</l>
    <l>The singer of the Songs Bucolic said,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;From that which Clio there with thee preludes,</l>
    <l>It does not seem that yet had made thee faithful</l>
    <l>That faith without which no good works suffice.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If this be so, what candles or what sun</l>
    <l>Scattered thy darkness so that thou didst trim</l>
    <l>Thy sails behind the Fisherman thereafter?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to him: &quot;Thou first directedst me</l>
    <l>Towards Parnassus, in its grots to drink,</l>
    <l>And first concerning God didst me enlighten.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou didst as he who walketh in the night,</l>
    <l>Who bears his light behind, which helps him not,</l>
    <l>But wary makes the persons after him,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When thou didst say: 'The age renews itself,</l>
    <l>Justice returns, and man's primeval time,</l>
    <l>And a new progeny descends from heaven.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Through thee I Poet was, through thee a Christian;</l>
    <l>But that thou better see what I design,</l>
    <l>To colour it will I extend my hand.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Already was the world in every part</l>
    <l>Pregnant with the true creed, disseminated</l>
    <l>By messengers of the eternal kingdom;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And thy assertion, spoken of above,</l>
    <l>With the new preachers was in unison;</l>
    <l>Whence I to visit them the custom took.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then they became so holy in my sight,</l>
    <l>That, when Domitian persecuted them,</l>
    <l>Not without tears of mine were their laments;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And all the while that I on earth remained,</l>
    <l>Them I befriended, and their upright customs</l>
    <l>Made me disparage all the other sects.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And ere I led the Greeks unto the rivers</l>
    <l>Of Thebes, in poetry, I was baptized,</l>
    <l>But out of fear was covertly a Christian,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For a long time professing paganism;</l>
    <l>And this lukewarmness caused me the fourth circle</l>
    <l>To circuit round more than four centuries.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou, therefore, who hast raised the covering</l>
    <l>That hid from me whatever good I speak of,</l>
    <l>While in ascending we have time to spare,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Tell me, in what place is our friend Terentius,</l>
    <l>Caecilius, Plautus, Varro, if thou knowest;</l>
    <l>Tell me if they are damned, and in what alley.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;These, Persius and myself, and others many,&quot;</l>
    <l>Replied my Leader, &quot;with that Grecian are</l>
    <l>Whom more than all the rest the Muses suckled,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In the first circle of the prison blind;</l>
    <l>Ofttimes we of the mountain hold discourse</l>
    <l>Which has our nurses ever with itself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Euripides is with us, Antiphon,</l>
    <l>Simonides, Agatho, and many other</l>
    <l>Greeks who of old their brows with laurel decked.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There some of thine own people may be seen,</l>
    <l>Antigone, Deiphile and Argia,</l>
    <l>And there Ismene mournful as of old.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There she is seen who pointed out Langia;</l>
    <l>There is Tiresias' daughter, and there Thetis,</l>
    <l>And there Deidamia with her sisters.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Silent already were the poets both,</l>
    <l>Attent once more in looking round about,</l>
    <l>From the ascent and from the walls released;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And four handmaidens of the day already</l>
    <l>Were left behind, and at the pole the fifth</l>
    <l>Was pointing upward still its burning horn,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What time my Guide: &quot;I think that tow'rds the edge</l>
    <l>Our dexter shoulders it behoves us turn,</l>
    <l>Circling the mount as we are wont to do.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus in that region custom was our ensign;</l>
    <l>And we resumed our way with less suspicion</l>
    <l>For the assenting of that worthy soul</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They in advance went on, and I alone</l>
    <l>Behind them, and I listened to their speech,</l>
    <l>Which gave me lessons in the art of song.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But soon their sweet discourses interrupted</l>
    <l>A tree which midway in the road we found,</l>
    <l>With apples sweet and grateful to the smell.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as a fir-tree tapers upward</l>
    <l>From bough to bough, so downwardly did that;</l>
    <l>I think in order that no one might climb it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>On that side where our pathway was enclosed</l>
    <l>Fell from the lofty rock a limpid water,</l>
    <l>And spread itself abroad upon the leaves.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Poets twain unto the tree drew near,</l>
    <l>And from among the foliage a voice</l>
    <l>Cried: &quot;Of this food ye shall have scarcity.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then said: &quot;More thoughtful Mary was of making</l>
    <l>The marriage feast complete and honourable,</l>
    <l>Than of her mouth which now for you responds;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And for their drink the ancient Roman women</l>
    <l>With water were content; and Daniel</l>
    <l>Disparaged food, and understanding won.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The primal age was beautiful as gold;</l>
    <l>Acorns it made with hunger savorous,</l>
    <l>And nectar every rivulet with thirst.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Honey and locusts were the aliments</l>
    <l>That fed the Baptist in the wilderness;</l>
    <l>Whence he is glorious, and so magnified</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As by the Evangel is revealed to you.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>