<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>After the gracious and glad salutations</l>
    <l>Had three and four times been reiterated,</l>
    <l>Sordello backward drew and said, &quot;Who are you?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Or ever to this mountain were directed</l>
    <l>The souls deserving to ascend to God,</l>
    <l>My bones were buried by Octavian.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I am Virgilius; and for no crime else</l>
    <l>Did I lose heaven, than for not having faith;&quot;</l>
    <l>In this wise then my Leader made reply.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As one who suddenly before him sees</l>
    <l>Something whereat he marvels, who believes</l>
    <l>And yet does not, saying, &quot;It is! it is not!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So he appeared; and then bowed down his brow,</l>
    <l>And with humility returned towards him,</l>
    <l>And, where inferiors embrace, embraced him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O glory of the Latians, thou,&quot; he said,</l>
    <l>&quot;Through whom our language showed what it could do</l>
    <l>O pride eternal of the place I came from,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What merit or what grace to me reveals thee?</l>
    <l>If I to hear thy words be worthy, tell me</l>
    <l>If thou dost come from Hell, and from what cloister.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Through all the circles of the doleful realm,&quot;</l>
    <l>Responded he, &quot;have I come hitherward;</l>
    <l>Heaven's power impelled me, and with that I come.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I by not doing, not by doing, lost</l>
    <l>The sight of that high sun which thou desirest,</l>
    <l>And which too late by me was recognized.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A place there is below not sad with torments,</l>
    <l>But darkness only, where the lamentations</l>
    <l>Have not the sound of wailing, but are sighs.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There dwell I with the little innocents</l>
    <l>Snatched by the teeth of Death, or ever they</l>
    <l>Were from our human sinfulness exempt.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There dwell I among those who the three saintly</l>
    <l>Virtues did not put on, and without vice</l>
    <l>The others knew and followed all of them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But if thou know and can, some indication</l>
    <l>Give us by which we may the sooner come</l>
    <l>Where Purgatory has its right beginning.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He answered: &quot;No fixed place has been assigned us;</l>
    <l>'Tis lawful for me to go up and round;</l>
    <l>So far as I can go, as guide I join thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But see already how the day declines,</l>
    <l>And to go up by night we are not able;</l>
    <l>Therefore 'tis well to think of some fair sojourn.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Souls are there on the right hand here withdrawn;</l>
    <l>If thou permit me I will lead thee to them,</l>
    <l>And thou shalt know them not without delight.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;How is this?&quot; was the answer; &quot;should one wish</l>
    <l>To mount by night would he prevented be</l>
    <l>By others? or mayhap would not have power?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And on the ground the good Sordello drew</l>
    <l>His finger, saying, &quot;See, this line alone</l>
    <l>Thou couldst not pass after the sun is gone;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not that aught else would hindrance give, however,</l>
    <l>To going up, save the nocturnal darkness;</l>
    <l>This with the want of power the will perplexes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We might indeed therewith return below,</l>
    <l>And, wandering, walk the hill-side round about,</l>
    <l>While the horizon holds the day imprisoned.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereon my Lord, as if in wonder, said:</l>
    <l>&quot;Do thou conduct us thither, where thou sayest</l>
    <l>That we can take delight in tarrying.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Little had we withdrawn us from that place,</l>
    <l>When I perceived the mount was hollowed out</l>
    <l>In fashion as the valleys here are hollowed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Thitherward,&quot; said that shade, &quot;will we repair,</l>
    <l>Where of itself the hill-side makes a lap,</l>
    <l>And there for the new day will we await.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Twixt hill and plain there was a winding path</l>
    <l>Which led us to the margin of that dell,</l>
    <l>Where dies the border more than half away.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Gold and fine silver, and scarlet and pearl-white,</l>
    <l>The Indian wood resplendent and serene,</l>
    <l>Fresh emerald the moment it is broken,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By herbage and by flowers within that hollow</l>
    <l>Planted, each one in colour would be vanquished,</l>
    <l>As by its greater vanquished is the less.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor in that place had nature painted only,</l>
    <l>But of the sweetness of a thousand odours</l>
    <l>Made there a mingled fragrance and unknown.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Salve Regina,&quot; on the green and flowers</l>
    <l>There seated, singing, spirits I beheld,</l>
    <l>Which were not visible outside the valley.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Before the scanty sun now seeks his nest,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began the Mantuan who had led us thither,</l>
    <l>&quot;Among them do not wish me to conduct you.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Better from off this ledge the acts and faces</l>
    <l>Of all of them will you discriminate,</l>
    <l>Than in the plain below received among them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who sits highest, and the semblance bears</l>
    <l>Of having what he should have done neglected,</l>
    <l>And to the others' song moves not his lips,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Rudolph the Emperor was, who had the power</l>
    <l>To heal the wounds that Italy have slain,</l>
    <l>So that through others slowly she revives.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other, who in look doth comfort him,</l>
    <l>Governed the region where the water springs,</l>
    <l>The Moldau bears the Elbe, and Elbe the sea.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>His name was Ottocar; and in swaddling-clothes</l>
    <l>Far better he than bearded Winceslaus</l>
    <l>His son, who feeds in luxury and ease.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the small-nosed, who close in council seems</l>
    <l>With him that has an aspect so benign,</l>
    <l>Died fleeing and disflowering the lily;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Look there, how he is beating at his breast!</l>
    <l>Behold the other one, who for his cheek</l>
    <l>Sighing has made of his own palm a bed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Father and father-in-law of France's Pest</l>
    <l>Are they, and know his vicious life and lewd,</l>
    <l>And hence proceeds the grief that so doth pierce them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who appears so stalwart, and chimes in,</l>
    <l>Singing, with that one of the manly nose,</l>
    <l>The cord of every valour wore begirt;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if as King had after him remained</l>
    <l>The stripling who in rear of him is sitting,</l>
    <l>Well had the valour passed from vase to vase,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Which cannot of the other heirs be said.</l>
    <l>Frederick and Jacomo possess the realms,</l>
    <l>But none the better heritage possesses.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not oftentimes upriseth through the branches</l>
    <l>The probity of man; and this He wills</l>
    <l>Who gives it, so that we may ask of Him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Eke to the large-nosed reach my words, no less</l>
    <l>Than to the other, Pier, who with him sings;</l>
    <l>Whence Provence and Apulia grieve already</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The plant is as inferior to its seed,</l>
    <l>As more than Beatrice and Margaret</l>
    <l>Costanza boasteth of her husband still.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold the monarch of the simple life,</l>
    <l>Harry of England, sitting there alone;</l>
    <l>He in his branches has a better issue.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who the lowest on the ground among them</l>
    <l>Sits looking upward, is the Marquis William,</l>
    <l>For whose sake Alessandria and her war</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Make Monferrat and Canavese weep.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>