<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>As much as 'twixt the close of the third hour</l>
    <l>And dawn of day appeareth of that sphere</l>
    <l>Which aye in fashion of a child is playing,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So much it now appeared, towards the night,</l>
    <l>Was of his course remaining to the sun;</l>
    <l>There it was evening, and 'twas midnight here;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the rays smote the middle of our faces,</l>
    <l>Because by us the mount was so encircled,</l>
    <l>That straight towards the west we now were going</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When I perceived my forehead overpowered</l>
    <l>Beneath the splendour far more than at first,</l>
    <l>And stupor were to me the things unknown,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whereat towards the summit of my brow</l>
    <l>I raised my hands, and made myself the visor</l>
    <l>Which the excessive glare diminishes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As when from off the water, or a mirror,</l>
    <l>The sunbeam leaps unto the opposite side,</l>
    <l>Ascending upward in the selfsame measure</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That it descends, and deviates as far</l>
    <l>From falling of a stone in line direct,</l>
    <l>(As demonstrate experiment and art,)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So it appeared to me that by a light</l>
    <l>Refracted there before me I was smitten;</l>
    <l>On which account my sight was swift to flee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;What is that, Father sweet, from which I cannot</l>
    <l>So fully screen my sight that it avail me,&quot;</l>
    <l>Said I, &quot;and seems towards us to be moving?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Marvel thou not, if dazzle thee as yet</l>
    <l>The family of heaven,&quot; he answered me;</l>
    <l>&quot;An angel 'tis, who comes to invite us upward.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Soon will it be, that to behold these things</l>
    <l>Shall not be grievous, but delightful to thee</l>
    <l>As much as nature fashioned thee to feel.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When we had reached the Angel benedight,</l>
    <l>With joyful voice he said: &quot;Here enter in</l>
    <l>To stairway far less steep than are the others.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We mounting were, already thence departed,</l>
    <l>And &quot;Beati misericordes&quot; was</l>
    <l>Behind us sung, &quot;Rejoice, thou that o'ercomest!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Master and myself, we two alone</l>
    <l>Were going upward, and I thought, in going,</l>
    <l>Some profit to acquire from words of his;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him directed me, thus asking:</l>
    <l>&quot;What did the spirit of Romagna mean,</l>
    <l>Mentioning interdict and partnership?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence he to me: &quot;Of his own greatest failing</l>
    <l>He knows the harm; and therefore wonder not</l>
    <l>If he reprove us, that we less may rue it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because are thither pointed your desires</l>
    <l>Where by companionship each share is lessened,</l>
    <l>Envy doth ply the bellows to your sighs.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But if the love of the supernal sphere</l>
    <l>Should upwardly direct your aspiration,</l>
    <l>There would not be that fear within your breast;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For there, as much the more as one says 'Our,'</l>
    <l>So much the more of good each one possesses,</l>
    <l>And more of charity in that cloister burns.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;I am more hungering to be satisfied,&quot;</l>
    <l>I said, &quot;than if I had before been silent,</l>
    <l>And more of doubt within my mind I gather.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How can it be, that boon distributed</l>
    <l>The more possessors can more wealthy make</l>
    <l>Therein, than if by few it be possessed?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Because thou fixest still</l>
    <l>Thy mind entirely upon earthly things,</l>
    <l>Thou pluckest darkness from the very light.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That goodness infinite and ineffable</l>
    <l>Which is above there, runneth unto love,</l>
    <l>As to a lucid body comes the sunbeam.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So much it gives itself as it finds ardour,</l>
    <l>So that as far as charity extends,</l>
    <l>O'er it increases the eternal valour.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the more people thitherward aspire,</l>
    <l>More are there to love well, and more they love there,</l>
    <l>And, as a mirror, one reflects the other.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if my reasoning appease thee not,</l>
    <l>Thou shalt see Beatrice; and she will fully</l>
    <l>Take from thee this and every other longing.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Endeavour, then, that soon may be extinct,</l>
    <l>As are the two already, the five wounds</l>
    <l>That close themselves again by being painful.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as I wished to say, &quot;Thou dost appease me,&quot;</l>
    <l>I saw that I had reached another circle,</l>
    <l>So that my eager eyes made me keep silence.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There it appeared to me that in a vision</l>
    <l>Ecstatic on a sudden I was rapt,</l>
    <l>And in a temple many persons saw;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And at the door a woman, with the sweet</l>
    <l>Behaviour of a mother, saying: &quot;Son,</l>
    <l>Why in this manner hast thou dealt with us?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Lo, sorrowing, thy father and myself</l>
    <l>Were seeking for thee;&quot;--and as here she ceased,</l>
    <l>That which appeared at first had disappeared.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then I beheld another with those waters</l>
    <l>Adown her cheeks which grief distils whenever</l>
    <l>From great disdain of others it is born,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And saying: &quot;If of that city thou art lord,</l>
    <l>For whose name was such strife among the gods,</l>
    <l>And whence doth every science scintillate,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Avenge thyself on those audacious arms</l>
    <l>That clasped our daughter, O Pisistratus;&quot;</l>
    <l>And the lord seemed to me benign and mild</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To answer her with aspect temperate:</l>
    <l>&quot;What shall we do to those who wish us ill,</l>
    <l>If he who loves us be by us condemned?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then saw I people hot in fire of wrath,</l>
    <l>With stones a young man slaying, clamorously</l>
    <l>Still crying to each other, &quot;Kill him! kill him!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And him I saw bow down, because of death</l>
    <l>That weighed already on him, to the earth,</l>
    <l>But of his eyes made ever gates to heaven,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Imploring the high Lord, in so great strife,</l>
    <l>That he would pardon those his persecutors,</l>
    <l>With such an aspect as unlocks compassion.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Soon as my soul had outwardly returned</l>
    <l>To things external to it which are true,</l>
    <l>Did I my not false errors recognize.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Leader, who could see me bear myself</l>
    <l>Like to a man that rouses him from sleep,</l>
    <l>Exclaimed: &quot;What ails thee, that thou canst not stand?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But hast been coming more than half a league</l>
    <l>Veiling thine eyes, and with thy legs entangled,</l>
    <l>In guise of one whom wine or sleep subdues?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O my sweet Father, if thou listen to me,</l>
    <l>I'll tell thee,&quot; said I, &quot;what appeared to me,</l>
    <l>When thus from me my legs were ta'en away.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he: &quot;If thou shouldst have a hundred masks</l>
    <l>Upon thy face, from me would not be shut</l>
    <l>Thy cogitations, howsoever small.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What thou hast seen was that thou mayst not fail</l>
    <l>To ope thy heart unto the waters of peace,</l>
    <l>Which from the eternal fountain are diffused.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I did not ask, 'What ails thee?' as he does</l>
    <l>Who only looketh with the eyes that see not</l>
    <l>When of the soul bereft the body lies,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But asked it to give vigour to thy feet;</l>
    <l>Thus must we needs urge on the sluggards, slow</l>
    <l>To use their wakefulness when it returns.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We passed along, athwart the twilight peering</l>
    <l>Forward as far as ever eye could stretch</l>
    <l>Against the sunbeams serotine and lucent;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And lo! by slow degrees a smoke approached</l>
    <l>In our direction, sombre as the night,</l>
    <l>Nor was there place to hide one's self therefrom.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This of our eyes and the pure air bereft us.</l>
  </p>
</page>