<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Ill strives the will against a better will;</l>
    <l>Therefore, to pleasure him, against my pleasure</l>
    <l>I drew the sponge not saturate from the water.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Onward I moved, and onward moved my Leader,</l>
    <l>Through vacant places, skirting still the rock,</l>
    <l>As on a wall close to the battlements;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For they that through their eyes pour drop by drop</l>
    <l>The malady which all the world pervades,</l>
    <l>On the other side too near the verge approach.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Accursed mayst thou be, thou old she-wolf,</l>
    <l>That more than all the other beasts hast prey,</l>
    <l>Because of hunger infinitely hollow!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O heaven, in whose gyrations some appear</l>
    <l>To think conditions here below are changed,</l>
    <l>When will he come through whom she shall depart?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Onward we went with footsteps slow and scarce,</l>
    <l>And I attentive to the shades I heard</l>
    <l>Piteously weeping and bemoaning them;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I by peradventure heard &quot;Sweet Mary!&quot;</l>
    <l>Uttered in front of us amid the weeping</l>
    <l>Even as a woman does who is in child-birth;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in continuance: &quot;How poor thou wast</l>
    <l>Is manifested by that hostelry</l>
    <l>Where thou didst lay thy sacred burden down.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafterward I heard: &quot;O good Fabricius,</l>
    <l>Virtue with poverty didst thou prefer</l>
    <l>To the possession of great wealth with vice.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So pleasurable were these words to me</l>
    <l>That I drew farther onward to have knowledge</l>
    <l>Touching that spirit whence they seemed to come.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He furthermore was speaking of the largess</l>
    <l>Which Nicholas unto the maidens gave,</l>
    <l>In order to conduct their youth to honour.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O soul that dost so excellently speak,</l>
    <l>Tell me who wast thou,&quot; said I, &quot;and why only</l>
    <l>Thou dost renew these praises well deserved?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not without recompense shall be thy word,</l>
    <l>If I return to finish the short journey</l>
    <l>Of that life which is flying to its end.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he: &quot;I'll tell thee, not for any comfort</l>
    <l>I may expect from earth, but that so much</l>
    <l>Grace shines in thee or ever thou art dead.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I was the root of that malignant plant</l>
    <l>Which overshadows all the Christian world,</l>
    <l>So that good fruit is seldom gathered from it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But if Douay and Ghent, and Lille and Bruges</l>
    <l>Had Power, soon vengeance would be taken on it;</l>
    <l>And this I pray of Him who judges all.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hugh Capet was I called upon the earth;</l>
    <l>From me were born the Louises and Philips,</l>
    <l>By whom in later days has France been governed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I was the son of a Parisian butcher,</l>
    <l>What time the ancient kings had perished all,</l>
    <l>Excepting one, contrite in cloth of gray.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I found me grasping in my hands the rein</l>
    <l>Of the realm's government, and so great power</l>
    <l>Of new acquest, and so with friends abounding,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That to the widowed diadem promoted</l>
    <l>The head of mine own offspring was, from whom</l>
    <l>The consecrated bones of these began.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So long as the great dowry of Provence</l>
    <l>Out of my blood took not the sense of shame,</l>
    <l>'Twas little worth, but still it did no harm.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then it began with falsehood and with force</l>
    <l>Its rapine; and thereafter, for amends,</l>
    <l>Took Ponthieu, Normandy, and Gascony.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Charles came to Italy, and for amends</l>
    <l>A victim made of Conradin, and then</l>
    <l>Thrust Thomas back to heaven, for amends.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A time I see, not very distant now,</l>
    <l>Which draweth forth another Charles from France,</l>
    <l>The better to make known both him and his.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unarmed he goes, and only with the lance</l>
    <l>That Judas jousted with; and that he thrusts</l>
    <l>So that he makes the paunch of Florence burst.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He thence not land, but sin and infamy,</l>
    <l>Shall gain, so much more grievous to himself</l>
    <l>As the more light such damage he accounts.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other, now gone forth, ta'en in his ship,</l>
    <l>See I his daughter sell, and chaffer for her</l>
    <l>As corsairs do with other female slaves.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What more, O Avarice, canst thou do to us,</l>
    <l>Since thou my blood so to thyself hast drawn,</l>
    <l>It careth not for its own proper flesh?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That less may seem the future ill and past,</l>
    <l>I see the flower-de-luce Alagna enter,</l>
    <l>And Christ in his own Vicar captive made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I see him yet another time derided;</l>
    <l>I see renewed the vinegar and gall,</l>
    <l>And between living thieves I see him slain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I see the modern Pilate so relentless,</l>
    <l>This does not sate him, but without decretal</l>
    <l>He to the temple bears his sordid sails!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When, O my Lord! shall I be joyful made</l>
    <l>By looking on the vengeance which, concealed,</l>
    <l>Makes sweet thine anger in thy secrecy?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What I was saying of that only bride</l>
    <l>Of the Holy Ghost, and which occasioned thee</l>
    <l>To turn towards me for some commentary,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So long has been ordained to all our prayers</l>
    <l>As the day lasts; but when the night comes on,</l>
    <l>Contrary sound we take instead thereof.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>At that time we repeat Pygmalion,</l>
    <l>Of whom a traitor, thief, and parricide</l>
    <l>Made his insatiable desire of gold;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the misery of avaricious Midas,</l>
    <l>That followed his inordinate demand,</l>
    <l>At which forevermore one needs but laugh.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The foolish Achan each one then records,</l>
    <l>And how he stole the spoils; so that the wrath</l>
    <l>Of Joshua still appears to sting him here.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then we accuse Sapphira with her husband,</l>
    <l>We laud the hoof-beats Heliodorus had,</l>
    <l>And the whole mount in infamy encircles</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Polymnestor who murdered Polydorus.</l>
    <l>Here finally is cried: 'O Crassus, tell us,</l>
    <l>For thou dost know, what is the taste of gold?'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Sometimes we speak, one loud, another low,</l>
    <l>According to desire of speech, that spurs us</l>
    <l>To greater now and now to lesser pace.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But in the good that here by day is talked of,</l>
    <l>Erewhile alone I was not; yet near by</l>
    <l>No other person lifted up his voice.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From him already we departed were,</l>
    <l>And made endeavour to o'ercome the road</l>
    <l>As much as was permitted to our power,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When I perceived, like something that is falling,</l>
    <l>The mountain tremble, whence a chill seized on me,</l>
    <l>As seizes him who to his death is going.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Certes so violently shook not Delos,</l>
    <l>Before Latona made her nest therein</l>
    <l>To give birth to the two eyes of the heaven.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then upon all sides there began a cry,</l>
    <l>Such that the Master drew himself towards me,</l>
    <l>Saying, &quot;Fear not, while I am guiding thee.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Gloria in excelsis Deo,&quot; all</l>
    <l>Were saying, from what near I comprehended,</l>
    <l>Where it was possible to hear the cry.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We paused immovable and in suspense,</l>
    <l>Even as the shepherds who first heard that song,</l>
    <l>Until the trembling ceased, and it was finished.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then we resumed again our holy path,</l>
    <l>Watching the shades that lay upon the ground,</l>
    <l>Already turned to their accustomed plaint.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>No ignorance ever with so great a strife</l>
    <l>Had rendered me importunate to know,</l>
    <l>If erreth not in this my memory,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As meditating then I seemed to have;</l>
    <l>Nor out of haste to question did I dare,</l>
    <l>Nor of myself I there could aught perceive;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So I went onward timorous and thoughtful.</l>
  </p>
</page>