<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>When the Septentrion of the highest heaven</l>
    <l>(Which never either setting knew or rising,</l>
    <l>Nor veil of other cloud than that of sin,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And which made every one therein aware</l>
    <l>Of his own duty, as the lower makes</l>
    <l>Whoever turns the helm to come to port)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Motionless halted, the veracious people,</l>
    <l>That came at first between it and the Griffin,</l>
    <l>Turned themselves to the car, as to their peace.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one of them, as if by Heaven commissioned,</l>
    <l>Singing, &quot;Veni, sponsa, de Libano&quot;</l>
    <l>Shouted three times, and all the others after.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the Blessed at the final summons</l>
    <l>Shall rise up quickened each one from his cavern,</l>
    <l>Uplifting light the reinvested flesh,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So upon that celestial chariot</l>
    <l>A hundred rose 'ad vocem tanti senis,'</l>
    <l>Ministers and messengers of life eternal.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>They all were saying, &quot;Benedictus qui venis,&quot;</l>
    <l>And, scattering flowers above and round about,</l>
    <l>&quot;Manibus o date lilia plenis.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ere now have I beheld, as day began,</l>
    <l>The eastern hemisphere all tinged with rose,</l>
    <l>And the other heaven with fair serene adorned;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the sun's face, uprising, overshadowed</l>
    <l>So that by tempering influence of vapours</l>
    <l>For a long interval the eye sustained it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus in the bosom of a cloud of flowers</l>
    <l>Which from those hands angelical ascended,</l>
    <l>And downward fell again inside and out,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Over her snow-white veil with olive cinct</l>
    <l>Appeared a lady under a green mantle,</l>
    <l>Vested in colour of the living flame.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And my own spirit, that already now</l>
    <l>So long a time had been, that in her presence</l>
    <l>Trembling with awe it had not stood abashed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Without more knowledge having by mine eyes,</l>
    <l>Through occult virtue that from her proceeded</l>
    <l>Of ancient love the mighty influence felt.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as on my vision smote the power</l>
    <l>Sublime, that had already pierced me through</l>
    <l>Ere from my boyhood I had yet come forth,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To the left hand I turned with that reliance</l>
    <l>With which the little child runs to his mother,</l>
    <l>When he has fear, or when he is afflicted,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To say unto Virgilius: &quot;Not a drachm</l>
    <l>Of blood remains in me, that does not tremble;</l>
    <l>I know the traces of the ancient flame.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But us Virgilius of himself deprived</l>
    <l>Had left, Virgilius, sweetest of all fathers,</l>
    <l>Virgilius, to whom I for safety gave me:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor whatsoever lost the ancient mother</l>
    <l>Availed my cheeks now purified from dew,</l>
    <l>That weeping they should not again be darkened.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Dante, because Virgilius has departed</l>
    <l>Do not weep yet, do not weep yet awhile;</l>
    <l>For by another sword thou need'st must weep.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>E'en as an admiral, who on poop and prow</l>
    <l>Comes to behold the people that are working</l>
    <l>In other ships, and cheers them to well-doing,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Upon the left hand border of the car,</l>
    <l>When at the sound I turned of my own name,</l>
    <l>Which of necessity is here recorded,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw the Lady, who erewhile appeared</l>
    <l>Veiled underneath the angelic festival,</l>
    <l>Direct her eyes to me across the river.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Although the veil, that from her head descended,</l>
    <l>Encircled with the foliage of Minerva,</l>
    <l>Did not permit her to appear distinctly,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In attitude still royally majestic</l>
    <l>Continued she, like unto one who speaks,</l>
    <l>And keeps his warmest utterance in reserve:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Look at me well; in sooth I'm Beatrice!</l>
    <l>How didst thou deign to come unto the Mountain?</l>
    <l>Didst thou not know that man is happy here?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Mine eyes fell downward into the clear fountain,</l>
    <l>But, seeing myself therein, I sought the grass,</l>
    <l>So great a shame did weigh my forehead down.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As to the son the mother seems superb,</l>
    <l>So she appeared to me; for somewhat bitter</l>
    <l>Tasteth the savour of severe compassion.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Silent became she, and the Angels sang</l>
    <l>Suddenly, &quot;In te, Domine, speravi:&quot;</l>
    <l>But beyond 'pedes meos' did not pass.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the snow among the living rafters</l>
    <l>Upon the back of Italy congeals,</l>
    <l>Blown on and drifted by Sclavonian winds,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And then, dissolving, trickles through itself</l>
    <l>Whene'er the land that loses shadow breathes,</l>
    <l>So that it seems a fire that melts a taper;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>E'en thus was I without a tear or sigh,</l>
    <l>Before the song of those who sing for ever</l>
    <l>After the music of the eternal spheres.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But when I heard in their sweet melodies</l>
    <l>Compassion for me, more than had they said,</l>
    <l>&quot;O wherefore, lady, dost thou thus upbraid him?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The ice, that was about my heart congealed,</l>
    <l>To air and water changed, and in my anguish</l>
    <l>Through mouth and eyes came gushing from my breast.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>She, on the right-hand border of the car</l>
    <l>Still firmly standing, to those holy beings</l>
    <l>Thus her discourse directed afterwards:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Ye keep your watch in the eternal day,</l>
    <l>So that nor night nor sleep can steal from you</l>
    <l>One step the ages make upon their path;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore my answer is with greater care,</l>
    <l>That he may hear me who is weeping yonder,</l>
    <l>So that the sin and dole be of one measure.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not only by the work of those great wheels,</l>
    <l>That destine every seed unto some end,</l>
    <l>According as the stars are in conjunction,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But by the largess of celestial graces,</l>
    <l>Which have such lofty vapours for their rain</l>
    <l>That near to them our sight approaches not,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Such had this man become in his new life</l>
    <l>Potentially, that every righteous habit</l>
    <l>Would have made admirable proof in him;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But so much more malignant and more savage</l>
    <l>Becomes the land untilled and with bad seed,</l>
    <l>The more good earthly vigour it possesses.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Some time did I sustain him with my look;</l>
    <l>Revealing unto him my youthful eyes,</l>
    <l>I led him with me turned in the right way.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as ever of my second age</l>
    <l>I was upon the threshold and changed life,</l>
    <l>Himself from me he took and gave to others.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When from the flesh to spirit I ascended,</l>
    <l>And beauty and virtue were in me increased,</l>
    <l>I was to him less dear and less delightful;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And into ways untrue he turned his steps,</l>
    <l>Pursuing the false images of good,</l>
    <l>That never any promises fulfil;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor prayer for inspiration me availed,</l>
    <l>By means of which in dreams and otherwise</l>
    <l>I called him back, so little did he heed them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So low he fell, that all appliances</l>
    <l>For his salvation were already short,</l>
    <l>Save showing him the people of perdition.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For this I visited the gates of death,</l>
    <l>And unto him, who so far up has led him,</l>
    <l>My intercessions were with weeping borne.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>God's lofty fiat would be violated,</l>
    <l>If Lethe should be passed, and if such viands</l>
    <l>Should tasted be, withouten any scot</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Of penitence, that gushes forth in tears.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>