<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Our Father, thou who dwellest in the heavens,</l>
    <l>Not circumscribed, but from the greater love</l>
    <l>Thou bearest to the first effects on high,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Praised be thy name and thine omnipotence</l>
    <l>By every creature, as befitting is</l>
    <l>To render thanks to thy sweet effluence.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Come unto us the peace of thy dominion,</l>
    <l>For unto it we cannot of ourselves,</l>
    <l>If it come not, with all our intellect.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as thine own Angels of their will</l>
    <l>Make sacrifice to thee, Hosanna singing,</l>
    <l>So may all men make sacrifice of theirs.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Give unto us this day our daily manna,</l>
    <l>Withouten which in this rough wilderness</l>
    <l>Backward goes he who toils most to advance.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as we the trespass we have suffered</l>
    <l>Pardon in one another, pardon thou</l>
    <l>Benignly, and regard not our desert.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Our virtue, which is easily o'ercome,</l>
    <l>Put not to proof with the old Adversary,</l>
    <l>But thou from him who spurs it so, deliver.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This last petition verily, dear Lord,</l>
    <l>Not for ourselves is made, who need it not,</l>
    <l>But for their sake who have remained behind us.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus for themselves and us good furtherance</l>
    <l>Those shades imploring, went beneath a weight</l>
    <l>Like unto that of which we sometimes dream,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unequally in anguish round and round</l>
    <l>And weary all, upon that foremost cornice,</l>
    <l>Purging away the smoke-stains of the world.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If there good words are always said for us,</l>
    <l>What may not here be said and done for them,</l>
    <l>By those who have a good root to their will?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well may we help them wash away the marks</l>
    <l>That hence they carried, so that clean and light</l>
    <l>They may ascend unto the starry wheels!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Ah! so may pity and justice you disburden</l>
    <l>Soon, that ye may have power to move the wing,</l>
    <l>That shall uplift you after your desire,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Show us on which hand tow'rd the stairs the way</l>
    <l>Is shortest, and if more than one the passes,</l>
    <l>Point us out that which least abruptly falls;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For he who cometh with me, through the burden</l>
    <l>Of Adam's flesh wherewith he is invested,</l>
    <l>Against his will is chary of his climbing.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The words of theirs which they returned to those</l>
    <l>That he whom I was following had spoken,</l>
    <l>It was not manifest from whom they came,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But it was said: &quot;To the right hand come with us</l>
    <l>Along the bank, and ye shall find a pass</l>
    <l>Possible for living person to ascend.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And were I not impeded by the stone,</l>
    <l>Which this proud neck of mine doth subjugate,</l>
    <l>Whence I am forced to hold my visage down,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Him, who still lives and does not name himself,</l>
    <l>Would I regard, to see if I may know him</l>
    <l>And make him piteous unto this burden.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A Latian was I, and born of a great Tuscan;</l>
    <l>Guglielmo Aldobrandeschi was my father;</l>
    <l>I know not if his name were ever with you.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The ancient blood and deeds of gallantry</l>
    <l>Of my progenitors so arrogant made me</l>
    <l>That, thinking not upon the common mother,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>All men I held in scorn to such extent</l>
    <l>I died therefor, as know the Sienese,</l>
    <l>And every child in Campagnatico.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I am Omberto; and not to me alone</l>
    <l>Has pride done harm, but all my kith and kin</l>
    <l>Has with it dragged into adversity.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And here must I this burden bear for it</l>
    <l>Till God be satisfied, since I did not</l>
    <l>Among the living, here among the dead.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Listening I downward bent my countenance;</l>
    <l>And one of them, not this one who was speaking,</l>
    <l>Twisted himself beneath the weight that cramps him,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And looked at me, and knew me, and called out,</l>
    <l>Keeping his eyes laboriously fixed</l>
    <l>On me, who all bowed down was going with them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O,&quot; asked I him, &quot;art thou not Oderisi,</l>
    <l>Agobbio's honour, and honour of that art</l>
    <l>Which is in Paris called illuminating?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Brother,&quot; said he, &quot;more laughing are the leaves</l>
    <l>Touched by the brush of Franco Bolognese;</l>
    <l>All his the honour now, and mine in part.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In sooth I had not been so courteous</l>
    <l>While I was living, for the great desire</l>
    <l>Of excellence, on which my heart was bent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here of such pride is paid the forfeiture;</l>
    <l>And yet I should not be here, were it not</l>
    <l>That, having power to sin, I turned to God.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O thou vain glory of the human powers,</l>
    <l>How little green upon thy summit lingers,</l>
    <l>If't be not followed by an age of grossness!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In painting Cimabue thought that he</l>
    <l>Should hold the field, now Giotto has the cry,</l>
    <l>So that the other's fame is growing dim.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So has one Guido from the other taken</l>
    <l>The glory of our tongue, and he perchance</l>
    <l>Is born, who from the nest shall chase them both.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Naught is this mundane rumour but a breath</l>
    <l>Of wind, that comes now this way and now that,</l>
    <l>And changes name, because it changes side.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What fame shalt thou have more, if old peel off</l>
    <l>From thee thy flesh, than if thou hadst been dead</l>
    <l>Before thou left the 'pappo' and the 'dindi,'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ere pass a thousand years? which is a shorter</l>
    <l>Space to the eterne, than twinkling of an eye</l>
    <l>Unto the circle that in heaven wheels slowest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With him, who takes so little of the road</l>
    <l>In front of me, all Tuscany resounded;</l>
    <l>And now he scarce is lisped of in Siena,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Where he was lord, what time was overthrown</l>
    <l>The Florentine delirium, that superb</l>
    <l>Was at that day as now 'tis prostitute.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Your reputation is the colour of grass</l>
    <l>Which comes and goes, and that discolours it</l>
    <l>By which it issues green from out the earth.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;Thy true speech fills my heart with good</l>
    <l>Humility, and great tumour thou assuagest;</l>
    <l>But who is he, of whom just now thou spakest?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;That,&quot; he replied, &quot;is Provenzan Salvani,</l>
    <l>And he is here because he had presumed</l>
    <l>To bring Siena all into his hands.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He has gone thus, and goeth without rest</l>
    <l>E'er since he died; such money renders back</l>
    <l>In payment he who is on earth too daring.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;If every spirit who awaits</l>
    <l>The verge of life before that he repent,</l>
    <l>Remains below there and ascends not hither,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>(Unless good orison shall him bestead,)</l>
    <l>Until as much time as he lived be passed,</l>
    <l>How was the coming granted him in largess?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;When he in greatest splendour lived,&quot; said he,</l>
    <l>&quot;Freely upon the Campo of Siena,</l>
    <l>All shame being laid aside, he placed himself;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And there to draw his friend from the duress</l>
    <l>Which in the prison-house of Charles he suffered,</l>
    <l>He brought himself to tremble in each vein.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I say no more, and know that I speak darkly;</l>
    <l>Yet little time shall pass before thy neighbours</l>
    <l>Will so demean themselves that thou canst gloss it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This action has released him from those confines.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>