<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>It was the hour when the diurnal heat</l>
    <l>No more can warm the coldness of the moon,</l>
    <l>Vanquished by earth, or peradventure Saturn,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When geomancers their Fortuna Major</l>
    <l>See in the orient before the dawn</l>
    <l>Rise by a path that long remains not dim,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There came to me in dreams a stammering woman,</l>
    <l>Squint in her eyes, and in her feet distorted,</l>
    <l>With hands dissevered and of sallow hue.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I looked at her; and as the sun restores</l>
    <l>The frigid members which the night benumbs,</l>
    <l>Even thus my gaze did render voluble</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Her tongue, and made her all erect thereafter</l>
    <l>In little while, and the lost countenance</l>
    <l>As love desires it so in her did colour.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When in this wise she had her speech unloosed,</l>
    <l>She 'gan to sing so, that with difficulty</l>
    <l>Could I have turned my thoughts away from her.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;I am,&quot; she sang, &quot;I am the Siren sweet</l>
    <l>Who mariners amid the main unman,</l>
    <l>So full am I of pleasantness to hear.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I drew Ulysses from his wandering way</l>
    <l>Unto my song, and he who dwells with me</l>
    <l>Seldom departs so wholly I content him.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Her mouth was not yet closed again, before</l>
    <l>Appeared a Lady saintly and alert</l>
    <l>Close at my side to put her to confusion.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Virgilius, O Virgilius! who is this?&quot;</l>
    <l>Sternly she said; and he was drawing near</l>
    <l>With eyes still fixed upon that modest one.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>She seized the other and in front laid open,</l>
    <l>Rending her garments, and her belly showed me;</l>
    <l>This waked me with the stench that issued from it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I turned mine eyes, and good Virgilius said:</l>
    <l>&quot;At least thrice have I called thee; rise and come;</l>
    <l>Find we the opening by which thou mayst enter.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I rose; and full already of high day</l>
    <l>Were all the circles of the Sacred Mountain,</l>
    <l>And with the new sun at our back we went.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Following behind him, I my forehead bore</l>
    <l>Like unto one who has it laden with thought,</l>
    <l>Who makes himself the half arch of a bridge,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When I heard say, &quot;Come, here the passage is,&quot;</l>
    <l>Spoken in a manner gentle and benign,</l>
    <l>Such as we hear not in this mortal region.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With open wings, which of a swan appeared,</l>
    <l>Upward he turned us who thus spake to us,</l>
    <l>Between the two walls of the solid granite.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He moved his pinions afterwards and fanned us,</l>
    <l>Affirming those 'qui lugent' to be blessed,</l>
    <l>For they shall have their souls with comfort filled.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;What aileth thee, that aye to earth thou gazest?&quot;</l>
    <l>To me my Guide began to say, we both</l>
    <l>Somewhat beyond the Angel having mounted.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;With such misgiving makes me go</l>
    <l>A vision new, which bends me to itself,</l>
    <l>So that I cannot from the thought withdraw me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Didst thou behold,&quot; he said, &quot;that old enchantress,</l>
    <l>Who sole above us henceforth is lamented?</l>
    <l>Didst thou behold how man is freed from her?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Suffice it thee, and smite earth with thy heels,</l>
    <l>Thine eyes lift upward to the lure, that whirls</l>
    <l>The Eternal King with revolutions vast.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the hawk, that first his feet surveys,</l>
    <l>Then turns him to the call and stretches forward,</l>
    <l>Through the desire of food that draws him thither,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Such I became, and such, as far as cleaves</l>
    <l>The rock to give a way to him who mounts,</l>
    <l>Went on to where the circling doth begin.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>On the fifth circle when I had come forth,</l>
    <l>People I saw upon it who were weeping,</l>
    <l>Stretched prone upon the ground, all downward turned.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Adhaesit pavimento anima mea,&quot;</l>
    <l>I heard them say with sighings so profound,</l>
    <l>That hardly could the words be understood.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O ye elect of God, whose sufferings</l>
    <l>Justice and Hope both render less severe,</l>
    <l>Direct ye us towards the high ascents.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;If ye are come secure from this prostration,</l>
    <l>And wish to find the way most speedily,</l>
    <l>Let your right hands be evermore outside.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus did the Poet ask, and thus was answered</l>
    <l>By them somewhat in front of us; whence I</l>
    <l>In what was spoken divined the rest concealed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And unto my Lord's eyes mine eyes I turned;</l>
    <l>Whence he assented with a cheerful sign</l>
    <l>To what the sight of my desire implored.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When of myself I could dispose at will,</l>
    <l>Above that creature did I draw myself,</l>
    <l>Whose words before had caused me to take note,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Saying: &quot;O Spirit, in whom weeping ripens</l>
    <l>That without which to God we cannot turn,</l>
    <l>Suspend awhile for me thy greater care.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Who wast thou, and why are your backs turned upwards,</l>
    <l>Tell me, and if thou wouldst that I procure thee</l>
    <l>Anything there whence living I departed.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he to me: &quot;Wherefore our backs the heaven</l>
    <l>Turns to itself, know shalt thou; but beforehand</l>
    <l>'Scias quod ego fui successor Petri.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Between Siestri and Chiaveri descends</l>
    <l>A river beautiful, and of its name</l>
    <l>The title of my blood its summit makes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A month and little more essayed I how</l>
    <l>Weighs the great cloak on him from mire who keeps it,</l>
    <l>For all the other burdens seem a feather.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Tardy, ah woe is me! was my conversion;</l>
    <l>But when the Roman Shepherd I was made,</l>
    <l>Then I discovered life to be a lie.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw that there the heart was not at rest,</l>
    <l>Nor farther in that life could one ascend;</l>
    <l>Whereby the love of this was kindled in me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Until that time a wretched soul and parted</l>
    <l>From God was I, and wholly avaricious;</l>
    <l>Now, as thou seest, I here am punished for it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What avarice does is here made manifest</l>
    <l>In the purgation of these souls converted,</l>
    <l>And no more bitter pain the Mountain has.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as our eye did not uplift itself</l>
    <l>Aloft, being fastened upon earthly things,</l>
    <l>So justice here has merged it in the earth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As avarice had extinguished our affection</l>
    <l>For every good, whereby was action lost,</l>
    <l>So justice here doth hold us in restraint,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Bound and imprisoned by the feet and hands;</l>
    <l>And so long as it pleases the just Lord</l>
    <l>Shall we remain immovable and prostrate.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I on my knees had fallen, and wished to speak;</l>
    <l>But even as I began, and he was 'ware,</l>
    <l>Only by listening, of my reverence,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;What cause,&quot; he said, &quot;has downward bent thee thus?&quot;</l>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;For your own dignity,</l>
    <l>Standing, my conscience stung me with remorse.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Straighten thy legs, and upward raise thee, brother,&quot;</l>
    <l>He answered: &quot;Err not, fellow-servant am I</l>
    <l>With thee and with the others to one power.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If e'er that holy, evangelic sound,</l>
    <l>Which sayeth 'neque nubent,' thou hast heard,</l>
    <l>Well canst thou see why in this wise I speak.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now go; no longer will I have thee linger,</l>
    <l>Because thy stay doth incommode my weeping,</l>
    <l>With which I ripen that which thou hast said.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>On earth I have a grandchild named Alagia,</l>
    <l>Good in herself, unless indeed our house</l>
    <l>Malevolent may make her by example,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And she alone remains to me on earth.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>