<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>By now the sun was crossing the horizon</l>
		<l>of the meridian whose highest point</l>
		<l>covers Jerusalem; and from the Ganges,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>night, circling opposite the sun, was moving</l>
		<l>together with the Scales that, when the length</l>
		<l>of dark defeats the day, desert night&apos;s hands;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that, above the shore that I had reached,</l>
		<l>the fair Aurora&apos;s white and scarlet cheeks</l>
		<l>were, as Aurora aged, becoming orange.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We still were by the sea, like those who think</l>
		<l>about the journey they will undertake,</l>
		<l>who go in heart but in the body stay.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as Mars, when it is overcome</l>
		<l>by the invading mists of dawn, glows red</l>
		<l>above the waters&apos; plain, low in the west,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so there appeared to me-and may I see it</l>
		<l>again-a light that crossed the sea: so swift,</l>
		<l>there is no flight of bird to equal it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When, for a moment, I&apos;d withdrawn my eyes</l>
		<l>that I might ask a question of my guide,</l>
		<l>I saw that light again, larger, more bright.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, to each side of it, I saw a whiteness,</l>
		<l>though I did not know what that whiteness was;</l>
		<l>below, another whiteness slowly showed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My master did not say a word before</l>
		<l>the whitenesses first seen appeared as wings;</l>
		<l>but then, when he had recognized the helmsman,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he cried: &quot;Bend, bend your knees: behold the angel</l>
		<l>of God, and join your hands; from this point on,</l>
		<l>this is the kind of minister you&apos;ll meet.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>See how much scorn he has for human means;</l>
		<l>he&apos;d have no other sail than his own wings</l>
		<l>and use no oar between such distant shores.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>See how he holds his wings, pointing to Heaven,</l>
		<l>piercing the air with his eternal pinions,</l>
		<l>which do not change as mortal plumage does.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he-that bird divine-as he drew closer</l>
		<l>and closer to us, seemed to gain in brightness,</l>
		<l>so that my eyes could not endure his nearness,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and I was forced to lower them; and he</l>
		<l>came on to shore with boat so light, so quick</l>
		<l>that nowhere did the water swallow it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The helmsman sent from Heaven, at the stern,</l>
		<l>seemed to have blessedness inscribed upon him;</l>
		<l>more than a hundred spirits sat within.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;In exitu Israel de Aegypto,&quot;</l>
		<l>with what is written after of that psalm,</l>
		<l>all of those spirits sang as with one voice.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then over them he made the holy cross</l>
		<l>as sign; they flung themselves down on the shore,</l>
		<l>and he moved off as he had come-swiftly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The crowd that he had left along the beach</l>
		<l>seemed not to know the place; they looked about</l>
		<l>like those whose eyes try out things new to them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Upon all sides the sun shot forth the day;</l>
		<l>and from mid-heaven its incisive arrows</l>
		<l>already had chased Capricorn away,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when those who&apos;d just arrived lifted their heads</l>
		<l>toward us and said: &quot;Do show us, if you know,</l>
		<l>the way by which we can ascend this slope.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And Virgil answered: &quot;You may be convinced</l>
		<l>that we are quite familiar with this shore;</l>
		<l>but we are strangers here, just as you are;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>we came but now, a little while before you,</l>
		<l>though by another path, so difficult</l>
		<l>and dense that this ascent seems sport to us.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The souls who, noticing my breathing, sensed</l>
		<l>that I was still a living being, then,</l>
		<l>out of astonishment, turned pale; and just</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as people crowd around a messenger</l>
		<l>who bears an olive branch, to hear his news,</l>
		<l>and no one hesitates to join that crush,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so here those happy spirits-all of them-</l>
		<l>stared hard at my face, just as if they had</l>
		<l>forgotten to proceed to their perfection.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw one of those spirits moving forward</l>
		<l>in order to embrace me-his affection</l>
		<l>so great that I was moved to mime his welcome.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O shades-in all except appearance-empty!</l>
		<l>Three times I clasped my hands behind him and</l>
		<l>as often brought them back against my chest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Dismay, I think, was painted on my face;</l>
		<l>at this, that shadow smiled as he withdrew;</l>
		<l>and I, still seeking him, again advanced.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Gently, he said that I could now stand back;</l>
		<l>then I knew who he was, and I beseeched</l>
		<l>him to remain awhile and talk with me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He answered: &quot;As I loved you when I was</l>
		<l>within my mortal flesh, so, freed, I love you:</l>
		<l>therefore I stay. But you, why do you journey?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;My own Casella, to return again</l>
		<l>to where I am, I journey thus; but why,&quot;</l>
		<l>I said, &quot;were you deprived of so much time?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he: &quot;No injury is done to me</l>
		<l>if he who takes up whom-and when-he pleases</l>
		<l>has kept me from this crossing many times,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for his own will derives from a just will.</l>
		<l>And yet, for three months now, he has accepted,</l>
		<l>most tranquilly, all those who would embark.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, I, who had turned then to the shore</l>
		<l>at which the Tiber&apos;s waters mix with salt,</l>
		<l>was gathered in by his benevolence.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Straight to that river mouth, he set his wings:</l>
		<l>that always is the place of gathering</l>
		<l>for those who do not sink to Acheron.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;If there&apos;s no new law that denies</l>
		<l>you memory or practice of the songs</l>
		<l>of love that used to quiet all my longings,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then may it please you with those songs to solace</l>
		<l>my soul somewhat; for-having journeyed here</l>
		<l>together with my body-it is weary.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Love that discourses to me in my mind&quot;</l>
		<l>he then began to sing-and sang so sweetly</l>
		<l>that I still hear that sweetness sound in me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My master, I, and all that company</l>
		<l>around the singer seemed so satisfied,</l>
		<l>as if no other thing might touch our minds.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We all were motionless and fixed upon</l>
		<l>the notes, when all at once the grave old man</l>
		<l>cried out: &quot;What have we here, you laggard spirits</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What negligence, what lingering is this?</l>
		<l>Quick, to the mountain to cast off the slough</l>
		<l>that will not let you see God show Himself!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even as doves, assembled where they feed,</l>
		<l>quietly gathering their grain or weeds,</l>
		<l>forgetful of their customary strut,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>will, if some thing appears that makes them fear,</l>
		<l>immediately leave their food behind</l>
		<l>because they are assailed by greater care;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did I see that new-come company-</l>
		<l>they left the song behind, turned toward the slope</l>
		<l>like those who go and yet do not know where.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And we were no less hasty in departure.</l>
	</p>
</page>
