<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>When dicing&apos;s done and players separate,</l>
		<l>the loser&apos;s left alone, disconsolate-</l>
		<l>rehearsing what he&apos;d thrown, he sadly learns;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>all of the crowd surrounds the one who won-</l>
		<l>one goes in front, and one tugs at his back,</l>
		<l>and at his side one asks to be remembered;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he does not halt but listens to them all;</l>
		<l>and when he gives them something, they desist;</l>
		<l>and so he can fend off the pressing throng.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I, in that persistent pack, was such:</l>
		<l>this way and that, I turned my face to them</l>
		<l>and, making promises, escaped their clutch.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There was the Aretine who met his death</l>
		<l>beneath Ghino di Tacco&apos;s bestial hands,</l>
		<l>and one who drowned when, in pursuit, he ran.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, with his outstretched hands, was Federigo</l>
		<l>Novello, praying, and the Pisan who</l>
		<l>made good Marzucco show his fortitude.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw Count Orso, and I saw the soul</l>
		<l>cleft from its body out of spite and envy-</l>
		<l>not, so it said, because it had been guilty-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I mean Pier de la Brosse (and may the Lady</l>
		<l>of Brabant, while she&apos;s still in this world, watch</l>
		<l>her ways-or end among a sadder flock).</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As soon as I was free from all those shades</l>
		<l>who always pray for others&apos; prayers for them,</l>
		<l>so as to reach their blessed state more quickly,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I started: &quot;O my light, it seems to me</l>
		<l>that in one passage you deny expressly</l>
		<l>that prayer can bend the rule of Heaven, yet</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>these people pray precisely for that end.</l>
		<l>Is their hope, therefore, only emptiness,</l>
		<l>or have I not read clearly what you said?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;My text is plain enough,</l>
		<l>and yet their hope is not delusive if</l>
		<l>one scrutinizes it with sober wit;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the peak of justice is not lowered when</l>
		<l>the fire of love accomplishes in one</l>
		<l>instant the expiation owed by all</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who dwell here; for where I asserted this-</l>
		<l>that prayers could not mend their fault-I spoke</l>
		<l>of prayers without a passageway to God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But in a quandary so deep, do not</l>
		<l>conclude with me, but wait for word that she,</l>
		<l>the light between your mind and truth, will speak-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>lest you misunderstand, the she I mean</l>
		<l>is Beatrice; upon this mountain&apos;s peak,</l>
		<l>there you shall see her smiling joyously.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;Lord, let us move ahead more quickly,</l>
		<l>for now I am less weary than before;</l>
		<l>and-you can see-the slope now casts a shadow.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;As long as it is day, we&apos;ll make as much</l>
		<l>headway as possible,&quot; he answered; &quot;but</l>
		<l>our climb won&apos;t be as rapid as you thought.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You will not reach the peak before you see</l>
		<l>the sun returning: now he hides behind</l>
		<l>the hills-you cannot interrupt his light.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But see-beyond-a soul who is completely</l>
		<l>apart, and seated, looking toward us; he</l>
		<l>will show us where to climb most speedily.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We came to him. O Lombard soul, what pride</l>
		<l>and what disdain were in your stance! Your eyes</l>
		<l>moved with such dignity, such gravity!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He said no thing to us but let us pass,</l>
		<l>his eyes intent upon us only as</l>
		<l>a lion watches when it is at rest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Yet Virgil made his way to him, appealing</l>
		<l>to him to show us how we&apos;d best ascend;</l>
		<l>and he did not reply to that request,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but asked us what our country was and who</l>
		<l>we were, at which my gentle guide began</l>
		<l>&quot;Mantua&quot;-and that spirit, who had been</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so solitary, rose from his position,</l>
		<l>saying:&quot;O Mantuan, I am Sordello,</l>
		<l>from your own land!&quot; And each embraced the other.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Ah, abject Italy, you inn of sorrows,</l>
		<l>you ship without a helmsman in harsh seas,</l>
		<l>no queen of provinces but of bordellos!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That noble soul had such enthusiasm:</l>
		<l>his city&apos;s sweet name was enough for him</l>
		<l>to welcome-there-his fellow-citizen;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But those who are alive within you now</l>
		<l>can&apos;t live without their warring-even those</l>
		<l>whom one same wall and one same moat enclose</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>gnaw at each other. Squalid Italy,</l>
		<l>search round your shores and then look inland-see</l>
		<l>if any part of you delight in peace.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What use was there in a Justinian&apos;s</l>
		<l>mending your bridle, when the saddle&apos;s empty?</l>
		<l>Indeed, were there no reins, your shame were less.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Ah you-who if you understood what God</l>
		<l>ordained, would then attend to things devout</l>
		<l>and in the saddle surely would allow</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Caesar to sit-see how this beast turns fierce</l>
		<l>because there are no spurs that would correct it,</l>
		<l>since you have laid your hands upon the bit!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O German Albert, you who have abandoned</l>
		<l>that steed become recalcitrant and savage,</l>
		<l>you who should ride astride its saddlebows-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>upon your blood may the just judgment of</l>
		<l>the stars descend with signs so strange and plain</l>
		<l>that your successor has to feel its terror!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For both you and your father, in your greed</l>
		<l>for lands that lay more close at hand, allowed</l>
		<l>the garden of the Empire to be gutted.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Come-you who pay no heed-do come and see</l>
		<l>Montecchi, Cappelletti, sad already,</l>
		<l>and, filled with fear, Monaldi, Filippeschi.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Come, cruel one, come see the tribulation</l>
		<l>of your nobility and heal their hurts;</l>
		<l>see how disconsolate is Santafior!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Come, see your Rome who, widowed and alone,</l>
		<l>weeps bitterly; both day and night, she moans:</l>
		<l>&quot;My Caesar, why are you not at my side?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Come, see how much your people love each other!</l>
		<l>And if no pity for us moves you, may</l>
		<l>shame for your own repute move you to act.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And if I am allowed, o highest Jove,</l>
		<l>to ask: You who on earth were crucified</l>
		<l>for us-have You turned elsewhere Your just eyes?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Or are You, in Your judgment&apos;s depth, devising</l>
		<l>a good that we cannot foresee, completely</l>
		<l>dissevered from our way of understanding?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For all the towns of Italy are full</l>
		<l>of tyrants, and each townsman who becomes</l>
		<l>a partisan is soon a new Marcellus.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My Florence, you indeed may be content</l>
		<l>that this digression would leave you exempt:</l>
		<l>your people&apos;s strivings spare you this lament.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Others have justice in their hearts, and thought</l>
		<l>is slow to let it fly off from their bow;</l>
		<l>but your folk keep it ready-on their lips.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Others refuse the weight of public service;</l>
		<l>whereas your people-eagerly-respond,</l>
		<l>even unasked, and shout: &quot;I&apos;ll take it on.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You might be happy now, for you have cause!</l>
		<l>You with your riches, peace, judiciousness!</l>
		<l>If I speak truly, facts won&apos;t prove me wrong.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Compared to you, Athens and Lacedaemon,</l>
		<l>though civil cities, with their ancient laws,</l>
		<l>had merely sketched the life of righteousness;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for you devise provisions so ingenious-</l>
		<l>whatever threads October sees you spin,</l>
		<l>when mid-November comes, will be unspun.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>How often, in the time you can remember,</l>
		<l>have you changed laws and coinage, offices</l>
		<l>and customs, and revised your citizens!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And if your memory has some clarity,</l>
		<l>then you will see yourself like that sick woman</l>
		<l>who finds no rest upon her feather-bed,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but, turning, tossing, tries to ease her pain.</l>
	</p>
</page>
