<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>But while their sudden flight was scattering</l>
		<l>those souls across the plain and toward the mountain</l>
		<l>where we are racked by rightful punishments,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I drew in closer to my true companion.</l>
		<l>For how could I have run ahead without him?</l>
		<l>Who could have helped me as I climbed the mountain</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He seemed like one who&apos;s stung by self-reproof;</l>
		<l>o pure and noble conscience, you in whom</l>
		<l>each petty fault becomes a harsh rebuke!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when his feet had left off hurrying-</l>
		<l>for haste denies all acts their dignity-</l>
		<l>my mind, which was-before-too focused, grew</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>more curious and widened its attention;</l>
		<l>I set my vision toward the slope that rises</l>
		<l>most steeply, up to heaven from the sea.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Behind my back the sun was flaming red;</l>
		<l>but there, ahead of me, its light was shattered</l>
		<l>because its rays were resting on my body.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when I saw the ground was dark in front</l>
		<l>of me and me alone, afraid that I</l>
		<l>had been abandoned, I turned to my side;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and he, my only comfort, as he turned</l>
		<l>around, began: &quot;Why must you still mistrust?</l>
		<l>Don&apos;t you believe that I am with-and guide-you?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The body from within which I cast shadows</l>
		<l>is buried where it now is evening: taken</l>
		<l>from Brindisi, it now belongs to Naples.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Thus, if no shadow falls in front of me,</l>
		<l>do not be more amazed than when you see</l>
		<l>the heavens not impede each other&apos;s rays.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The Power has disposed such bodiless</l>
		<l>bodies to suffer torments, heat and cold;</l>
		<l>how this is done, He would not have us know.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Foolish is he who hopes our intellect</l>
		<l>can reach the end of that unending road</l>
		<l>only one Substance in three Persons follows.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Confine yourselves, o humans, to the quia;</l>
		<l>had you been able to see all, there would</l>
		<l>have been no need for Mary to give birth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You saw the fruitless longing of those men</l>
		<l>who would-if reason could-have been content,</l>
		<l>those whose desire eternally laments:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I speak of Aristotle and of Plato-</l>
		<l>and many others.&quot; Here he bent his head</l>
		<l>and said no more, remaining with his sorrow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By this time we had reached the mountain&apos;s base,</l>
		<l>discovering a wall of rock so sheer</l>
		<l>that even agile legs are useless there.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The loneliest, most jagged promontory</l>
		<l>that lies between Turbia and Lerici,</l>
		<l>compared with it, provides stairs wide and easy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Now who knows where, along this mountainside,&quot;</l>
		<l>my master, halting, asked, &quot;one finds a rise</l>
		<l>where even he who has no wings can climb?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>While he, his eyes upon the ground, consulted</l>
		<l>his mind, considering what road to take,</l>
		<l>and I looked up around the wall of rock,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>along the left a band of souls appeared</l>
		<l>to me to be approaching us-but so</l>
		<l>unhurriedly, their movements did not show.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Lift up your eyes,&quot; I told my master; &quot;here</l>
		<l>are those who can advise us how to go,</l>
		<l>if you can find no counsel in yourself.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this, he looked at them and, less distressed,</l>
		<l>replied: &quot;Let us go there; their steps are slow;</l>
		<l>and you, my gentle son, hold fast to hope.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The distance from that company to us-</l>
		<l>I mean when we had gone a thousand paces-</l>
		<l>was still as far as a fine hurler&apos;s toss,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when they all huddled toward the hard rock wall</l>
		<l>and, once they&apos;d crowded there, refused to budge,</l>
		<l>even as men, when apprehensive, halt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O chosen souls, you who have ended well,&quot;</l>
		<l>Virgil began, &quot;by virtue of that peace</l>
		<l>which I believe awaits you all, please tell</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>us where the slope inclines and can be climbed;</l>
		<l>for he who best discerns the worth of time</l>
		<l>is most distressed whenever time is lost.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even as sheep that move, first one, then two,</l>
		<l>then three, out of the fold-the others also</l>
		<l>stand, eyes and muzzles lowered, timidly;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and what the first sheep does, the others do,</l>
		<l>and if it halts, they huddle close behind,</l>
		<l>simple and quiet and not knowing why:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, then, I saw those spirits in the front</l>
		<l>of that flock favored by good fortune move-</l>
		<l>their looks were modest; seemly, slow, their walk.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As soon as these souls saw, upon my right,</l>
		<l>along the ground, a gap in the sun&apos;s light,</l>
		<l>where shadow stretched from me to the rock wall,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>they stopped and then drew back somewhat; and all</l>
		<l>who came behind them-though they did not know</l>
		<l>why those ahead had halted-also slowed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Without your asking, I shall tell you plainly</l>
		<l>that you are looking at a human body;</l>
		<l>that&apos;s why the sunlight on the ground is broken.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Don&apos;t be astonished; rest assured that he</l>
		<l>would not attempt to cross this wall without</l>
		<l>a force that Heaven sent him as support.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These were my master&apos;s words. That worthy band</l>
		<l>replied: &quot;Come back, and move in our direction,&quot;</l>
		<l>and gestured-with backhanded motions-right.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And one of them began: &quot;Whoever you</l>
		<l>may be, as you move forward, turn and see:</l>
		<l>consider if-beyond-you&apos;ve ever seen me.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I turned to look at him attentively:</l>
		<l>he was fair-haired and handsome and his aspect</l>
		<l>was noble-but one eyebrow had been cleft</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>by a swordstroke. When I had humbly noted</l>
		<l>that I had never seen him, he said: &quot;Look</l>
		<l>now&quot;-showing me a wound high on his chest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, as he smiled, he told me: &quot;I am Manfred,</l>
		<l>the grandson of the Empress Constance; thus,</l>
		<l>I pray that, when you reach the world again,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you may go to my lovely daughter, mother</l>
		<l>of kings of Sicily and Aragon-</l>
		<l>tell her the truth, lest she&apos;s heard something other.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After my body had been shattered by</l>
		<l>two fatal blows, in tears, I then consigned</l>
		<l>myself to Him who willingly forgives.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My sins were ghastly, but the Infinite</l>
		<l>Goodness has arms so wide that It accepts</l>
		<l>who ever would return, imploring It.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And if Cosenza&apos;s pastor, who was sent</l>
		<l>to hunt me down-alive or dead-by Clement,</l>
		<l>had understood this facet of God&apos;s mercy,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my body&apos;s bones would still be there-beneath</l>
		<l>the custody of the great heap of stones-</l>
		<l>near Benevento, at the bridgehead; now</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>rain bathes my bones, the wind has driven them</l>
		<l>beyond the Kingdom, near the Verde&apos;s banks,</l>
		<l>where he transported them with tapers spent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Despite the Church&apos;s curse, there is no one</l>
		<l>so lost that the eternal love cannot</l>
		<l>return-as long as hope shows something green.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But it is true that anyone who dies</l>
		<l>in contumacy of the Holy Church,</l>
		<l>though he repented at the end, must wait</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>along this shore for thirty times the span</l>
		<l>he spent in his presumptuousness, unless</l>
		<l>that edict is abridged through fitting prayers.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now see if you, by making known to my</l>
		<l>kind Constance where you saw my soul and why</l>
		<l>delay&apos;s decreed for me, can make me happy;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>those here-through those beyond-advance more quickly.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
