<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The angel now was left behind us, he</l>
		<l>who had directed us to the sixth terrace,</l>
		<l>having erased one P that scarred my face;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he had declared that those who longed for justice</l>
		<l>are blessed, and his voice concluded that</l>
		<l>message with &quot;sitiunt,&quot; without the rest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And while I climbed behind the two swift spirits,</l>
		<l>not laboring at all, for I was lighter</l>
		<l>than I had been along the other stairs,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Virgil began: &quot;Love that is kindled by</l>
		<l>virtue, will, in another, find reply,</l>
		<l>as long as that love&apos;s flame appears without;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, from the time when Juvenal, descending</l>
		<l>among us, in Hell&apos;s Limbo, had made plain</l>
		<l>the fondness that you felt for me, my own</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>benevolence toward you has been much richer</l>
		<l>than any ever given to a person</l>
		<l>one has not seen; thus, now these stairs seem shor</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But tell me (and, as friend, forgive me if</l>
		<l>excessive candor lets my reins relax,</l>
		<l>and, as a friend, exchange your words with me):</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>how was it that you found within your breast</l>
		<l>a place for avarice, when you possessed</l>
		<l>the wisdom you had nurtured with such care?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These words at first brought something of a smile</l>
		<l>to Statius; then he answered: &quot;Every word</l>
		<l>you speak, to me is a dear sign of love.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Indeed, because true causes are concealed,</l>
		<l>we often face deceptive reasoning</l>
		<l>and things provoke perplexity in us.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Your question makes me sure that you&apos;re convinced-</l>
		<l>perhaps because my circle was the fifth-</l>
		<l>that, in the life I once lived, avarice</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>had been my sin. Know then that I was far</l>
		<l>from avarice-it was my lack of measure</l>
		<l>thousands of months have punished. And if I</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>had not corrected my assessment by</l>
		<l>my understanding what your verses meant</l>
		<l>when you, as if enraged by human nature,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>exclaimed: &apos;Why cannot you, o holy hunger</l>
		<l>for gold, restrain the appetite of mortals?&apos;-</l>
		<l>I&apos;d now, while rolling weights, know sorry jousts.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I became aware that hands might open</l>
		<l>too wide, like wings, in spending; and of this,</l>
		<l>as of my other sins, I did repent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>How many are to rise again with heads</l>
		<l>cropped close, whom ignorance prevents from reachi</l>
		<l>repentance in-and at the end of-life!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And know that when a sin is countered byu</l>
		<l>another fault-directly opposite&quot;</l>
		<l>to it-then, here, both sins see their green wither</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Thus, I join those who pay for avarice</l>
		<l>in my purgation, though what brought me here</l>
		<l>was prodigality-its opposite.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Now, when you sang the savage wars of those</l>
		<l>twin sorrows of Jocasta,&quot; said the singer</l>
		<l>of the bucolic poems, &quot;it does not seem-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>from those notes struck by you and Clio there-</l>
		<l>that you had yet turned faithful to the faith</l>
		<l>without which righteous works do not suffice.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If that is so, then what sun or what candles</l>
		<l>drew you from darkness so that, in their wake,</l>
		<l>you set your sails behind the fisherman?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to him: &quot;You were the first to send me</l>
		<l>to drink within Parnassus&apos; caves and you,</l>
		<l>the first who, after God, enlightened me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You did as he who goes by night and carries</l>
		<l>the lamp behind him-he is of no help</l>
		<l>to his own self but teaches those who follow-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when you declared: &apos;The ages are renewed;</l>
		<l>justice and man&apos;s first time on earth return;</l>
		<l>from Heaven a new progeny descends.&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Through you I was a poet and, through you,</l>
		<l>a Christian; but that you may see more plainly,</l>
		<l>I&apos;ll set my hand to color what I sketch.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Disseminated by the messengers</l>
		<l>of the eternal kingdom, the true faith</l>
		<l>by then had penetrated all the world,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and the new preachers preached in such accord</l>
		<l>with what you&apos;d said (and I have just repeated),</l>
		<l>that I was drawn into frequenting them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then they appeared to me to be so saintly</l>
		<l>that, when Domitian persecuted them,</l>
		<l>my own laments accompanied their grief;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and while I could-as long as I had life-</l>
		<l>I helped them, and their honest practices</l>
		<l>made me disdainful of all other sects.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Before-within my poem-I&apos;d led the Greeks</l>
		<l>unto the streams of Thebes, I was baptized;</l>
		<l>but out of fear, I was a secret Christian</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and, for a long time, showed myself as pagan;</l>
		<l>for this halfheartedness, for more than</l>
		<l>four centuries, I circled the fourth circle.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And now may you, who lifted up the lid</l>
		<l>that hid from me the good of which I speak,</l>
		<l>while time is left us as we climb, tell me</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>where is our ancient Terence, and Caecilius</l>
		<l>and Plautus, where is Varius, if you know;</l>
		<l>tell me if they are damned, and in what quarter.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;All these and Persius, I, and many others,&quot;</l>
		<l>my guide replied, &quot;are with that Greek to whom</l>
		<l>the Muses gave their gifts in greatest measure.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Our place is the blind prison, its first circle;</l>
		<l>and there we often talk about the mountain</l>
		<l>where those who were our nurses always dwell.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Euripides is with us, Antiphon,</l>
		<l>Simonides, and Agathon, as well</l>
		<l>as many other Greeks who once wore laurel</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>upon their brow; and there-of your own people-</l>
		<l>one sees Antigone, Deiphyle,</l>
		<l>Ismene, sad still, Argia as she was.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There one can see the woman who showed Langia,</l>
		<l>and there, Tiresias&apos; daughter; there is Thetis;</l>
		<l>and, with her sisters, there, Deidamia.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Both poets now were silent, once again</l>
		<l>intent on their surroundings-they were free</l>
		<l>of stairs and walls; with day&apos;s first four handmai</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>already left behind, and with the fifth</l>
		<l>guiding the chariot-pole and lifting it,</l>
		<l>so that its horn of flame rose always higher,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my master said: &quot;I think it&apos;s time that we</l>
		<l>turn our right shoulders toward the terrace edge,</l>
		<l>circling the mountain in the way we&apos;re used to.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In this way habit served us as a banner;</l>
		<l>and when we chose that path, our fear was less</l>
		<l>because that worthy soul gave his assent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those two were in the lead; I walked alone,</l>
		<l>behind them, listening to their colloquy,</l>
		<l>which taught me much concerning poetry.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But their delightful conversation soon</l>
		<l>was interrupted by a tree that blocked</l>
		<l>our path; its fruits were fine, their scent was sw</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and even as a fir-tree tapers upward</l>
		<l>from branch to branch, that tree there tapered dow</l>
		<l>so as-I think-to ward off any climber.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Upon our left, where wall enclosed our path,</l>
		<l>bright running water fell from the high rock</l>
		<l>and spread itself upon the leaves above.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When the two poets had approached the tree,</l>
		<l>a voice emerging from within the leaves</l>
		<l>cried out: &quot;This food shall be denied to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then it cried: &quot;Mary&apos;s care was for the marriage-</l>
		<l>feast&apos;s being seemly and complete, not for</l>
		<l>her mouth (which now would intercede for you).</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when they drank, of old, the Roman women</l>
		<l>were satisfied with water; and young Daniel,</l>
		<l>through his disdain of food, acquired wisdom.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The first age was as fair as gold: when hungry,</l>
		<l>men found the taste of acorns good; when thirsty,</l>
		<l>they found that every little stream was nectar.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When he was in the wilderness, the Baptist</l>
		<l>had fed on nothing more than honey, locusts:</l>
		<l>for this he was made great, as glorious</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as, in the Gospel, is made plain to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
