<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>As many as the hours in which the sphere</l>
		<l>that&apos;s always playing like a child appears</l>
		<l>from daybreak to the end of the third hour,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so many were the hours of light still left</l>
		<l>before the course of day had reached sunset;</l>
		<l>vespers was there; and where we are, midnight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When sunlight struck directly at our faces,</l>
		<l>for we had circled so much of the mountain</l>
		<l>that now we headed straight into the west,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then I could feel my vision overcome</l>
		<l>by radiance greater than I&apos;d sensed before,</l>
		<l>and unaccounted things left me amazed;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>at which, that they might serve me as a shade,</l>
		<l>I lifted up my hands above my brow,</l>
		<l>to limit some of that excessive splendor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As when a ray of light, from water or</l>
		<l>a mirror, leaps in the opposed direction</l>
		<l>and rises at an angle equal to</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>its angle of descent, and to each side</l>
		<l>the distance from the vertical is equal,</l>
		<l>as science and experiment have shown;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did it seem to me that I had been</l>
		<l>struck there by light reflected, facing me,</l>
		<l>at which my eyes turned elsewhere rapidly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Kind father, what is that against which I</l>
		<l>have tried in vain,&quot; I said, &quot;to screen my eyes?</l>
		<l>It seems to move toward us.&quot; And he replied:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Don&apos;t wonder if you are still dazzled by</l>
		<l>the family of Heaven: a messenger</l>
		<l>has come, and he invites us to ascend.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Soon, in the sight of such things, there will be</l>
		<l>no difficulty for you, but delight-</l>
		<l>as much as nature fashioned you to feel.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No sooner had we reached the blessed angel</l>
		<l>than with glad voice he told us: &quot;Enter here;</l>
		<l>these are less steep than were the other stairs.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We climbed, already past that point; behind us,</l>
		<l>we heard &quot;Beati misericordes&quot; sung</l>
		<l>and then &quot;Rejoice, you who have overcome.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I and my master journeyed on alone,</l>
		<l>we two together, upward; as we walked,</l>
		<l>I thought I&apos;d gather profit from his words;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and even as I turned toward him, I asked:</l>
		<l>&quot;What did the spirit of Romagna mean</l>
		<l>when he said, &apos;Sharing cannot have a part&apos;?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And his reply: &quot;He knows the harm that lies</l>
		<l>in his worst vice; if he chastises it,</l>
		<l>to ease its expiation-do not wonder.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For when your longings center on things such</l>
		<l>that sharing them apportions less to each,</l>
		<l>then envy stirs the bellows of your sighs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But if the love within the Highest Sphere</l>
		<l>should turn your longings heavenward, the fear</l>
		<l>inhabiting your breast would disappear;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for there, the more there are who would say &apos;ours,</l>
		<l>so much the greater is the good possessed</l>
		<l>by each-so much more love burns in that cloister.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;I am more hungry now for satisfaction&quot;</l>
		<l>I said, &quot;than if I&apos;d held my tongue before;</l>
		<l>I host a deeper doubt within my mind.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>How can a good that&apos;s shared by more possessors</l>
		<l>enable each to be more rich in it</l>
		<l>than if that good had been possessed by few?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;But if you still persist</l>
		<l>in letting your mind fix on earthly things,</l>
		<l>then even from true light you gather darkness.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That Good, ineffable and infinite,</l>
		<l>which is above, directs Itself toward love</l>
		<l>as light directs itself to polished bodies.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Where ardor is, that Good gives of Itself;</l>
		<l>and where more love is, there that Good confers</l>
		<l>a greater measure of eternal worth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when there are more souls above who love,</l>
		<l>there&apos;s more to love well there, and they love more,</l>
		<l>and, mirror-like, each soul reflects the other.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And if my speech has not appeased your hunger,</l>
		<l>you will see Beatrice-she will fulfill</l>
		<l>this and all other longings that you feel.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now only strive, so that the other five</l>
		<l>wounds may be canceled quickly, as the two</l>
		<l>already are-the wounds contrition heals.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But wanting then to say, &quot;You have appeased me,&quot;</l>
		<l>I saw that I had reached another circle,</l>
		<l>and my desiring eyes made me keep still.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There I seemed, suddenly, to be caught up</l>
		<l>in an ecstatic vision and to see</l>
		<l>some people in a temple; and a woman</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just at the threshold, in the gentle manner</l>
		<l>that mothers use, was saying: &quot;O my son,</l>
		<l>why have you done this to us? You can see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>how we have sought you-sorrowing, your father</l>
		<l>and I.&quot; And at this point, as she fell still,</l>
		<l>what had appeared at first now disappeared.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then there appeared to me another woman:</l>
		<l>upon her cheeks-the tears that grief distills</l>
		<l>when it is born of much scorn for another.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>She said: &quot;If you are ruler of that city</l>
		<l>to name which even goddesses once vied-</l>
		<l>where every science had its source of light-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>revenge yourself on the presumptuous</l>
		<l>arms that embraced our daughter, o Pisistratus.&quot;</l>
		<l>And her lord seemed to me benign and mild,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>his aspect temperate, as he replied:</l>
		<l>&quot;What shall we do to one who&apos;d injure us</l>
		<l>if one who loves us earns our condemnation?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Next I saw people whom the fire of wrath</l>
		<l>had kindled, as they stoned a youth and kept</l>
		<l>on shouting loudly to each other: &quot;Kill!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Kill!&quot; &quot;Kill!&quot; I saw him now, weighed down by death,</l>
		<l>sink to the ground, although his eyes were bent</l>
		<l>always on Heaven-they were Heaven&apos;s gates-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>praying to his high Lord, despite the torture,</l>
		<l>to pardon those who were his persecutors;</l>
		<l>his look was such that it unlocked compassion.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when my soul returned outside itself</l>
		<l>and met the things outside it that are real,</l>
		<l>I then could recognize my not false errors.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide, on seeing me behave as if</l>
		<l>I were a man who&apos;s freed himself from sleep,</l>
		<l>said: &quot;What is wrong with you? You can&apos;t walk straight;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for more than half a league now you have moved</l>
		<l>with clouded eyes and lurching legs, as if</l>
		<l>you were a man whom wine or sleep has gripped!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Oh, my kind father, if you hear me out,</l>
		<l>I&apos;ll tell you what appeared to me,&quot; I said,</l>
		<l>&quot;when I had lost the right use of my legs.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he: &quot;Although you had a hundred masks</l>
		<l>upon your face, that still would not conceal</l>
		<l>from me the thoughts you thought, however slight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What you have seen was shown lest you refuse</l>
		<l>to open up your heart unto the waters</l>
		<l>of peace that pour from the eternal fountain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I did not ask &apos;What&apos;s wrong with you?&apos; as one</l>
		<l>who only sees with earthly eyes, which-once</l>
		<l>the body, stripped of soul, lies dead-can&apos;t see;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I asked so that your feet might find more force:</l>
		<l>so must one urge the indolent, too slow</l>
		<l>to use their waking time when it returns.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We made our way until the end of vespers,</l>
		<l>peering, as far ahead as sight could stretch,</l>
		<l>at rays of light that, although late, were bright.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But, gradually, smoke as black as night</l>
		<l>began to overtake us; and there was</l>
		<l>no place where we could have avoided it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This smoke deprived us of pure air and sight.</l>
	</p>
</page>
