<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>To course across more kindly waters now</l>
		<l>my talent&apos;s little vessel lifts her sails,</l>
		<l>leaving behind herself a sea so cruel;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and what I sing will be that second kingdom,</l>
		<l>in which the human soul is cleansed of sin,</l>
		<l>becoming worthy of ascent to Heaven.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But here, since I am yours, o holy Muses,</l>
		<l>may this poem rise again from Hell&apos;s dead realm;</l>
		<l>and may Calliope rise somewhat here,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>accompanying my singing with that music</l>
		<l>whose power struck the poor Pierides</l>
		<l>so forcefully that they despaired of pardon.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The gentle hue of oriental sapphire</l>
		<l>in which the sky&apos;s serenity was steeped-</l>
		<l>its aspect pure as far as the horizon-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>brought back my joy in seeing just as soon</l>
		<l>as I had left behind the air of death</l>
		<l>that had afflicted both my sight and breast.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The lovely planet that is patroness</l>
		<l>of love made all the eastern heavens glad,</l>
		<l>veiling the Pisces in the train she led.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I turned to the right, setting my mind</l>
		<l>upon the other pole, and saw four stars</l>
		<l>not seen before except by the first people.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Heaven appeared to revel in their flames:</l>
		<l>o northern hemisphere, because you were</l>
		<l>denied that sight, you are a widower!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After my eyes took leave of those four stars,</l>
		<l>turning a little toward the other pole,</l>
		<l>from which the Wain had disappeared by now,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw a solitary patriarch</l>
		<l>near me-his aspect worthy of such reverence</l>
		<l>that even son to father owes no more.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His beard was long and mixed with white, as were</l>
		<l>the hairs upon his head; and his hair spread</l>
		<l>down to his chest in a divided tress.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The rays of the four holy stars so framed</l>
		<l>his face with light that in my sight he seemed</l>
		<l>like one who is confronted by the sun.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Who are you-who, against the hidden river,</l>
		<l>were able to escape the eternal prison?&quot;</l>
		<l>he said, moving those venerable plumes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Who was your guide? What served you both as lantern</l>
		<l>when, from the deep night that will always keep</l>
		<l>the hellish valley dark, you were set free?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The laws of the abyss-have they been broken?</l>
		<l>Or has a new, a changed decree in Heaven</l>
		<l>let you, though damned, approach my rocky slopes?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide took hold of me decisively;</l>
		<l>by way of words and hands and other signs,</l>
		<l>he made my knees and brow show reverence.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he replied: &quot;I do not come through my</l>
		<l>own self. There was a lady sent from Heaven;</l>
		<l>her pleas led me to help and guide this man.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But since your will would have a far more full</l>
		<l>and accurate account of our condition,</l>
		<l>my will cannot withhold what you request.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This man had yet to see his final evening;</l>
		<l>but, through his folly, little time was left</l>
		<l>before he did-he was so close to it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As I have told you, I was sent to him</l>
		<l>for his deliverance; the only road</l>
		<l>I could have taken was the road I took.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I showed him all the people of perdition;</l>
		<l>now I intend to show to him those spirits</l>
		<l>who, in your care, are bent on expiation.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To tell you how I led him would take long;</l>
		<l>it is a power descending from above</l>
		<l>that helps me guide him here, to see and hear you.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now may it please you to approve his coming;</l>
		<l>he goes in search of liberty-so precious,</l>
		<l>as he who gives his life for it must know.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You know it-who, in Utica, found death</l>
		<l>for freedom was not bitter, when you left</l>
		<l>the garb that will be bright on the great day.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Eternal edicts are not broken for us;</l>
		<l>this man&apos;s alive, and I&apos;m not bound by Minos;</l>
		<l>but I am from the circle where the chaste</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>eyes of your Marcia are; and she still prays</l>
		<l>to you, o holy breast, to keep her as</l>
		<l>your own: for her love, then, incline to us.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Allow our journey through your seven realms.</l>
		<l>I shall thank her for kindness you bestow-</l>
		<l>if you would let your name be named below.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;While I was there, within the other world,</l>
		<l>Marcia so pleased my eyes,&quot; he then replied,</l>
		<l>&quot;each kindness she required, I satisfied.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now that she dwells beyond the evil river,</l>
		<l>she has no power to move me any longer,</l>
		<l>such was the law decreed when I was freed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But if a lady come from Heaven speeds</l>
		<l>and helps you, as you say, there is no need</l>
		<l>of flattery; it is enough, indeed,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to ask me for her sake. Go then; but first</l>
		<l>wind a smooth rush around his waist and bathe</l>
		<l>his face, to wash away all of Hell&apos;s stains;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for it would not be seemly to approach</l>
		<l>with eyes still dimmed by any mists, the first</l>
		<l>custodian angel, one from Paradise.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This solitary island, all around</l>
		<l>its very base, there where the breakers pound,</l>
		<l>bears rushes on its soft and muddy ground.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There is no other plant that lives below:</l>
		<l>no plant with leaves or plant that, as it grows,</l>
		<l>hardens-and breaks beneath the waves&apos; harsh blows.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That done, do not return by this same pass;</l>
		<l>the sun, which rises now, will show you how</l>
		<l>this hillside can be climbed more easily.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>With that he vanished; and without a word,</l>
		<l>I rose and drew in closer to my guide,</l>
		<l>and it was on him that I set my eyes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he began: &quot;Son, follow in my steps;</l>
		<l>let us go back; this is the point at which</l>
		<l>the plain slopes down to reach its lowest bounds.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Daybreak was vanquishing the dark&apos;s last hour,</l>
		<l>which fled before it; in the distance, I</l>
		<l>could recognize the trembling of the sea.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We made our way across the lonely plain,</l>
		<l>like one returning to a lost pathway,</l>
		<l>who, till he finds it, seems to move in vain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When we had reached the point where dew contends</l>
		<l>with sun and, under sea winds, in the shade,</l>
		<l>wins out because it won&apos;t evaporate,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my master gently placed both of his hands-</l>
		<l>outspread-upon the grass; therefore, aware</l>
		<l>of what his gesture and intention were,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I reached and offered him my tear-stained cheeks;</l>
		<l>and on my cheeks, he totally revealed</l>
		<l>the color that Inferno had concealed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then we arrived at the deserted shore,</l>
		<l>which never yet had seen its waters coursed</l>
		<l>by any man who journeyed back again.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, just as pleased another, he girt me.</l>
		<l>O wonder! Where he plucked the humble plant</l>
		<l>that he had chosen, there that plant sprang up</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>again, identical, immediately.</l>
	</p>
</page>
