<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The hour when climbers cannot pause had come:</l>
		<l>the sun had left to Taurus the meridian,</l>
		<l>and night had left it to the Scorpion.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, like one who will not stop but moves</l>
		<l>along his path, no matter what he sees,</l>
		<l>if he is goaded by necessity,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>we made our way into the narrow gap</l>
		<l>and, one behind the other, took the stairs</l>
		<l>so strait that climbers there must separate.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as the fledgling stork will lift its wing</l>
		<l>because it wants to fly, but dares not try</l>
		<l>to leave the nest, and lets its wing drop back,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so I, with my desire to question kindled</l>
		<l>then spent, arrived as far as making ready</l>
		<l>to speak. But my dear father, though our steps</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>were hurrying, did not stop talking, for</l>
		<l>he said: &quot;The iron of the arrow&apos;s touched</l>
		<l>the longbow; let the shaft of speech fly off.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I had confidence enough to open</l>
		<l>my mouth and ask him: &quot;How can one grow lean</l>
		<l>where there is never need for nourishment?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;If you recall how Meleager was</l>
		<l>consumed,&quot; he said, &quot;just when the firebrand</l>
		<l>was spent, this won&apos;t be hard to understand;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and if you think how, though your body&apos;s swift,</l>
		<l>your image in the mirror captures it,</l>
		<l>then what perplexed will seem to you transparent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But that your will to know may be appeased,</l>
		<l>here&apos;s Statius, and I call on him and ask</l>
		<l>that he now be the healer of your doubts.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;If I explain eternal ways to him,&quot;</l>
		<l>Statius replied, &quot;while you are present here,</l>
		<l>let my excuse be: I cannot refuse you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he began: &quot;If, son, your mind receives</l>
		<l>and keeps my words, then what I say will serve</l>
		<l>as light upon the how that you have asked.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The thirsty veins drink up the perfect blood-</l>
		<l>but not all of that blood: a portion&apos;s left,</l>
		<l>like leavings that are taken from the table.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within the heart, that part acquires power</l>
		<l>to form all of another&apos;s human limbs,</l>
		<l>as blood that flows through veins feeds one&apos;s own </l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Digested yet again, that part descends</l>
		<l>to what is best not named; from there it drips</l>
		<l>into the natural receptacle,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>upon another&apos;s blood; the two bloods mix,</l>
		<l>one ready to be passive and one active</l>
		<l>because a perfect place, the heart, prepared them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The active, having reached the passive, starts</l>
		<l>to work: first it coagulates-and then</l>
		<l>quickens-the matter it has made more dense.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Having become a soul (much like a plant,</l>
		<l>though with this difference-a plant&apos;s complete,</l>
		<l>whereas a fetus still is journeying),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the active virtue labors, so the fetus</l>
		<l>may move and feel, like a sea-sponge; and then</l>
		<l>it starts to organize the powers it&apos;s seeded.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this point, son, the power that had come</l>
		<l>from the begetter&apos;s heart unfolds and spreads,</l>
		<l>that nature may see every limb perfected.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But how the animal becomes a speaking</l>
		<l>being, you&apos;ve not yet seen; this point&apos;s so hard,</l>
		<l>it led one wiser than you are to err</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in separating from the possible</l>
		<l>intellect the soul, since he could see</l>
		<l>no organ for the mind-so did he teach.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Open your heart to truth we now have reached</l>
		<l>and know that, once the brain&apos;s articulation</l>
		<l>within the fetus has attained perfection,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then the First Mover turns toward it with joy</l>
		<l>on seeing so much art in nature and</l>
		<l>breathes into it new spirit-vigorous-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>which draws all that is active in the fetus</l>
		<l>into its substance and becomes one soul</l>
		<l>that lives and feels and has self-consciousness.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That what I say may leave you less perplexed,</l>
		<l>consider the sun&apos;s heat that, when combined</l>
		<l>with sap that flows from vines, is then made wine.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when Lachesis lacks more thread, then soul&apos;s</l>
		<l>divided from the flesh; potentially,</l>
		<l>it bears with it the human and divine;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but with the human powers mute, the rest-</l>
		<l>intelligence and memory and will-</l>
		<l>are more acute in action than they were.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>With no delay, the soul falls of itself-</l>
		<l>astonishingly-on one of two shores;</l>
		<l>there it learns-early-what way it will journey.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, once the soul is circumscribed by space,</l>
		<l>the power that gives form irradiates</l>
		<l>as-and as much as-once it formed live limbs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And even as the saturated air,</l>
		<l>since it reflects the rays the sun has sent,</l>
		<l>takes rainbow colors as its ornament,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so there, where the soul stopped, the nearby air</l>
		<l>takes on the form that soul impressed on it,</l>
		<l>a shape that is, potentially, real body;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and then, just as a flame will follow after</l>
		<l>the fire whenever fire moves, so that</l>
		<l>new form becomes the spirit&apos;s follower.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Since from that airy body it takes on</l>
		<l>its semblance, that soul is called &apos;shade&apos;: that s</l>
		<l>forms organs for each sense, even for sight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This airy body lets us speak and laugh;</l>
		<l>with it we form the tears and sigh the sighs</l>
		<l>that you, perhaps, have heard around this mountain</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as we are held fast by longings and</l>
		<l>by other sentiments, our shade takes form:</l>
		<l>this is the cause of your astonishment.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By now we&apos;d reached the final turning we</l>
		<l>would meet and took the pathway right, at which</l>
		<l>we were preoccupied with other cares.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, from the wall, the mountain hurls its flame</l>
		<l>but, from the terrace side, there whirls a wind</l>
		<l>that pushes back the fire and limits it;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>thus, on the open side, proceeding one</l>
		<l>by one, we went; I feared the fire on</l>
		<l>the left and, on the right, the precipice.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My guide said: &quot;On this terrace, it is best</l>
		<l>to curb your eyes: the least distraction-left</l>
		<l>or right-can mean a step you will regret.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, from the heart of that great conflagration,</l>
		<l>I heard &quot;Summae Deus clementiae&quot;</l>
		<l>sung-and was not less keen to turn my eyes;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and I saw spirits walking in the flames,</l>
		<l>so that I looked at them and at my steps,</l>
		<l>sharing the time I had to look at each.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After they&apos;d reached that hymn&apos;s end, &quot;Virum non</l>
		<l>cognosco&quot; were the words they cried aloud;</l>
		<l>then they began the hymn in a low voice</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>again, and, done again, they cried: &quot;Diana</l>
		<l>kept to the woods and banished Helice</l>
		<l>after she&apos;d felt the force of Venus&apos; poison.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then they returned to singing; and they praised</l>
		<l>aloud those wives and husbands who were chaste,</l>
		<l>as virtue and as matrimony mandate.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This is-I think-the way these spirits act</l>
		<l>as long as they are burned by fire: this is</l>
		<l>the care and this the nourishment with which</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>one has to heal the final wound of all.</l>
	</p>
</page>
