<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Remember, reader, if you&apos;ve ever been</l>
		<l>caught in the mountains by a mist through which</l>
		<l>you only saw as moles see through their skin,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>how, when the thick, damp vapors once begin</l>
		<l>to thin, the sun&apos;s sphere passes feebly through them,</l>
		<l>then your imagination will be quick</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to reach the point where it can see how I</l>
		<l>first came to see the sun again-when it</l>
		<l>was almost at the point at which it sets.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, my steps matched my master&apos;s trusty steps;</l>
		<l>out of that cloud I came, reaching the rays</l>
		<l>that, on the shores below, by now were spent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O fantasy, you that at times would snatch</l>
		<l>us so from outward things-we notice nothing</l>
		<l>although a thousand trumpets sound around us-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who moves you when the senses do not spur you?</l>
		<l>A light that finds its form in Heaven moves you-</l>
		<l>directly or led downward by God&apos;s will.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within my fantasy I saw impressed</l>
		<l>the savagery of one who then, transformed,</l>
		<l>became the bird that most delights in song;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>at this, my mind withdrew to the within,</l>
		<l>to what imagining might bring; no thing</l>
		<l>that came from the without could enter in.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then into my deep fantasy there rained</l>
		<l>one who was crucified; and as he died,</l>
		<l>he showed his savagery and his disdain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Around him were great Ahasuerus and</l>
		<l>Esther his wife, and the just Mordecai,</l>
		<l>whose saying and whose doing were so upright.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when this image shattered of itself,</l>
		<l>just like a bubble that has lost the water</l>
		<l>beneath which it was formed, there then rose up</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in my envisioning a girl who wept</l>
		<l>most bitterly and said: &quot;O queen, why did</l>
		<l>you, in your wrath, desire to be no more?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So as to keep Lavinia, you killed</l>
		<l>yourself; now you have lost me! I am she,</l>
		<l>mother, who mourns your fall before another&apos;s.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even as sleep is shattered when new light</l>
		<l>strikes suddenly against closed eyes and, once</l>
		<l>it&apos;s shattered, gleams before it dies completely,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so my imagination fell away</l>
		<l>as soon as light-more powerful than light</l>
		<l>we are accustomed to-beat on my eyes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I looked about to see where I might be;</l>
		<l>but when a voice said: &quot;Here one can ascend,&quot;</l>
		<l>then I abandoned every other intent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That voice made my will keen to see the one</l>
		<l>who&apos;d spoken-with the eagerness that cannot</l>
		<l>be still until it faces what it wants.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But even as the sun, become too strong,</l>
		<l>defeats our vision, veiling its own form,</l>
		<l>so there my power of sight was overcome.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;This spirit is divine; and though unasked,</l>
		<l>he would conduct us to the upward path;</l>
		<l>he hides himself with that same light he sheds.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He does with us as men do with themselves;</l>
		<l>for he who sees a need but waits to be</l>
		<l>asked is already set on cruel refusal.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now let our steps accept his invitation,</l>
		<l>and let us try to climb before dark falls-</l>
		<l>then, until day returns, we&apos;ll have to halt.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So said my guide; and toward a stairway, he</l>
		<l>and I, together, turned; and just as soon</l>
		<l>as I was at the first step, I sensed something</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>much like the motion of a wing, and wind</l>
		<l>that beat against my face, and words: &quot;Beati</l>
		<l>pacifici, those free of evil anger!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Above us now the final rays before;</l>
		<l>the fall of night were raised to such a height</l>
		<l>that we could see the stars on every side.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O why, my strength, do you so melt away?&quot;</l>
		<l>I said within myself, because I felt</l>
		<l>the force within my legs compelled to halt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We&apos;d reached a point at which the upward stairs</l>
		<l>no longer climbed, and we were halted there</l>
		<l>just like a ship when it has touched the shore.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I listened for a while, hoping to hear</l>
		<l>whatever there might be in this new circle;</l>
		<l>then I turned toward my master, asking him:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Tell me, my gentle father: what offense</l>
		<l>is purged within the circle we have reached?</l>
		<l>Although our feet must stop, your words need not.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;Precisely here, the love</l>
		<l>of good that is too tepidly pursued</l>
		<l>is mended; here the lazy oar plies harder.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But so that you may understand more clearly,</l>
		<l>now turn your mind to me, and you will gather</l>
		<l>some useful fruit from our delaying here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My son, there&apos;s no Creator and no creature</l>
		<l>who ever was without love-natural</l>
		<l>or mental; and you know that,&quot; he began.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The natural is always without error,</l>
		<l>but mental love may choose an evil object</l>
		<l>or err through too much or too little vigor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As long as it&apos;s directed toward the First Good</l>
		<l>and tends toward secondary goods with measure,</l>
		<l>it cannot be the cause of evil pleasure;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but when it twists toward evil, or attends</l>
		<l>to good with more or less care than it should,</l>
		<l>those whom He made have worked against their Maker</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From this you see that-of necessity-</l>
		<l>love is the seed in you of every virtue</l>
		<l>and of all acts deserving punishment.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now, since love never turns aside its eyes</l>
		<l>from the well-being of its subject, things</l>
		<l>are surely free from hatred of themselves;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and since no being can be seen as self-</l>
		<l>existing and divorced from the First Being,</l>
		<l>each creature is cut off from hating Him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Thus, if I have distinguished properly,</l>
		<l>ill love must mean to wish one&apos;s neighbor ill;</l>
		<l>and this love&apos;s born in three ways in your clay.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There&apos;s he who, through abasement of another,</l>
		<l>hopes for supremacy; he only longs</l>
		<l>to see his neighbor&apos;s excellence cast down.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then there is one who, when he is outdone,</l>
		<l>fears his own loss of fame, power, honor, favor;</l>
		<l>his sadness loves misfortune for his neighbor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there is he who, over injury</l>
		<l>received, resentful, for revenge grows greedy</l>
		<l>and, angrily, seeks out another&apos;s harm.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This threefold love is expiated here</l>
		<l>below; now I would have you understand</l>
		<l>the love that seeks the good distortedly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Each apprehends confusedly a Good</l>
		<l>in which the mind may rest, and longs for It;</l>
		<l>and, thus, all strive to reach that Good; but if</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the love that urges you to know It or</l>
		<l>to reach that Good is lax, this terrace, after</l>
		<l>a just repentance, punishes for that.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There is a different good, which does not make</l>
		<l>men glad; it is not happiness, is not</l>
		<l>true essence, fruit and root of every good.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The love that-profligately-yields to that</l>
		<l>is wept on in three terraces above us;</l>
		<l>but I&apos;ll not say what three shapes that loves take</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>may you seek those distinctions for yourself.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
