<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Weeping, the women then began-now three,</l>
		<l>now four, alternately-to psalm gently,</l>
		<l>&quot;Deus venerunt gentes&quot;; and at this,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>sighing and full of pity, Beatrice</l>
		<l>was changed; she listened, grieving little less</l>
		<l>than Mary when, beneath the Cross, she wept.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But when the seven virgins had completed</l>
		<l>their psalm, and she was free to speak, erect,</l>
		<l>her coloring like ardent fire, she answered:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Modicum, et non videbitis me</l>
		<l>et iterum sisters delightful to me,</l>
		<l>modicum, et vos videbitis me.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then she set all the seven nymphs in front</l>
		<l>of her and signaled me, the lady, and</l>
		<l>the sage who had remained, to move behind her.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So she advanced; and I do not believe</l>
		<l>that she had taken her tenth step upon</l>
		<l>the ground before her eyes had struck my eyes;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and gazing tranquilly, &quot;Pray come more quickly,&quot;</l>
		<l>she said to me, &quot;so that you are more ready</l>
		<l>to listen to me should I speak to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As soon as I, responding to my duty,</l>
		<l>had joined her, she said: &quot;Brother, why not try,</l>
		<l>since now you&apos;re at my side, to query me?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Like those who, speaking to superiors</l>
		<l>too reverently do not speak distinctly,</l>
		<l>not drawing their clear voice up to their teeth-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did I speak with sound too incomplete</l>
		<l>when I began: &quot;Lady, you know my need</l>
		<l>to know, and know how it can be appeased.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And she to me: &quot;I&apos;d have you disentangle</l>
		<l>yourself, from this point on, from fear and shame,</l>
		<l>that you no longer speak like one who dreams.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Know that the vessel which the serpent broke</l>
		<l>was and is not; but he whose fault it is</l>
		<l>may rest assured-God&apos;s vengeance fears no hindranc</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The eagle that had left its plumes within</l>
		<l>the chariot, which then became a monster</l>
		<l>and then a prey, will not forever be</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>without an heir; for I can plainly see,</l>
		<l>and thus I tell it: stars already close</l>
		<l>at hand, which can&apos;t be blocked or checked, will b</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a time in which, dispatched by God, a Five</l>
		<l>Hundred and Ten and Five will slay the whore</l>
		<l>together with that giant who sins with her.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And what I tell, as dark as Sphinx and Themis,</l>
		<l>may leave you less convinced because-like these-</l>
		<l>it tires the intellect with quandaries;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but soon events themselves will be the Naiads</l>
		<l>that clarify this obstinate enigma-</l>
		<l>but without injury to grain or herds.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Take note; and even as I speak these words,</l>
		<l>do you transmit them in your turn to those</l>
		<l>who live the life that is a race to death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when you write them, keep in mind that you</l>
		<l>must not conceal what you&apos;ve seen of the tree</l>
		<l>that now has been despoiled twice over here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Whoever robs or rends that tree offends,</l>
		<l>with his blaspheming action, God; for He</l>
		<l>created it for His sole use-holy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For tasting of that tree, the first soul waited</l>
		<l>five thousand years and more in grief and longing</l>
		<l>for Him who on Himself avenged that taste.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Your intellect&apos;s asleep if it can&apos;t see</l>
		<l>how singular&apos;s the cause that makes that tree</l>
		<l>so tall and makes it grow invertedly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And if, like waters of the Elsa, your</l>
		<l>vain thoughts did not encrust your mind; if your</l>
		<l>delight in them were not like Pyramus</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>staining the mulberry, you&apos;d recognize</l>
		<l>in that tree&apos;s form and height the moral sense</l>
		<l>God&apos;s justice had when He forbade trespass.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But since I see your intellect is made</l>
		<l>of stone and, petrified, grown so opaque-</l>
		<l>the light of what I say has left you dazed-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I&apos;d also have you bear my words within you-</l>
		<l>if not inscribed, at least outlined-just as</l>
		<l>the pilgrim&apos;s staff is brought back wreathed with </l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;Even as wax the seal&apos;s impressed,</l>
		<l>where there&apos;s no alteration in the form,</l>
		<l>so does my brain now bear what you have stamped.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But why does your desired word ascend</l>
		<l>so high above my understanding that</l>
		<l>the more I try, the more am I denied?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;That you may recognize,&quot; she said, &quot;the school</l>
		<l>that you have followed and may see if what</l>
		<l>it taught can comprehend what I have said-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and see that, as the earth is distant from</l>
		<l>the highest and the swiftest of the heavens,</l>
		<l>so distant is your way from the divine.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I replied to her: &quot;I don&apos;t remember</l>
		<l>making myself a stranger to you, nor</l>
		<l>does conscience gnaw at me because of that.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;And if you can&apos;t remember that,&quot; she answered,</l>
		<l>smiling, &quot;then call to mind how you-today-</l>
		<l>have drunk of Lethe; and if smoke is proof</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of fire, then it is clear: we can conclude</l>
		<l>from this forgetfulness, that in your will</l>
		<l>there was a fault-your will had turned elsewhere.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But from now on the words I speak will be</l>
		<l>naked; that is appropriate if they</l>
		<l>would be laid bare before your still-crude sight.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>More incandescent now, with slower steps,</l>
		<l>the sun was pacing the meridian,</l>
		<l>which alters with the place from which it&apos;s seen,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when, just as one who serves as escort for</l>
		<l>a group will halt if he has come upon</l>
		<l>things strange or even traces of strangeness,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the seven ladies halted at the edge</l>
		<l>of a dense shadow such as mountains cast,</l>
		<l>beneath green leaves and black boughs, on cold ban</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In front of them I seemed to see Euphrates</l>
		<l>and Tigris issuing from one same spring</l>
		<l>and then, as friends do, separating slowly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O light, o glory of the human race,</l>
		<l>what water is this, flowing from one source</l>
		<l>and then becoming distant from itself?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Her answer to what I had asked was: &quot;Ask</l>
		<l>Matilda to explain this&quot;; and the lovely</l>
		<l>lady, as one who frees herself from blame,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>replied: &quot;He&apos;s heard of this and other matters</l>
		<l>from me; and I am sure that Lethe&apos;s waters</l>
		<l>have not obscured his memory of this.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And Beatrice :&quot;Perhaps some greater care,</l>
		<l>which often weakens memory, has made</l>
		<l>his mind, in things regarding sight, grow dark.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But see Eunoe as it flows from there:</l>
		<l>lead him to it and, as you&apos;re used to doing,</l>
		<l>revive the power that is faint in him.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As would the noble soul, which offers no</l>
		<l>excuse, but makes another&apos;s will its own</l>
		<l>as soon as signs reveal that will; just so,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when she had taken me, the lovely lady</l>
		<l>moved forward; and she said with womanly</l>
		<l>courtesy to Statius: &quot;Come with him.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If, reader, I had ampler space in which</l>
		<l>to write, I&apos;d sing-though incompletely-that</l>
		<l>sweet draught for which my thirst was limitless;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but since all of the pages pre-disposed</l>
		<l>for this, the second canticle, are full,</l>
		<l>the curb of art will not let me continue.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From that most holy wave I now returned</l>
		<l>to Beatrice; remade, as new trees are</l>
		<l>renewed when they bring forth new boughs, I was</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>pure and prepared to climb unto the stars.</l>
	</p>
</page>
