<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The subtle teacher had completed his</l>
		<l>discourse to me; attentively he watched</l>
		<l>my eyes to see if I seemed satisfied.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I, still goaded by new thirst, was silent</l>
		<l>without, although within I said: &quot;Perhaps</l>
		<l>I have displeased him with too many questions.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But that true father, who had recognized</l>
		<l>the timid want I would not tell aloud,</l>
		<l>by speaking, gave me courage to speak out.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At which I said: &quot;Master, my sight is so</l>
		<l>illumined by your light-I recognize</l>
		<l>all that your words declare or analyze.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, I pray you, gentle father dear,</l>
		<l>to teach me what love is: you have reduced</l>
		<l>to love both each good and its opposite.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He said: &quot;Direct your intellect&apos;s sharp eyes</l>
		<l>toward me, and let the error of the blind</l>
		<l>who&apos;d serve as guides be evident to you.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The soul, which is created quick to love,</l>
		<l>responds to everything that pleases, just</l>
		<l>as soon as beauty wakens it to act.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Your apprehension draws an image from</l>
		<l>a real object and expands upon</l>
		<l>that object until soul has turned toward it;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and if, so turned, the soul tends steadfastly,</l>
		<l>then that propensity is love-it&apos;s nature</l>
		<l>that joins the soul in you, anew, through beauty.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, just as flames ascend because the form</l>
		<l>of fire was fashioned to fly upward, toward</l>
		<l>the stuff of its own sphere, where it lasts longes</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so does the soul, when seized, move into longing,</l>
		<l>a motion of the spirit, never resting</l>
		<l>till the beloved thing has made it joyous.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now you can plainly see how deeply hidden</l>
		<l>truth is from scrutinists who would insist</l>
		<l>that every love is, in itself, praiseworthy;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and they are led to error by the matter</l>
		<l>of love, because it may seem-always-good;</l>
		<l>but not each seal is fine, although the wax is.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Your speech and my own wit that followed it,&quot;</l>
		<l>I answered him, &quot;have shown me what love is;</l>
		<l>but that has filled me with still greater doubt;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for if love&apos;s offered to us from without</l>
		<l>and is the only foot with which soul walks,</l>
		<l>soul-going straight or crooked-has no merit.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;What reason can see here,</l>
		<l>I can impart; past that, for truth of faith,</l>
		<l>it&apos;s Beatrice alone you must await.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Every substantial form, at once distinct</l>
		<l>from matter and conjoined to it, ingathers</l>
		<l>the force that is distinctively its own,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a force unknown to us until it acts-</l>
		<l>it&apos;s never shown except in its effects,</l>
		<l>just as green boughs display the life in plants.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And thus man does not know the source of his</l>
		<l>intelligence of primal notions and</l>
		<l>his tending toward desire&apos;s primal objects:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>both are in you just as in bees there is</l>
		<l>the honey-making urge; such primal will</l>
		<l>deserves no praise, and it deserves no blame.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now, that all other longings may conform</l>
		<l>to this first will, there is in you, inborn,</l>
		<l>the power that counsels, keeper of the threshold</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of your assent: this is the principle</l>
		<l>on which your merit may be judged, for it</l>
		<l>garners and winnows good and evil longings.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those reasoners who reached the roots of things</l>
		<l>learned of this inborn freedom; the bequest</l>
		<l>that, thus, they left unto the world is ethics.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even if we allow necessity</l>
		<l>as source for every love that flames in you,</l>
		<l>the power to curb that love is still your own.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This noble power is what Beatrice</l>
		<l>means by free will; therefore, remember it,</l>
		<l>if she should ever speak of it to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The moon, with midnight now behind us, made</l>
		<l>the stars seem scarcer to us; it was shaped</l>
		<l>just like a copper basin, gleaming, new;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and countercourse, it crossed those paths the sun</l>
		<l>ignites when those in Rome can see it set</l>
		<l>between the Corsicans and the Sardinians.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That gracious shade for whom Pietola</l>
		<l>won more renown than any Mantuan town,</l>
		<l>had freed me from the weight of doubt I bore;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that I, having harvested his clear</l>
		<l>and open answers to my questions, stood</l>
		<l>like one who, nearing sleep, has random visions.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But readiness for sleep was suddenly</l>
		<l>taken from me by people who, behind</l>
		<l>our backs, already turned in our direction.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as-of old-Ismenus and Asopus,</l>
		<l>at night, along their banks, saw crowds and clamor</l>
		<l>whenever Thebans had to summon Bacchus,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>such was the arching crowd that curved around</l>
		<l>that circle, driven on, as I made out,</l>
		<l>by righteous will as well as by just love.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Soon all that mighty throng drew near us, for</l>
		<l>they ran and ran; and two, in front of them,</l>
		<l>who wept, were crying: &quot;In her journey, Mary</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>made haste to reach the mountain, and, in order</l>
		<l>to conquer Lerida, first Caesar thrust</l>
		<l>against Marseilles, and then to Spain he rushed.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Following them, the others cried: &quot;Quick, quick,</l>
		<l>lest time be lost through insufficient love;</l>
		<l>where urge for good is keen, grace finds new green</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O people in whom eager fervor now</l>
		<l>may compensate for sloth and negligence</l>
		<l>you showed in doing good half-heartedly,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he-who&apos;s alive, and surely I don&apos;t lie</l>
		<l>to you-would climb above as soon as he</l>
		<l>has seen the sun shed light on us again;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then, tell us where the passage lies at hand.&quot;</l>
		<l>My guide said this. One of the souls replied:</l>
		<l>&quot;Come, follow us, and you will find the gap.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We are so fully anxious to advance-</l>
		<l>we cannot halt; and do forgive us, should</l>
		<l>you take our penance for discourtesy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I was St. Zeno&apos;s abbot in Verona</l>
		<l>under the rule of valiant Barbarossa,</l>
		<l>of whom Milan still speaks with so much sorrow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there is one with one foot in the grave,</l>
		<l>who soon will weep over that monastery,</l>
		<l>lamenting that he once had power there,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>because, in place of its true shepherd, he</l>
		<l>put one who was unsound of body and,</l>
		<l>still more, of mind, and born in sin-his son.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I don&apos;t know if he said more or was silent-</l>
		<l>he had already raced so far beyond us;</l>
		<l>but I heard this much and was pleased to hear it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he who was my help in every need</l>
		<l>said: &quot;Turn around: see those two coming-they</l>
		<l>whose words mock sloth.&quot; And I heard those two say</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>behind all of the rest: &quot;The ones for whom</l>
		<l>the sea parted were dead before the Jordan</l>
		<l>saw those who had inherited its lands;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and those who did not suffer trials until</l>
		<l>the end together with Anchises&apos; son</l>
		<l>gave themselves up to life without renown.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, when those shades were so far off from us</l>
		<l>that seeing them became impossible,</l>
		<l>a new thought rose inside of me and, from</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that thought, still others-many and diverse-</l>
		<l>were born: I was so drawn from random thought</l>
		<l>to thought that, wandering in mind, I shut</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my eyes, transforming thought on thought to dream.</l>
	</p>
</page>
