<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>My eyes were so insistent, so intent</l>
		<l>on finding satisfaction for their ten-</l>
		<l>year thirst that every other sense was spent.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And to each side, my eyes were walled in by</l>
		<l>indifference to all else (with its old net,</l>
		<l>the holy smile so drew them to itself),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when I was forced to turn my eyes leftward</l>
		<l>by those three goddesses because I heard</l>
		<l>them warning me: &quot;You stare too fixedly.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And the condition that afflicts the sight</l>
		<l>when eyes have just been struck by the sun&apos;s force</l>
		<l>left me without my vision for a time.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But when my sight became accustomed to</l>
		<l>lesser sensations (that is, lesser than</l>
		<l>the mighty force that made my eyes retreat),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw the glorious army: it had wheeled</l>
		<l>around and to the right; it had turned east;</l>
		<l>it faced the seven flames and faced the sun.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as, protected by its shields, a squadron</l>
		<l>will wheel, to save itself, around its standard</l>
		<l>until all of its men have changed direction;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so here all troops of the celestial kingdom</l>
		<l>within the vanguard passed in front of us</l>
		<l>before the chariot swung around the pole-shaft.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Back to the wheels the ladies then returned;</l>
		<l>and though the griffin moved the blessed burden,</l>
		<l>when he did that, none of his feathers stirred.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The lovely lady who&apos;d helped me ford Lethe,</l>
		<l>and I and Statius, following the wheel</l>
		<l>that turned right, round the inner, smaller arc,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>were slowly passing through the tall woods-empty</l>
		<l>because of one who had believed the serpent;</l>
		<l>our pace was measured by angelic song.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The space we covered could be matched perhaps</l>
		<l>by three flights of an unleashed arrow&apos;s shafts,</l>
		<l>when Beatrice descended from the chariot.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Adam,&quot; I heard all of them murmuring,</l>
		<l>and then they drew around a tree whose every</l>
		<l>branch had been stripped of flowers and of leaves.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As it grows higher, so its branches spread</l>
		<l>wider; it reached a height that even in</l>
		<l>their forests would amaze the Indians.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Blessed are you, whose beak does not, o griffin,</l>
		<l>pluck the sweet-tasting fruit that is forbidden</l>
		<l>and then afflicts the belly that has eaten!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, round the robust tree, the others shouted;</l>
		<l>and the two-natured animal: &quot;Thus is</l>
		<l>the seed of every righteous man preserved.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And turning to the pole-shaft he had pulled,</l>
		<l>he drew it to the foot of the stripped tree</l>
		<l>and, with a branch of that tree, tied the two.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just like our plants that, when the great light fa</l>
		<l>on earth, mixed with the light that shines behind</l>
		<l>the stars of the celestial Fishes, swell</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>with buds-each plant renews its coloring</l>
		<l>before the sun has yoked its steeds beneath</l>
		<l>another constellation: so the tree,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>whose boughs-before-had been so solitary,</l>
		<l>was now renewed, showing a tint that was</l>
		<l>less than the rose, more than the violet.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I did not understand the hymn that they</l>
		<l>then sang-it is not sung here on this earth-</l>
		<l>nor, drowsy, did I listen to the end.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Could I describe just how the ruthless eyes</l>
		<l>(eyes whose long wakefulness cost them so dear),</l>
		<l>hearing the tale of Syrinx, fell asleep,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then like a painter painting from a model,</l>
		<l>I&apos;d draw the way in which I fell asleep;</l>
		<l>but I refrain-let one more skillful paint.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I move, therefore, straight to my waking time;</l>
		<l>I say that radiance rent the veil of sleep,</l>
		<l>as did a voice: &quot;Rise up: what are you doing?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even as Peter, John, and James, when brought</l>
		<l>to see the blossoms of the apple tree-</l>
		<l>whose fruit abets the angels&apos; hungering,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>providing endless wedding-feasts in Heaven-</l>
		<l>were overwhelmed by what they saw, but then,</l>
		<l>hearing the word that shattered deeper sleeps,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>arose and saw their fellowship was smaller-</l>
		<l>since Moses and Elijah now had left-</l>
		<l>and saw a difference in their Teacher&apos;s dress;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so I awoke and saw, standing above me,</l>
		<l>she who before-compassionate-had guided</l>
		<l>my steps along the riverbank. Completely</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>bewildered, I asked: &quot;Where is Beatrice?&quot;</l>
		<l>And she: &quot;Beneath the boughs that were renewed,</l>
		<l>she&apos;s seated on the root of that tree; see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the company surrounding her; the rest</l>
		<l>have left; behind the griffin they have climbed</l>
		<l>on high with song that is more sweet, more deep.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I do not know if she said more than that,</l>
		<l>because,by now, I had in sight one who</l>
		<l>excluded all things other from my view.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>She sat alone upon the simple ground,</l>
		<l>left there as guardian of the chariot</l>
		<l>I&apos;d seen the two-form animal tie fast.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The seven nymphs encircled her as garland,</l>
		<l>and in their hands they held the lamps that can</l>
		<l>not be extinguished by the north or south winds.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Here you shall be-awhile-a visitor;</l>
		<l>but you shall be with me-and without end-</l>
		<l>Rome&apos;s citizen, the Rome in which Christ is</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Roman; and thus, to profit that world which</l>
		<l>lives badly, watch the chariot steadfastly</l>
		<l>and, when you have returned beyond, transcribe</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>what you have seen.&quot; Thus, Beatrice; and I,</l>
		<l>devoutly, at the feet of her commandments,</l>
		<l>set mind and eyes where she had wished me to.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Never has lightning fallen with such swift</l>
		<l>motion from a thick cloud, when it descends</l>
		<l>from the most distant limit in the heavens,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as did the bird of Jove that I saw swoop</l>
		<l>down through the tree, tearing the bark as well</l>
		<l>as the new leaves and the new flowering.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It struck the chariot with all its force;</l>
		<l>the chariot twisted, like a ship that&apos;s crossed</l>
		<l>by seas that now storm starboard and now port.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I then saw, as it leaped into the body</l>
		<l>of that triumphal chariot, a fox</l>
		<l>that seemed to lack all honest nourishment:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but, as she railed against its squalid sins,</l>
		<l>my lady forced that fox to flight as quick</l>
		<l>as, stripped of flesh, its bones permitted it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I could see the eagle plunge-again</l>
		<l>down through the tree-into the chariot</l>
		<l>and leave it feathered with its plumage; and,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just like a voice from an embittered heart,</l>
		<l>a voice issued from Heaven, saying this:</l>
		<l>&quot;O my small bark, your freight is wickedness!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then did the ground between the two wheels seem</l>
		<l>to me to open; from the earth, a dragon</l>
		<l>emerged; it drove its tail up through the chariot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and like a wasp when it retracts its sting,</l>
		<l>drawing its venomed tail back to itself,</l>
		<l>it dragged part of the bottom off, and went</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>its way, undulating. And what was left</l>
		<l>was covered with the eagle&apos;s plumes-perhaps</l>
		<l>offered with sound and kind intent-much as</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>grass covers fertile ground; and the pole-shaft</l>
		<l>and both wheels were re-covered in less time</l>
		<l>than mouth must be kept open when one sighs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Transfigured so, the saintly instrument</l>
		<l>grew heads, which sprouted from its parts; three g</l>
		<l>upon the pole-shaft, and one at each corner.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The three were horned like oxen, but the four</l>
		<l>had just a single horn upon their foreheads:</l>
		<l>such monsters never have been seen before.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just like a fortress set on a steep slope,</l>
		<l>securely seated there, ungirt, a whore,</l>
		<l>whose eyes were quick to rove, appeared to me;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and I saw at her side, erect, a giant,</l>
		<l>who seemed to serve as her custodian;</l>
		<l>and they-again, again-embraced each other.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But when she turned her wandering, wanton eyes</l>
		<l>to me, then that ferocious amador</l>
		<l>beat her from head to foot; then, swollen with</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>suspicion, fierce with anger, he untied</l>
		<l>the chariot-made-monster, dragging it</l>
		<l>into the wood, so that I could not see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>either the whore or the strange chariot-beast.</l>
	</p>
</page>
