<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Against a better will, the will fights weakly;</l>
		<l>therefore, to please him, though against my pleasu</l>
		<l>I drew my unquenched sponge out of the water.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I moved on, and my guide moved through the un-</l>
		<l>encumbered space, hugging the rock, as one</l>
		<l>walks on a wall, close to the battlements;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for those whose eyes would melt down, drop by drop</l>
		<l>the evil that possesses all the world,</l>
		<l>were too close to the edge, on the far side.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>May you be damned, o ancient wolf, whose power</l>
		<l>can claim more prey than all the other beasts-</l>
		<l>your hungering is deep and never-ending!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O heavens, through whose revolutions many</l>
		<l>think things on earth are changed, when will he co</l>
		<l>the one whose works will drive that wolf away?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Our steps were short and slow as we moved on;</l>
		<l>I was attentive to the shades; I heard</l>
		<l>the sorrow in their tears and lamentations.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I, by chance, heard one ahead of us</l>
		<l>crying in his lament, &quot;Sweet Mary,&quot; as</l>
		<l>a woman would outcry in labor pains.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he continued: &quot;In that hostel where</l>
		<l>you had set down your holy burden, there</l>
		<l>one can discover just how poor you were.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Following this I heard: &quot;O good Fabricius,</l>
		<l>you chose, as your possessions, indigence</l>
		<l>with virtue rather than much wealth with vice.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These words had been so pleasing to me-I</l>
		<l>moved forward, so that I might come to know</l>
		<l>the spirit from whom they had seemed to come.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He kept on speaking, telling the largesse</l>
		<l>of Nicholas-the gifts he gave the maidens</l>
		<l>so that they might be honorably wed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O soul who speaks of so much righteousness,</l>
		<l>do tell me who you were,&quot; I said, &quot;and why</l>
		<l>just you alone renew these seemly praises.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Your speaking to me will not go unthanked</l>
		<l>when I return to finish the short span</l>
		<l>of that life which now hurries toward its end.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he: &quot;I&apos;ll tell you-not because I hope</l>
		<l>for solace from your world, but for such grace</l>
		<l>as shines in you before your death&apos;s arrived.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I was the root of the obnoxious plant</l>
		<l>that overshadows all the Christian lands,</l>
		<l>so that fine fruit can rarely rise from them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But if Douai and Lille and Bruges and Ghent</l>
		<l>had power, they would soon take vengeance on it;</l>
		<l>and this I beg of Him who judges all.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The name I bore beyond was Hugh Capet:</l>
		<l>of me were born the Louises and Philips</l>
		<l>by whom France has been ruled most recently.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I was the son of a Parisian butcher.</l>
		<l>When all the line of ancient kings was done</l>
		<l>and only one-a monk in gray-survived,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I found the reins that ruled the kingdom tight</l>
		<l>within my hands, and I held so much new-</l>
		<l>gained power and possessed so many friends</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that, to the widowed crown, my own son&apos;s head</l>
		<l>was elevated, and from him began</l>
		<l>the consecrated bones of all those kings.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Until the giant dowry of Provence</l>
		<l>removed all sense of shame within my house,</l>
		<l>my line was not worth much, but did no wrong.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There its rapine began with lies and force;</l>
		<l>and then it seized-that it might make amends-</l>
		<l>Ponthieu and Normandy and Gascony.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Charles came to Italy and, for amends,</l>
		<l>made Conradin a victim, and then thrust</l>
		<l>back Thomas into Heaven, for amends.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I see a time-not too far off-in which</l>
		<l>another Charles advances out of France</l>
		<l>to make himself and his descendants famous.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He does not carry weapons when he comes,</l>
		<l>only the lance that Judas tilted; this</l>
		<l>he couches so-he twists the paunch of Florence.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From this he&apos;ll gain not land, just shame and sin,</l>
		<l>which will be all the heavier for him</l>
		<l>as he would reckon lightly such disgrace.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The other, who once left his ship as prisoner-</l>
		<l>I see him sell his daughter, bargaining</l>
		<l>as pirates haggle over female slaves.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O avarice, my house is now your captive:</l>
		<l>it traffics in the flesh of its own children-</l>
		<l>what more is left for you to do to us?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That past and future evil may seem less,</l>
		<l>I see the fleur-de-lis enter Anagni</l>
		<l>and, in His vicar, Christ made prisoner.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I see Him mocked a second time; I see</l>
		<l>the vinegar and gall renewed-and He</l>
		<l>is slain between two thieves who&apos;re still alive.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I see the new Pilate, one so cruel</l>
		<l>that, still not sated, he, without decree,</l>
		<l>carries his greedy sails into the Temple.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O You, my Lord, when will You let me be</l>
		<l>happy on seeing vengeance that, concealed,</l>
		<l>makes sweet Your anger in Your secrecy?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What I have said about the only bride</l>
		<l>the Holy Ghost has known, the words that made</l>
		<l>you turn to me for commentary-these</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>words serve as answer to our prayers as long</l>
		<l>as it is day; but when night falls, then we</l>
		<l>recite examples that are contrary.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then we tell over how Pygmalion,</l>
		<l>out of his greedy lust for gold, became</l>
		<l>a thief and traitor and a parricide;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the wretchedness of avaricious Midas,</l>
		<l>resulting from his ravenous request,</l>
		<l>the consequence that always makes men laugh;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and each of us recalls the foolish Achan-</l>
		<l>how he had robbed the spoils, so that the anger</l>
		<l>of Joshua still seems to sting him here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then we acase Sapphira and her husband;</l>
		<l>we praise the kicks Heliodorus suffered;</l>
		<l>and Polymnestor, who killed Polydorus,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>resounds, in infamy, round all this mountain;</l>
		<l>and finally, what we cry here is: Crassus,</l>
		<l>tell us, because you know: &quot;How does gold taste?&quot;&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At times one speaks aloud, another low,</l>
		<l>according to the sentiment that goads</l>
		<l>us now to be more swift and now more slow:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>thus, I was not alone in speaking of</l>
		<l>the good we cite by day, but here nearby</l>
		<l>no other spirit raised his voice as high.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We had already taken leave of him</l>
		<l>and were already struggling to advance</l>
		<l>along that road as far as we were able,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when I could feel the mountain tremble like</l>
		<l>a falling thing; at which a chill seized me</l>
		<l>as cold grips one who goes to meet his death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Delos had surely not been buffeted</l>
		<l>so hard before Latona planted there</l>
		<l>the nest in which to bear the sky&apos;s two eyes.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then such a shout rose up on every side</l>
		<l>that, drawing near to me, my master said:</l>
		<l>&quot;Don&apos;t be afraid, as long as I&apos;m your guide.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Gloria in excelsis Deo,&quot; they all cried-</l>
		<l>so did I understand from those nearby,</l>
		<l>whose shouted words were able to be heard.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just like the shepherds who first heard that song,</l>
		<l>we stood, but did not move, in expectation,</l>
		<l>until the trembling stopped, the song was done.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then we took up again our holy path,</l>
		<l>watching the shades who lay along the ground,</l>
		<l>who had resumed their customary tears.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My ignorance has never struggled so,</l>
		<l>has never made me long so much to know-</l>
		<l>if memory does not mislead me now-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as it seemed then to long within my thoughts;</l>
		<l>nor did I dare to ask-we were so rushed;</l>
		<l>nor, by myself, could I discern the cause.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, timid, pensive, I pursued my way.</l>
	</p>
</page>
