<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Who is this man who, although death has yet</l>
		<l>to grant him flight, can circle round our mountain</l>
		<l>and can, at will, open and shut his eyes?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;I don&apos;t know who he is, but I do know</l>
		<l>he&apos;s not alone; you&apos;re closer; question him</l>
		<l>and greet him gently, so that he replies.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So were two spirits, leaning toward each other,</l>
		<l>discussing me, along my right-hand side;</l>
		<l>then they bent back their heads to speak to me,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and one began: &quot;O soul who-still enclosed</l>
		<l>within the body-make your way toward Heaven,</l>
		<l>may you, through love, console us; tell us who</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you are, from where you come; the grace that you&apos;ve</l>
		<l>received-a thing that&apos;s never come to pass</l>
		<l>before-has caused us much astonishment.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I: &quot;Through central Tuscany there spreads</l>
		<l>a little stream first born in Falterona;</l>
		<l>one hundred miles can&apos;t fill the course it needs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I bring this body from that river&apos;s banks;</l>
		<l>to tell you who I am would be to speak</l>
		<l>in vain-my name has not yet gained much fame.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;If, with my understanding, I have seized</l>
		<l>your meaning properly,&quot; replied to me</l>
		<l>the one who&apos;d spoken first, &quot;you mean the Arno.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The other said to him: &quot;Why did he hide</l>
		<l>that river&apos;s name, even as one would do</l>
		<l>in hiding something horrible from view?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The shade to whom this question was addressed</l>
		<l>repaid with this: &quot;I do not know; but it</l>
		<l>is right for such a valley&apos;s name to perish,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for from its source (at which the rugged chain-</l>
		<l>from which Pelorus was cut off-surpasses</l>
		<l>most other places with its mass of mountains)</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>until its end point (where it offers back</l>
		<l>those waters that evaporating skies</l>
		<l>drew from the sea, that streams may be supplied),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>virtue is seen as serpent, and all flee</l>
		<l>from it as if it were an enemy,</l>
		<l>either because the site is ill-starred or</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>their evil custom goads them so; therefore,</l>
		<l>the nature of that squalid valley&apos;s people</l>
		<l>has changed, as if they were in Circe&apos;s pasture.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That river starts its miserable course</l>
		<l>among foul hogs, more fit for acorns than</l>
		<l>for food devised to serve the needs of man.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, as that stream descends, it comes on curs</l>
		<l>that, though their force is feeble, snap and snarl</l>
		<l>scornful of them, it swerves its snout away.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And, downward, it flows on; and when that ditch,</l>
		<l>ill-fated and accursed, grows wider, it</l>
		<l>finds, more and more, the dogs becoming wolves.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Descending then through many dark ravines,</l>
		<l>it comes on foxes so full of deceit-</l>
		<l>there is no trap that they cannot defeat.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nor will I keep from speech because my comrade</l>
		<l>hears me (and it will serve you, too, to keep</l>
		<l>in mind what prophecy reveals to me).</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I see your grandson: he&apos;s become a hunter</l>
		<l>of wolves along the banks of the fierce river,</l>
		<l>and he strikes every one of them with terror.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He sells their flesh while they are still alive;</l>
		<l>then, like an ancient beast, he turns to slaughter</l>
		<l>depriving many of life, himself of honor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Bloody, he comes out from the wood he&apos;s plundered,</l>
		<l>leaving it such that in a thousand years</l>
		<l>it will not be the forest that it was.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as the face of one who has heard word</l>
		<l>of pain and injury becomes perturbed,</l>
		<l>no matter from what side that menace stirs,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did I see that other soul, who&apos;d turned</l>
		<l>to listen, growing anxious and dejected</l>
		<l>when he had taken in his comrade&apos;s words.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The speech of one, the aspect of the other</l>
		<l>had made me need to know their names, and I</l>
		<l>both queried and beseeched at the same time,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>at which the spirit who had spoken first</l>
		<l>to me began again: &quot;You&apos;d have me do</l>
		<l>for you that which, to me, you have refused.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But since God would, in you, have His grace glow</l>
		<l>so brightly, I shall not be miserly;</l>
		<l>know, therefore, that I was Guido del Duca.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My blood was so afire with envy that,</l>
		<l>when I had seen a man becoming happy,</l>
		<l>the lividness in me was plain to see.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From what I&apos;ve sown, this is the straw I reap:</l>
		<l>o humankind, why do you set your hearts</l>
		<l>there where our sharing cannot have a part?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This is Rinieri, this is he-the glory,</l>
		<l>the honor of the house of Calboli;</l>
		<l>but no one has inherited his worth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It&apos;s not his kin alone, between the Po</l>
		<l>and mountains, and the Reno and the coast,</l>
		<l>who&apos;ve lost the truth&apos;s grave good and lost the go</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of gentle living, too; those lands are full</l>
		<l>of poisoned stumps; by now, however much</l>
		<l>one were to cultivate, it is too late.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Where is good Lizio? Arrigo Mainardi?</l>
		<l>Pier Traversaro? Guido di Carpigna?</l>
		<l>O Romagnoles returned to bastardy!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When will a Fabbro flourish in Bologna?</l>
		<l>When, in Faenza, a Bernadin di Fosco,</l>
		<l>the noble offshoot of a humble plant?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Don&apos;t wonder, Tuscan, if I weep when I</l>
		<l>remember Ugolino d&apos;Azzo, one</l>
		<l>who lived among us, and Guido da Prata,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the house of Traversara, of Anastagi</l>
		<l>(both houses without heirs), and Federigo</l>
		<l>Tignoso and his gracious company,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the ladies and the knights, labors and leisure</l>
		<l>to which we once were urged by courtesy</l>
		<l>and love, where hearts now host perversity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O Bretinoro, why do you not flee-</l>
		<l>when you&apos;ve already lost your family</l>
		<l>and many men who&apos;ve fled iniquity?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Bagnacaval does well: it breeds no more-</l>
		<l>and Castrocuro ill, and Conio worse,</l>
		<l>for it insists on breeding counts so cursed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Once freed of their own demon, the Pagani</l>
		<l>will do quite well, but not so well that any</l>
		<l>will testify that they are pure and worthy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Your name, o Ugolin de&apos; Fantolini,</l>
		<l>is safe, since one no longer waits for heirs</l>
		<l>to blacken it with their degeneracy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But, Tuscan, go your way; I am more pleased</l>
		<l>to weep now than to speak: for that which we</l>
		<l>have spoken presses heavily on me!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We knew those gentle souls had heard us move</l>
		<l>away; therefore, their silence made us feel</l>
		<l>more confident about the path we took.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When we, who&apos;d gone ahead, were left alone,</l>
		<l>a voice that seemed like lightning as it splits</l>
		<l>the air encountered us, a voice that said:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Whoever captures me will slaughter me&quot;;</l>
		<l>and then it fled like thunder when it fades</l>
		<l>after the cloud is suddenly ripped through.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As soon as that first voice had granted us</l>
		<l>a truce, another voice cried out with such</l>
		<l>uproar-like thunder quick to follow thunder:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;I am Aglauros, who was turned to stone&quot;;</l>
		<l>and then, to draw more near the poet, I</l>
		<l>moved to my right instead of moving forward.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By now the air on every side was quiet;</l>
		<l>and he told me: &quot;That is the sturdy bit</l>
		<l>that should hold every man within his limits.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But you would take the bait, so that the hook</l>
		<l>of the old adversary draws you to him;</l>
		<l>thus, neither spur nor curb can serve to save you.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Heaven would call-and it encircles-you;</l>
		<l>it lets you see its never-ending beauties;</l>
		<l>and yet your eyes would only see the ground;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>thus, He who sees all things would strike you down."</l>
	</p>
</page>
