<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Oppressed with stupor, I unto my guide</l>
    <l>Turned like a little child who always runs</l>
    <l>For refuge there where he confideth most;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And she, even as a mother who straightway</l>
    <l>Gives comfort to her pale and breathless boy</l>
    <l>With voice whose wont it is to reassure him,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Said to me: &quot;Knowest thou not thou art in heaven,</l>
    <l>And knowest thou not that heaven is holy all</l>
    <l>And what is done here cometh from good zeal?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After what wise the singing would have changed thee</l>
    <l>And I by smiling, thou canst now imagine,</l>
    <l>Since that the cry has startled thee so much,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In which if thou hadst understood its prayers</l>
    <l>Already would be known to thee the vengeance</l>
    <l>Which thou shalt look upon before thou diest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The sword above here smiteth not in haste</l>
    <l>Nor tardily, howe'er it seem to him</l>
    <l>Who fearing or desiring waits for it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But turn thee round towards the others now,</l>
    <l>For very illustrious spirits shalt thou see,</l>
    <l>If thou thy sight directest as I say.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As it seemed good to her mine eyes I turned,</l>
    <l>And saw a hundred spherules that together</l>
    <l>With mutual rays each other more embellished.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I stood as one who in himself represses</l>
    <l>The point of his desire, and ventures not</l>
    <l>To question, he so feareth the too much.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And now the largest and most luculent</l>
    <l>Among those pearls came forward, that it might</l>
    <l>Make my desire concerning it content.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Within it then I heard: &quot;If thou couldst see</l>
    <l>Even as myself the charity that burns</l>
    <l>Among us, thy conceits would be expressed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But, that by waiting thou mayst not come late</l>
    <l>To the high end, I will make answer even</l>
    <l>Unto the thought of which thou art so chary.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That mountain on whose slope Cassino stands</l>
    <l>Was frequented of old upon its summit</l>
    <l>By a deluded folk and ill-disposed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I am he who first up thither bore</l>
    <l>The name of Him who brought upon the earth</l>
    <l>The truth that so much sublimateth us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And such abundant grace upon me shone</l>
    <l>That all the neighbouring towns I drew away</l>
    <l>From the impious worship that seduced the world.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>These other fires, each one of them, were men</l>
    <l>Contemplative, enkindled by that heat</l>
    <l>Which maketh holy flowers and fruits spring up.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here is Macarius, here is Romualdus,</l>
    <l>Here are my brethren, who within the cloisters</l>
    <l>Their footsteps stayed and kept a steadfast heart.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I to him: &quot;The affection which thou showest</l>
    <l>Speaking with me, and the good countenance</l>
    <l>Which I behold and note in all your ardours,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In me have so my confidence dilated</l>
    <l>As the sun doth the rose, when it becomes</l>
    <l>As far unfolded as it hath the power.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore I pray, and thou assure me, father,</l>
    <l>If I may so much grace receive, that I</l>
    <l>May thee behold with countenance unveiled.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He thereupon: &quot;Brother, thy high desire</l>
    <l>In the remotest sphere shall be fulfilled,</l>
    <l>Where are fulfilled all others and my own.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There perfect is, and ripened, and complete,</l>
    <l>Every desire; within that one alone</l>
    <l>Is every part where it has always been;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For it is not in space, nor turns on poles,</l>
    <l>And unto it our stairway reaches up,</l>
    <l>Whence thus from out thy sight it steals away.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Up to that height the Patriarch Jacob saw it</l>
    <l>Extending its supernal part, what time</l>
    <l>So thronged with angels it appeared to him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But to ascend it now no one uplifts</l>
    <l>His feet from off the earth, and now my Rule</l>
    <l>Below remaineth for mere waste of paper.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The walls that used of old to be an Abbey</l>
    <l>Are changed to dens of robbers, and the cowls</l>
    <l>Are sacks filled full of miserable flour.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But heavy usury is not taken up</l>
    <l>So much against God's pleasure as that fruit</l>
    <l>Which maketh so insane the heart of monks;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For whatsoever hath the Church in keeping</l>
    <l>Is for the folk that ask it in God's name,</l>
    <l>Not for one's kindred or for something worse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The flesh of mortals is so very soft,</l>
    <l>That good beginnings down below suffice not</l>
    <l>From springing of the oak to bearing acorns.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Peter began with neither gold nor silver,</l>
    <l>And I with orison and abstinence,</l>
    <l>And Francis with humility his convent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if thou lookest at each one's beginning,</l>
    <l>And then regardest whither he has run,</l>
    <l>Thou shalt behold the white changed into brown.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In verity the Jordan backward turned,</l>
    <l>And the sea's fleeing, when God willed were more</l>
    <l>A wonder to behold, than succour here.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus unto me he said; and then withdrew</l>
    <l>To his own band, and the band closed together;</l>
    <l>Then like a whirlwind all was upward rapt.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The gentle Lady urged me on behind them</l>
    <l>Up o'er that stairway by a single sign,</l>
    <l>So did her virtue overcome my nature;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor here below, where one goes up and down</l>
    <l>By natural law, was motion e'er so swift</l>
    <l>That it could be compared unto my wing.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Reader, as I may unto that devout</l>
    <l>Triumph return, on whose account I often</l>
    <l>For my transgressions weep and beat my breast,--</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou hadst not thrust thy finger in the fire</l>
    <l>And drawn it out again, before I saw</l>
    <l>The sign that follows Taurus, and was in it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O glorious stars, O light impregnated</l>
    <l>With mighty virtue, from which I acknowledge</l>
    <l>All of my genius, whatsoe'er it be,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With you was born, and hid himself with you,</l>
    <l>He who is father of all mortal life,</l>
    <l>When first I tasted of the Tuscan air;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And then when grace was freely given to me</l>
    <l>To enter the high wheel which turns you round,</l>
    <l>Your region was allotted unto me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To you devoutly at this hour my soul</l>
    <l>Is sighing, that it virtue may acquire</l>
    <l>For the stern pass that draws it to itself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Thou art so near unto the last salvation,&quot;</l>
    <l>Thus Beatrice began, &quot;thou oughtest now</l>
    <l>To have thine eves unclouded and acute;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And therefore, ere thou enter farther in,</l>
    <l>Look down once more, and see how vast a world</l>
    <l>Thou hast already put beneath thy feet;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that thy heart, as jocund as it may,</l>
    <l>Present itself to the triumphant throng</l>
    <l>That comes rejoicing through this rounded ether.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I with my sight returned through one and all</l>
    <l>The sevenfold spheres, and I beheld this globe</l>
    <l>Such that I smiled at its ignoble semblance;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And that opinion I approve as best</l>
    <l>Which doth account it least; and he who thinks</l>
    <l>Of something else may truly be called just.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I saw the daughter of Latona shining</l>
    <l>Without that shadow, which to me was cause</l>
    <l>That once I had believed her rare and dense.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The aspect of thy son, Hyperion,</l>
    <l>Here I sustained, and saw how move themselves</l>
    <l>Around and near him Maia and Dione.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thence there appeared the temperateness of Jove</l>
    <l>'Twixt son and father, and to me was clear</l>
    <l>The change that of their whereabout they make;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And all the seven made manifest to me</l>
    <l>How great they are, and eke how swift they are,</l>
    <l>And how they are in distant habitations.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The threshing-floor that maketh us so proud,</l>
    <l>To me revolving with the eternal Twins,</l>
    <l>Was all apparent made from hill to harbour!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then to the beauteous eyes mine eyes I turned.</l>
  </p>
</page>