<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Osanna sanctus Deus Sabaoth,</l>
    <l>Superillustrans claritate tua</l>
    <l>Felices ignes horum malahoth!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In this wise, to his melody returning,</l>
    <l>This substance, upon which a double light</l>
    <l>Doubles itself, was seen by me to sing,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And to their dance this and the others moved,</l>
    <l>And in the manner of swift-hurrying sparks</l>
    <l>Veiled themselves from me with a sudden distance.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Doubting was I, and saying, &quot;Tell her, tell her,&quot;</l>
    <l>Within me, &quot;tell her,&quot; saying, &quot;tell my Lady,&quot;</l>
    <l>Who slakes my thirst with her sweet effluences;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And yet that reverence which doth lord it over</l>
    <l>The whole of me only by B and ICE,</l>
    <l>Bowed me again like unto one who drowses.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Short while did Beatrice endure me thus;</l>
    <l>And she began, lighting me with a smile</l>
    <l>Such as would make one happy in the fire:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;According to infallible advisement,</l>
    <l>After what manner a just vengeance justly</l>
    <l>Could be avenged has put thee upon thinking,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But I will speedily thy mind unloose;</l>
    <l>And do thou listen, for these words of mine</l>
    <l>Of a great doctrine will a present make thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By not enduring on the power that wills</l>
    <l>Curb for his good, that man who ne'er was born,</l>
    <l>Damning himself damned all his progeny;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whereby the human species down below</l>
    <l>Lay sick for many centuries in great error,</l>
    <l>Till to descend it pleased the Word of God</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To where the nature, which from its own Maker</l>
    <l>Estranged itself, he joined to him in person</l>
    <l>By the sole act of his eternal love.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now unto what is said direct thy sight;</l>
    <l>This nature when united to its Maker,</l>
    <l>Such as created, was sincere and good;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But by itself alone was banished forth</l>
    <l>From Paradise, because it turned aside</l>
    <l>Out of the way of truth and of its life.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore the penalty the cross held out,</l>
    <l>If measured by the nature thus assumed,</l>
    <l>None ever yet with so great justice stung,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And none was ever of so great injustice,</l>
    <l>Considering who the Person was that suffered,</l>
    <l>Within whom such a nature was contracted.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From one act therefore issued things diverse;</l>
    <l>To God and to the Jews one death was pleasing;</l>
    <l>Earth trembled at it and the Heaven was opened.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>It should no longer now seem difficult</l>
    <l>To thee, when it is said that a just vengeance</l>
    <l>By a just court was afterward avenged.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But now do I behold thy mind entangled</l>
    <l>From thought to thought within a knot, from which</l>
    <l>With great desire it waits to free itself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou sayest, 'Well discern I what I hear;</l>
    <l>But it is hidden from me why God willed</l>
    <l>For our redemption only this one mode.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Buried remaineth, brother, this decree</l>
    <l>Unto the eyes of every one whose nature</l>
    <l>Is in the flame of love not yet adult.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Verily, inasmuch as at this mark</l>
    <l>One gazes long and little is discerned,</l>
    <l>Wherefore this mode was worthiest will I say.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Goodness Divine, which from itself doth spurn</l>
    <l>All envy, burning in itself so sparkles</l>
    <l>That the eternal beauties it unfolds.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whate'er from this immediately distils</l>
    <l>Has afterwards no end, for ne'er removed</l>
    <l>Is its impression when it sets its seal.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whate'er from this immediately rains down</l>
    <l>Is wholly free, because it is not subject</l>
    <l>Unto the influences of novel things.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The more conformed thereto, the more it pleases;</l>
    <l>For the blest ardour that irradiates all things</l>
    <l>In that most like itself is most vivacious.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With all of these things has advantaged been</l>
    <l>The human creature; and if one be wanting,</l>
    <l>From his nobility he needs must fall.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Tis sin alone which doth disfranchise him,</l>
    <l>And render him unlike the Good Supreme,</l>
    <l>So that he little with its light is blanched,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And to his dignity no more returns,</l>
    <l>Unless he fill up where transgression empties</l>
    <l>With righteous pains for criminal delights.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Your nature when it sinned so utterly</l>
    <l>In its own seed, out of these dignities</l>
    <l>Even as out of Paradise was driven,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor could itself recover, if thou notest</l>
    <l>With nicest subtilty, by any way,</l>
    <l>Except by passing one of these two fords:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Either that God through clemency alone</l>
    <l>Had pardon granted, or that man himself</l>
    <l>Had satisfaction for his folly made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Fix now thine eye deep into the abyss</l>
    <l>Of the eternal counsel, to my speech</l>
    <l>As far as may be fastened steadfastly!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Man in his limitations had not power</l>
    <l>To satisfy, not having power to sink</l>
    <l>In his humility obeying then,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Far as he disobeying thought to rise;</l>
    <l>And for this reason man has been from power</l>
    <l>Of satisfying by himself excluded.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore it God behoved in his own ways</l>
    <l>Man to restore unto his perfect life,</l>
    <l>I say in one, or else in both of them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But since the action of the doer is</l>
    <l>So much more grateful, as it more presents</l>
    <l>The goodness of the heart from which it issues,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Goodness Divine, that doth imprint the world,</l>
    <l>Has been contented to proceed by each</l>
    <l>And all its ways to lift you up again;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor 'twixt the first day and the final night</l>
    <l>Such high and such magnificent proceeding</l>
    <l>By one or by the other was or shall be;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For God more bounteous was himself to give</l>
    <l>To make man able to uplift himself,</l>
    <l>Than if he only of himself had pardoned;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And all the other modes were insufficient</l>
    <l>For justice, were it not the Son of God</l>
    <l>Himself had humbled to become incarnate.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now, to fill fully each desire of thine,</l>
    <l>Return I to elucidate one place,</l>
    <l>In order that thou there mayst see as I do.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou sayst: 'I see the air, I see the fire,</l>
    <l>The water, and the earth, and all their mixtures</l>
    <l>Come to corruption, and short while endure;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And these things notwithstanding were created;'</l>
    <l>Therefore if that which I have said were true,</l>
    <l>They should have been secure against corruption.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Angels, brother, and the land sincere</l>
    <l>In which thou art, created may be called</l>
    <l>Just as they are in their entire existence;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But all the elements which thou hast named,</l>
    <l>And all those things which out of them are made,</l>
    <l>By a created virtue are informed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Created was the matter which they have;</l>
    <l>Created was the informing influence</l>
    <l>Within these stars that round about them go.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The soul of every brute and of the plants</l>
    <l>By its potential temperament attracts</l>
    <l>The ray and motion of the holy lights;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But your own life immediately inspires</l>
    <l>Supreme Beneficence, and enamours it</l>
    <l>So with herself, it evermore desires her.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And thou from this mayst argue furthermore</l>
    <l>Your resurrection, if thou think again</l>
    <l>How human flesh was fashioned at that time</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When the first parents both of them were made.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>