<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Soon as the blessed flame had taken up</l>
    <l>The final word to give it utterance,</l>
    <l>Began the holy millstone to revolve,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in its gyre had not turned wholly round,</l>
    <l>Before another in a ring enclosed it,</l>
    <l>And motion joined to motion, song to song;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Song that as greatly doth transcend our Muses,</l>
    <l>Our Sirens, in those dulcet clarions,</l>
    <l>As primal splendour that which is reflected.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as are spanned athwart a tender cloud</l>
    <l>Two rainbows parallel and like in colour,</l>
    <l>When Juno to her handmaid gives command,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>(The one without born of the one within,</l>
    <l>Like to the speaking of that vagrant one</l>
    <l>Whom love consumed as doth the sun the vapours,)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And make the people here, through covenant</l>
    <l>God set with Noah, presageful of the world</l>
    <l>That shall no more be covered with a flood,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In such wise of those sempiternal roses</l>
    <l>The garlands twain encompassed us about,</l>
    <l>And thus the outer to the inner answered.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After the dance, and other grand rejoicings,</l>
    <l>Both of the singing, and the flaming forth</l>
    <l>Effulgence with effulgence blithe and tender,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Together, at once, with one accord had stopped,</l>
    <l>(Even as the eyes, that, as volition moves them,</l>
    <l>Must needs together shut and lift themselves,)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Out of the heart of one of the new lights</l>
    <l>There came a voice, that needle to the star</l>
    <l>Made me appear in turning thitherward.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And it began: &quot;The love that makes me fair</l>
    <l>Draws me to speak about the other leader,</l>
    <l>By whom so well is spoken here of mine.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Tis right, where one is, to bring in the other,</l>
    <l>That, as they were united in their warfare,</l>
    <l>Together likewise may their glory shine.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The soldiery of Christ, which it had cost</l>
    <l>So dear to arm again, behind the standard</l>
    <l>Moved slow and doubtful and in numbers few,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When the Emperor who reigneth evermore</l>
    <l>Provided for the host that was in peril,</l>
    <l>Through grace alone and not that it was worthy;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And, as was said, he to his Bride brought succour</l>
    <l>With champions twain, at whose deed, at whose word</l>
    <l>The straggling people were together drawn.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Within that region where the sweet west wind</l>
    <l>Rises to open the new leaves, wherewith</l>
    <l>Europe is seen to clothe herself afresh,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not far off from the beating of the waves,</l>
    <l>Behind which in his long career the sun</l>
    <l>Sometimes conceals himself from every man,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Is situate the fortunate Calahorra,</l>
    <l>Under protection of the mighty shield</l>
    <l>In which the Lion subject is and sovereign.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therein was born the amorous paramour</l>
    <l>Of Christian Faith, the athlete consecrate,</l>
    <l>Kind to his own and cruel to his foes;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And when it was created was his mind</l>
    <l>Replete with such a living energy,</l>
    <l>That in his mother her it made prophetic.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As soon as the espousals were complete</l>
    <l>Between him and the Faith at holy font,</l>
    <l>Where they with mutual safety dowered each other,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The woman, who for him had given assent,</l>
    <l>Saw in a dream the admirable fruit</l>
    <l>That issue would from him and from his heirs;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And that he might be construed as he was,</l>
    <l>A spirit from this place went forth to name him</l>
    <l>With His possessive whose he wholly was.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Dominic was he called; and him I speak of</l>
    <l>Even as of the husbandman whom Christ</l>
    <l>Elected to his garden to assist him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Envoy and servant sooth he seemed of Christ,</l>
    <l>For the first love made manifest in him</l>
    <l>Was the first counsel that was given by Christ.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Silent and wakeful many a time was he</l>
    <l>Discovered by his nurse upon the ground,</l>
    <l>As if he would have said, 'For this I came.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O thou his father, Felix verily!</l>
    <l>O thou his mother, verily Joanna,</l>
    <l>If this, interpreted, means as is said!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not for the world which people toil for now</l>
    <l>In following Ostiense and Taddeo,</l>
    <l>But through his longing after the true manna,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He in short time became so great a teacher,</l>
    <l>That he began to go about the vineyard,</l>
    <l>Which fadeth soon, if faithless be the dresser;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And of the See, (that once was more benignant</l>
    <l>Unto the righteous poor, not through itself,</l>
    <l>But him who sits there and degenerates,)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not to dispense or two or three for six,</l>
    <l>Not any fortune of first vacancy,</l>
    <l>'Non decimas quae sunt pauperum Dei,'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He asked for, but against the errant world</l>
    <l>Permission to do battle for the seed,</l>
    <l>Of which these four and twenty plants surround thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then with the doctrine and the will together,</l>
    <l>With office apostolical he moved,</l>
    <l>Like torrent which some lofty vein out-presses;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in among the shoots heretical</l>
    <l>His impetus with greater fury smote,</l>
    <l>Wherever the resistance was the greatest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Of him were made thereafter divers runnels,</l>
    <l>Whereby the garden catholic is watered,</l>
    <l>So that more living its plantations stand.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If such the one wheel of the Biga was,</l>
    <l>In which the Holy Church itself defended</l>
    <l>And in the field its civic battle won,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Truly full manifest should be to thee</l>
    <l>The excellence of the other, unto whom</l>
    <l>Thomas so courteous was before my coming.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But still the orbit, which the highest part</l>
    <l>Of its circumference made, is derelict,</l>
    <l>So that the mould is where was once the crust.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>His family, that had straight forward moved</l>
    <l>With feet upon his footprints, are turned round</l>
    <l>So that they set the point upon the heel.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And soon aware they will be of the harvest</l>
    <l>Of this bad husbandry, when shall the tares</l>
    <l>Complain the granary is taken from them.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Yet say I, he who searcheth leaf by leaf</l>
    <l>Our volume through, would still some page discover</l>
    <l>Where he could read, 'I am as I am wont.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Twill not be from Casal nor Acquasparta,</l>
    <l>From whence come such unto the written word</l>
    <l>That one avoids it, and the other narrows.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Bonaventura of Bagnoregio's life</l>
    <l>Am I, who always in great offices</l>
    <l>Postponed considerations sinister.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here are Illuminato and Agostino,</l>
    <l>Who of the first barefooted beggars were</l>
    <l>That with the cord the friends of God became.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hugh of Saint Victor is among them here,</l>
    <l>And Peter Mangiador, and Peter of Spain,</l>
    <l>Who down below in volumes twelve is shining;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nathan the seer, and metropolitan</l>
    <l>Chrysostom, and Anselmus, and Donatus</l>
    <l>Who deigned to lay his hand to the first art;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here is Rabanus, and beside me here</l>
    <l>Shines the Calabrian Abbot Joachim,</l>
    <l>He with the spirit of prophecy endowed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To celebrate so great a paladin</l>
    <l>Have moved me the impassioned courtesy</l>
    <l>And the discreet discourses of Friar Thomas,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And with me they have moved this company.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>