<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Let him imagine, who would well conceive</l>
    <l>What now I saw, and let him while I speak</l>
    <l>Retain the image as a steadfast rock,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The fifteen stars, that in their divers regions</l>
    <l>The sky enliven with a light so great</l>
    <l>That it transcends all clusters of the air;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Let him the Wain imagine unto which</l>
    <l>Our vault of heaven sufficeth night and day,</l>
    <l>So that in turning of its pole it fails not;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Let him the mouth imagine of the horn</l>
    <l>That in the point beginneth of the axis</l>
    <l>Round about which the primal wheel revolves,--</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To have fashioned of themselves two signs in heaven,</l>
    <l>Like unto that which Minos' daughter made,</l>
    <l>The moment when she felt the frost of death;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one to have its rays within the other,</l>
    <l>And both to whirl themselves in such a manner</l>
    <l>That one should forward go, the other backward;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And he will have some shadowing forth of that</l>
    <l>True constellation and the double dance</l>
    <l>That circled round the point at which I was;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because it is as much beyond our wont,</l>
    <l>As swifter than the motion of the Chiana</l>
    <l>Moveth the heaven that all the rest outspeeds.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There sang they neither Bacchus, nor Apollo,</l>
    <l>But in the divine nature Persons three,</l>
    <l>And in one person the divine and human.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The singing and the dance fulfilled their measure,</l>
    <l>And unto us those holy lights gave need,</l>
    <l>Growing in happiness from care to care.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then broke the silence of those saints concordant</l>
    <l>The light in which the admirable life</l>
    <l>Of God's own mendicant was told to me,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And said: &quot;Now that one straw is trodden out</l>
    <l>Now that its seed is garnered up already,</l>
    <l>Sweet love invites me to thresh out the other.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Into that bosom, thou believest, whence</l>
    <l>Was drawn the rib to form the beauteous cheek</l>
    <l>Whose taste to all the world is costing dear,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And into that which, by the lance transfixed,</l>
    <l>Before and since, such satisfaction made</l>
    <l>That it weighs down the balance of all sin,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whate'er of light it has to human nature</l>
    <l>Been lawful to possess was all infused</l>
    <l>By the same power that both of them created;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And hence at what I said above dost wonder,</l>
    <l>When I narrated that no second had</l>
    <l>The good which in the fifth light is enclosed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now ope thine eyes to what I answer thee,</l>
    <l>And thou shalt see thy creed and my discourse</l>
    <l>Fit in the truth as centre in a circle.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That which can die, and that which dieth not,</l>
    <l>Are nothing but the splendour of the idea</l>
    <l>Which by his love our Lord brings into being;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because that living Light, which from its fount</l>
    <l>Effulgent flows, so that it disunites not</l>
    <l>From Him nor from the Love in them intrined,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Through its own goodness reunites its rays</l>
    <l>In nine subsistences, as in a mirror,</l>
    <l>Itself eternally remaining One.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thence it descends to the last potencies,</l>
    <l>Downward from act to act becoming such</l>
    <l>That only brief contingencies it makes;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And these contingencies I hold to be</l>
    <l>Things generated, which the heaven produces</l>
    <l>By its own motion, with seed and without.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Neither their wax, nor that which tempers it,</l>
    <l>Remains immutable, and hence beneath</l>
    <l>The ideal signet more and less shines through;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore it happens, that the selfsame tree</l>
    <l>After its kind bears worse and better fruit,</l>
    <l>And ye are born with characters diverse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If in perfection tempered were the wax,</l>
    <l>And were the heaven in its supremest virtue,</l>
    <l>The brilliance of the seal would all appear;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But nature gives it evermore deficient,</l>
    <l>In the like manner working as the artist,</l>
    <l>Who has the skill of art and hand that trembles.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If then the fervent Love, the Vision clear,</l>
    <l>Of primal Virtue do dispose and seal,</l>
    <l>Perfection absolute is there acquired.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus was of old the earth created worthy</l>
    <l>Of all and every animal perfection;</l>
    <l>And thus the Virgin was impregnate made;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that thine own opinion I commend,</l>
    <l>That human nature never yet has been,</l>
    <l>Nor will be, what it was in those two persons.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now if no farther forth I should proceed,</l>
    <l>'Then in what way was he without a peer?'</l>
    <l>Would be the first beginning of thy words.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But, that may well appear what now appears not,</l>
    <l>Think who he was, and what occasion moved him</l>
    <l>To make request, when it was told him, 'Ask.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I've not so spoken that thou canst not see</l>
    <l>Clearly he was a king who asked for wisdom,</l>
    <l>That he might be sufficiently a king;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Twas not to know the number in which are</l>
    <l>The motors here above, or if 'necesse'</l>
    <l>With a contingent e'er 'necesse' make,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Non si est dare primum motum esse,'</l>
    <l>Or if in semicircle can be made</l>
    <l>Triangle so that it have no right angle.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence, if thou notest this and what I said,</l>
    <l>A regal prudence is that peerless seeing</l>
    <l>In which the shaft of my intention strikes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if on 'rose' thou turnest thy clear eyes,</l>
    <l>Thou'lt see that it has reference alone</l>
    <l>To kings who're many, and the good are rare.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With this distinction take thou what I said,</l>
    <l>And thus it can consist with thy belief</l>
    <l>Of the first father and of our Delight.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And lead shall this be always to thy feet,</l>
    <l>To make thee, like a weary man, move slowly</l>
    <l>Both to the Yes and No thou seest not;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For very low among the fools is he</l>
    <l>Who affirms without distinction, or denies,</l>
    <l>As well in one as in the other case;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because it happens that full often bends</l>
    <l>Current opinion in the false direction,</l>
    <l>And then the feelings bind the intellect.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Far more than uselessly he leaves the shore,</l>
    <l>(Since he returneth not the same he went,)</l>
    <l>Who fishes for the truth, and has no skill;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in the world proofs manifest thereof</l>
    <l>Parmenides, Melissus, Brissus are,</l>
    <l>And many who went on and knew not whither;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus did Sabellius, Arius, and those fools</l>
    <l>Who have been even as swords unto the Scriptures</l>
    <l>In rendering distorted their straight faces.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor yet shall people be too confident</l>
    <l>In judging, even as he is who doth count</l>
    <l>The corn in field or ever it be ripe.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For I have seen all winter long the thorn</l>
    <l>First show itself intractable and fierce,</l>
    <l>And after bear the rose upon its top;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I have seen a ship direct and swift</l>
    <l>Run o'er the sea throughout its course entire,</l>
    <l>To perish at the harbour's mouth at last.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Let not Dame Bertha nor Ser Martin think,</l>
    <l>Seeing one steal, another offering make,</l>
    <l>To see them in the arbitrament divine;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For one may rise, and fall the other may.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>