<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>If e'er it happen that the Poem Sacred,</l>
    <l>To which both heaven and earth have set their hand,</l>
    <l>So that it many a year hath made me lean,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O'ercome the cruelty that bars me out</l>
    <l>From the fair sheepfold, where a lamb I slumbered,</l>
    <l>An enemy to the wolves that war upon it,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With other voice forthwith, with other fleece</l>
    <l>Poet will I return, and at my font</l>
    <l>Baptismal will I take the laurel crown;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because into the Faith that maketh known</l>
    <l>All souls to God there entered I, and then</l>
    <l>Peter for her sake thus my brow encircled.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafterward towards us moved a light</l>
    <l>Out of that band whence issued the first-fruits</l>
    <l>Which of his vicars Christ behind him left,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And then my Lady, full of ecstasy,</l>
    <l>Said unto me: &quot;Look, look! behold the Baron</l>
    <l>For whom below Galicia is frequented.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In the same way as, when a dove alights</l>
    <l>Near his companion, both of them pour forth,</l>
    <l>Circling about and murmuring, their affection,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So one beheld I by the other grand</l>
    <l>Prince glorified to be with welcome greeted,</l>
    <l>Lauding the food that there above is eaten.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But when their gratulations were complete,</l>
    <l>Silently 'coram me' each one stood still,</l>
    <l>So incandescent it o'ercame my sight.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Smiling thereafterwards, said Beatrice:</l>
    <l>&quot;Illustrious life, by whom the benefactions</l>
    <l>Of our Basilica have been described,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Make Hope resound within this altitude;</l>
    <l>Thou knowest as oft thou dost personify it</l>
    <l>As Jesus to the three gave greater clearness.&quot;--</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Lift up thy head, and make thyself assured;</l>
    <l>For what comes hither from the mortal world</l>
    <l>Must needs be ripened in our radiance.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This comfort came to me from the second fire;</l>
    <l>Wherefore mine eyes I lifted to the hills,</l>
    <l>Which bent them down before with too great weight.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Since, through his grace, our Emperor wills that thou</l>
    <l>Shouldst find thee face to face, before thy death,</l>
    <l>In the most secret chamber, with his Counts,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that, the truth beholden of this court,</l>
    <l>Hope, which below there rightfully enamours,</l>
    <l>Thereby thou strengthen in thyself and others,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Say what it is, and how is flowering with it</l>
    <l>Thy mind, and say from whence it came to thee.&quot;</l>
    <l>Thus did the second light again continue.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And the Compassionate, who piloted</l>
    <l>The plumage of my wings in such high flight,</l>
    <l>Did in reply anticipate me thus:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;No child whatever the Church Militant</l>
    <l>Of greater hope possesses, as is written</l>
    <l>In that Sun which irradiates all our band;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore it is conceded him from Egypt</l>
    <l>To come into Jerusalem to see,</l>
    <l>Or ever yet his warfare be completed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The two remaining points, that not for knowledge</l>
    <l>Have been demanded, but that he report</l>
    <l>How much this virtue unto thee is pleasing,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To him I leave; for hard he will not find them,</l>
    <l>Nor of self-praise; and let him answer them;</l>
    <l>And may the grace of God in this assist him!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As a disciple, who his teacher follows,</l>
    <l>Ready and willing, where he is expert,</l>
    <l>That his proficiency may be displayed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Hope,&quot; said I, &quot;is the certain expectation</l>
    <l>Of future glory, which is the effect</l>
    <l>Of grace divine and merit precedent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From many stars this light comes unto me;</l>
    <l>But he instilled it first into my heart</l>
    <l>Who was chief singer unto the chief captain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Sperent in te,' in the high Theody</l>
    <l>He sayeth, 'those who know thy name;' and who</l>
    <l>Knoweth it not, if he my faith possess?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou didst instil me, then, with his instilling</l>
    <l>In the Epistle, so that I am full,</l>
    <l>And upon others rain again your rain.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>While I was speaking, in the living bosom</l>
    <l>Of that combustion quivered an effulgence,</l>
    <l>Sudden and frequent, in the guise of lightning;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then breathed: &quot;The love wherewith I am inflamed</l>
    <l>Towards the virtue still which followed me</l>
    <l>Unto the palm and issue of the field,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wills that I breathe to thee that thou delight</l>
    <l>In her; and grateful to me is thy telling</l>
    <l>Whatever things Hope promises to thee.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;The ancient Scriptures and the new</l>
    <l>The mark establish, and this shows it me,</l>
    <l>Of all the souls whom God hath made his friends.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Isaiah saith, that each one garmented</l>
    <l>In his own land shall be with twofold garments,</l>
    <l>And his own land is this delightful life.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thy brother, too, far more explicitly,</l>
    <l>There where he treateth of the robes of white,</l>
    <l>This revelation manifests to us.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And first, and near the ending of these words,</l>
    <l>&quot;Sperent in te&quot; from over us was heard,</l>
    <l>To which responsive answered all the carols.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafterward a light among them brightened,</l>
    <l>So that, if Cancer one such crystal had,</l>
    <l>Winter would have a month of one sole day.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as uprises, goes, and enters the dance</l>
    <l>A winsome maiden, only to do honour</l>
    <l>To the new bride, and not from any failing,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even thus did I behold the brightened splendour</l>
    <l>Approach the two, who in a wheel revolved</l>
    <l>As was beseeming to their ardent love.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Into the song and music there it entered;</l>
    <l>And fixed on them my Lady kept her look,</l>
    <l>Even as a bride silent and motionless.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;This is the one who lay upon the breast</l>
    <l>Of him our Pelican; and this is he</l>
    <l>To the great office from the cross elected.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Lady thus; but therefore none the more</l>
    <l>Did move her sight from its attentive gaze</l>
    <l>Before or afterward these words of hers.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as a man who gazes, and endeavours</l>
    <l>To see the eclipsing of the sun a little,</l>
    <l>And who, by seeing, sightless doth become,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So I became before that latest fire,</l>
    <l>While it was said, &quot;Why dost thou daze thyself</l>
    <l>To see a thing which here hath no existence?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Earth in the earth my body is, and shall be</l>
    <l>With all the others there, until our number</l>
    <l>With the eternal proposition tallies.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With the two garments in the blessed cloister</l>
    <l>Are the two lights alone that have ascended:</l>
    <l>And this shalt thou take back into your world.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And at this utterance the flaming circle</l>
    <l>Grew quiet, with the dulcet intermingling</l>
    <l>Of sound that by the trinal breath was made,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As to escape from danger or fatigue</l>
    <l>The oars that erst were in the water beaten</l>
    <l>Are all suspended at a whistle's sound.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ah, how much in my mind was I disturbed,</l>
    <l>When I turned round to look on Beatrice,</l>
    <l>That her I could not see, although I was</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Close at her side and in the Happy World!</l>
  </p>
</page>