<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>The world used in its peril to believe</l>
    <l>That the fair Cypria delirious love</l>
    <l>Rayed out, in the third epicycle turning;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wherefore not only unto her paid honour</l>
    <l>Of sacrifices and of votive cry</l>
    <l>The ancient nations in the ancient error,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But both Dione honoured they and Cupid,</l>
    <l>That as her mother, this one as her son,</l>
    <l>And said that he had sat in Dido's lap;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And they from her, whence I beginning take,</l>
    <l>Took the denomination of the star</l>
    <l>That woos the sun, now following, now in front.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I was not ware of our ascending to it;</l>
    <l>But of our being in it gave full faith</l>
    <l>My Lady whom I saw more beauteous grow.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as within a flame a spark is seen,</l>
    <l>And as within a voice a voice discerned,</l>
    <l>When one is steadfast, and one comes and goes,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Within that light beheld I other lamps</l>
    <l>Move in a circle, speeding more and less,</l>
    <l>Methinks in measure of their inward vision.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From a cold cloud descended never winds,</l>
    <l>Or visible or not, so rapidly</l>
    <l>They would not laggard and impeded seem</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To any one who had those lights divine</l>
    <l>Seen come towards us, leaving the gyration</l>
    <l>Begun at first in the high Seraphim.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And behind those that most in front appeared</l>
    <l>Sounded &quot;Osanna!&quot; so that never since</l>
    <l>To hear again was I without desire.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then unto us more nearly one approached,</l>
    <l>And it alone began: &quot;We all are ready</l>
    <l>Unto thy pleasure, that thou joy in us.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>We turn around with the celestial Princes,</l>
    <l>One gyre and one gyration and one thirst,</l>
    <l>To whom thou in the world of old didst say,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Ye who, intelligent, the third heaven are moving;'</l>
    <l>And are so full of love, to pleasure thee</l>
    <l>A little quiet will not be less sweet.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After these eyes of mine themselves had offered</l>
    <l>Unto my Lady reverently, and she</l>
    <l>Content and certain of herself had made them,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Back to the light they turned, which so great promise</l>
    <l>Made of itself, and &quot;Say, who art thou?&quot; was</l>
    <l>My voice, imprinted with a great affection.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O how and how much I beheld it grow</l>
    <l>With the new joy that superadded was</l>
    <l>Unto its joys, as soon as I had spoken!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus changed, it said to me: &quot;The world possessed me</l>
    <l>Short time below; and, if it had been more,</l>
    <l>Much evil will be which would not have been.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My gladness keepeth me concealed from thee,</l>
    <l>Which rayeth round about me, and doth hide me</l>
    <l>Like as a creature swathed in its own silk.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Much didst thou love me, and thou hadst good reason;</l>
    <l>For had I been below, I should have shown thee</l>
    <l>Somewhat beyond the foliage of my love.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That left-hand margin, which doth bathe itself</l>
    <l>In Rhone, when it is mingled with the Sorgue,</l>
    <l>Me for its lord awaited in due time,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And that horn of Ausonia, which is towned</l>
    <l>With Bari, with Gaeta and Catona,</l>
    <l>Whence Tronto and Verde in the sea disgorge.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Already flashed upon my brow the crown</l>
    <l>Of that dominion which the Danube waters</l>
    <l>After the German borders it abandons;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And beautiful Trinacria, that is murky</l>
    <l>'Twixt Pachino and Peloro, (on the gulf</l>
    <l>Which greatest scath from Eurus doth receive,)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not through Typhoeus, but through nascent sulphur,</l>
    <l>Would have awaited her own monarchs still,</l>
    <l>Through me from Charles descended and from Rudolph,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If evil lordship, that exasperates ever</l>
    <l>The subject populations, had not moved</l>
    <l>Palermo to the outcry of 'Death! death!'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if my brother could but this foresee,</l>
    <l>The greedy poverty of Catalonia</l>
    <l>Straight would he flee, that it might not molest him;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For verily 'tis needful to provide,</l>
    <l>Through him or other, so that on his bark</l>
    <l>Already freighted no more freight be placed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>His nature, which from liberal covetous</l>
    <l>Descended, such a soldiery would need</l>
    <l>As should not care for hoarding in a chest.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Because I do believe the lofty joy</l>
    <l>Thy speech infuses into me, my Lord,</l>
    <l>Where every good thing doth begin and end</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou seest as I see it, the more grateful</l>
    <l>Is it to me; and this too hold I dear,</l>
    <l>That gazing upon God thou dost discern it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Glad hast thou made me; so make clear to me,</l>
    <l>Since speaking thou hast stirred me up to doubt,</l>
    <l>How from sweet seed can bitter issue forth.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This I to him; and he to me: &quot;If I</l>
    <l>Can show to thee a truth, to what thou askest</l>
    <l>Thy face thou'lt hold as thou dost hold thy back.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Good which all the realm thou art ascending</l>
    <l>Turns and contents, maketh its providence</l>
    <l>To be a power within these bodies vast;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And not alone the natures are foreseen</l>
    <l>Within the mind that in itself is perfect,</l>
    <l>But they together with their preservation.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For whatsoever thing this bow shoots forth</l>
    <l>Falls foreordained unto an end foreseen,</l>
    <l>Even as a shaft directed to its mark.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If that were not, the heaven which thou dost walk</l>
    <l>Would in such manner its effects produce,</l>
    <l>That they no longer would be arts, but ruins.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This cannot be, if the Intelligences</l>
    <l>That keep these stars in motion are not maimed,</l>
    <l>And maimed the First that has not made them perfect.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Wilt thou this truth have clearer made to thee?&quot;</l>
    <l>And I: &quot;Not so; for 'tis impossible</l>
    <l>That nature tire, I see, in what is needful.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence he again: &quot;Now say, would it be worse</l>
    <l>For men on earth were they not citizens?&quot;</l>
    <l>&quot;Yes,&quot; I replied; &quot;and here I ask no reason.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;And can they be so, if below they live not</l>
    <l>Diversely unto offices diverse?</l>
    <l>No, if your master writeth well for you.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So came he with deductions to this point;</l>
    <l>Then he concluded: &quot;Therefore it behoves</l>
    <l>The roots of your effects to be diverse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Hence one is Solon born, another Xerxes,</l>
    <l>Another Melchisedec, and another he</l>
    <l>Who, flying through the air, his son did lose.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Revolving Nature, which a signet is</l>
    <l>To mortal wax, doth practise well her art,</l>
    <l>But not one inn distinguish from another;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thence happens it that Esau differeth</l>
    <l>In seed from Jacob; and Quirinus comes</l>
    <l>From sire so vile that he is given to Mars.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A generated nature its own way</l>
    <l>Would always make like its progenitors,</l>
    <l>If Providence divine were not triumphant.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now that which was behind thee is before thee;</l>
    <l>But that thou know that I with thee am pleased,</l>
    <l>With a corollary will I mantle thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Evermore nature, if it fortune find</l>
    <l>Discordant to it, like each other seed</l>
    <l>Out of its region, maketh evil thrift;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if the world below would fix its mind</l>
    <l>On the foundation which is laid by nature,</l>
    <l>Pursuing that, 'twould have the people good.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But you unto religion wrench aside</l>
    <l>Him who was born to gird him with the sword,</l>
    <l>And make a king of him who is for sermons;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore your footsteps wander from the road.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>