<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>O Ye, who in some pretty little boat,</l>
    <l>Eager to listen, have been following</l>
    <l>Behind my ship, that singing sails along,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Turn back to look again upon your shores;</l>
    <l>Do not put out to sea, lest peradventure,</l>
    <l>In losing me, you might yourselves be lost.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The sea I sail has never yet been passed;</l>
    <l>Minerva breathes, and pilots me Apollo,</l>
    <l>And Muses nine point out to me the Bears.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ye other few who have the neck uplifted</l>
    <l>Betimes to th' bread of Angels upon which</l>
    <l>One liveth here and grows not sated by it,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well may you launch upon the deep salt-sea</l>
    <l>Your vessel, keeping still my wake before you</l>
    <l>Upon the water that grows smooth again.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Those glorious ones who unto Colchos passed</l>
    <l>Were not so wonder-struck as you shall be,</l>
    <l>When Jason they beheld a ploughman made!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The con-created and perpetual thirst</l>
    <l>For the realm deiform did bear us on,</l>
    <l>As swift almost as ye the heavens behold.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Upward gazed Beatrice, and I at her;</l>
    <l>And in such space perchance as strikes a bolt</l>
    <l>And flies, and from the notch unlocks itself,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Arrived I saw me where a wondrous thing</l>
    <l>Drew to itself my sight; and therefore she</l>
    <l>From whom no care of mine could be concealed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Towards me turning, blithe as beautiful,</l>
    <l>Said unto me: &quot;Fix gratefully thy mind</l>
    <l>On God, who unto the first star has brought us.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>It seemed to me a cloud encompassed us,</l>
    <l>Luminous, dense, consolidate and bright</l>
    <l>As adamant on which the sun is striking.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Into itself did the eternal pearl</l>
    <l>Receive us, even as water doth receive</l>
    <l>A ray of light, remaining still unbroken.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If I was body, (and we here conceive not</l>
    <l>How one dimension tolerates another,</l>
    <l>Which needs must be if body enter body,)</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>More the desire should be enkindled in us</l>
    <l>That essence to behold, wherein is seen</l>
    <l>How God and our own nature were united.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There will be seen what we receive by faith,</l>
    <l>Not demonstrated, but self-evident</l>
    <l>In guise of the first truth that man believes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I made reply: &quot;Madonna, as devoutly</l>
    <l>As most I can do I give thanks to Him</l>
    <l>Who has removed me from the mortal world.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me what the dusky spots may be</l>
    <l>Upon this body, which below on earth</l>
    <l>Make people tell that fabulous tale of Cain?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Somewhat she smiled; and then, &quot;If the opinion</l>
    <l>Of mortals be erroneous,&quot; she said,</l>
    <l>&quot;Where'er the key of sense doth not unlock,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Certes, the shafts of wonder should not pierce thee</l>
    <l>Now, forasmuch as, following the senses,</l>
    <l>Thou seest that the reason has short wings.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me what thou think'st of it thyself.&quot;</l>
    <l>And I: &quot;What seems to us up here diverse,</l>
    <l>Is caused, I think, by bodies rare and dense.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And she: &quot;Right truly shalt thou see immersed</l>
    <l>In error thy belief, if well thou hearest</l>
    <l>The argument that I shall make against it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Lights many the eighth sphere displays to you</l>
    <l>Which in their quality and quantity</l>
    <l>May noted be of aspects different.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If this were caused by rare and dense alone,</l>
    <l>One only virtue would there be in all</l>
    <l>Or more or less diffused, or equally.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Virtues diverse must be perforce the fruits</l>
    <l>Of formal principles; and these, save one,</l>
    <l>Of course would by thy reasoning be destroyed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Besides, if rarity were of this dimness</l>
    <l>The cause thou askest, either through and through</l>
    <l>This planet thus attenuate were of matter,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Or else, as in a body is apportioned</l>
    <l>The fat and lean, so in like manner this</l>
    <l>Would in its volume interchange the leaves.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Were it the former, in the sun's eclipse</l>
    <l>It would be manifest by the shining through</l>
    <l>Of light, as through aught tenuous interfused.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This is not so; hence we must scan the other,</l>
    <l>And if it chance the other I demolish,</l>
    <l>Then falsified will thy opinion be.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But if this rarity go not through and through,</l>
    <l>There needs must be a limit, beyond which</l>
    <l>Its contrary prevents the further passing,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And thence the foreign radiance is reflected,</l>
    <l>Even as a colour cometh back from glass,</l>
    <l>The which behind itself concealeth lead.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now thou wilt say the sunbeam shows itself</l>
    <l>More dimly there than in the other parts,</l>
    <l>By being there reflected farther back.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From this reply experiment will free thee</l>
    <l>If e'er thou try it, which is wont to be</l>
    <l>The fountain to the rivers of your arts.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Three mirrors shalt thou take, and two remove</l>
    <l>Alike from thee, the other more remote</l>
    <l>Between the former two shall meet thine eyes.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Turned towards these, cause that behind thy back</l>
    <l>Be placed a light, illuming the three mirrors</l>
    <l>And coming back to thee by all reflected.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Though in its quantity be not so ample</l>
    <l>The image most remote, there shalt thou see</l>
    <l>How it perforce is equally resplendent.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now, as beneath the touches of warm rays</l>
    <l>Naked the subject of the snow remains</l>
    <l>Both of its former colour and its cold,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thee thus remaining in thy intellect,</l>
    <l>Will I inform with such a living light,</l>
    <l>That it shall tremble in its aspect to thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Within the heaven of the divine repose</l>
    <l>Revolves a body, in whose virtue lies</l>
    <l>The being of whatever it contains.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The following heaven, that has so many eyes,</l>
    <l>Divides this being by essences diverse,</l>
    <l>Distinguished from it, and by it contained.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other spheres, by various differences,</l>
    <l>All the distinctions which they have within them</l>
    <l>Dispose unto their ends and their effects.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus do these organs of the world proceed,</l>
    <l>As thou perceivest now, from grade to grade;</l>
    <l>Since from above they take, and act beneath.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Observe me well, how through this place I come</l>
    <l>Unto the truth thou wishest, that hereafter</l>
    <l>Thou mayst alone know how to keep the ford</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The power and motion of the holy spheres,</l>
    <l>As from the artisan the hammer's craft,</l>
    <l>Forth from the blessed motors must proceed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The heaven, which lights so manifold make fair,</l>
    <l>From the Intelligence profound, which turns it,</l>
    <l>The image takes, and makes of it a seal.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as the soul within your dust</l>
    <l>Through members different and accommodated</l>
    <l>To faculties diverse expands itself,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So likewise this Intelligence diffuses</l>
    <l>Its virtue multiplied among the stars.</l>
    <l>Itself revolving on its unity.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Virtue diverse doth a diverse alloyage</l>
    <l>Make with the precious body that it quickens,</l>
    <l>In which, as life in you, it is combined.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From the glad nature whence it is derived,</l>
    <l>The mingled virtue through the body shines,</l>
    <l>Even as gladness through the living pupil.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From this proceeds whate'er from light to light</l>
    <l>Appeareth different, not from dense and rare:</l>
    <l>This is the formal principle that produces,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>According to its goodness, dark and bright.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>