<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Perchance six thousand miles remote from us</l>
    <l>Is glowing the sixth hour, and now this world</l>
    <l>Inclines its shadow almost to a level,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When the mid-heaven begins to make itself</l>
    <l>So deep to us, that here and there a star</l>
    <l>Ceases to shine so far down as this depth,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as advances bright exceedingly</l>
    <l>The handmaid of the sun, the heaven is closed</l>
    <l>Light after light to the most beautiful;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not otherwise the Triumph, which for ever</l>
    <l>Plays round about the point that vanquished me,</l>
    <l>Seeming enclosed by what itself encloses,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Little by little from my vision faded;</l>
    <l>Whereat to turn mine eyes on Beatrice</l>
    <l>My seeing nothing and my love constrained me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If what has hitherto been said of her</l>
    <l>Were all concluded in a single praise,</l>
    <l>Scant would it be to serve the present turn.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not only does the beauty I beheld</l>
    <l>Transcend ourselves, but truly I believe</l>
    <l>Its Maker only may enjoy it all.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Vanquished do I confess me by this passage</l>
    <l>More than by problem of his theme was ever</l>
    <l>O'ercome the comic or the tragic poet;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For as the sun the sight that trembles most,</l>
    <l>Even so the memory of that sweet smile</l>
    <l>My mind depriveth of its very self.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From the first day that I beheld her face</l>
    <l>In this life, to the moment of this look,</l>
    <l>The sequence of my song has ne'er been severed;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But now perforce this sequence must desist</l>
    <l>From following her beauty with my verse,</l>
    <l>As every artist at his uttermost.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Such as I leave her to a greater fame</l>
    <l>Than any of my trumpet, which is bringing</l>
    <l>Its arduous matter to a final close,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With voice and gesture of a perfect leader</l>
    <l>She recommenced: &quot;We from the greatest body</l>
    <l>Have issued to the heaven that is pure light;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Light intellectual replete with love,</l>
    <l>Love of true good replete with ecstasy,</l>
    <l>Ecstasy that transcendeth every sweetness.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Here shalt thou see the one host and the other</l>
    <l>Of Paradise, and one in the same aspects</l>
    <l>Which at the final judgment thou shalt see.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as a sudden lightning that disperses</l>
    <l>The visual spirits, so that it deprives</l>
    <l>The eye of impress from the strongest objects,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus round about me flashed a living light,</l>
    <l>And left me swathed around with such a veil</l>
    <l>Of its effulgence, that I nothing saw.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Ever the Love which quieteth this heaven</l>
    <l>Welcomes into itself with such salute,</l>
    <l>To make the candle ready for its flame.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>No sooner had within me these brief words</l>
    <l>An entrance found, than I perceived myself</l>
    <l>To be uplifted over my own power,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I with vision new rekindled me,</l>
    <l>Such that no light whatever is so pure</l>
    <l>But that mine eyes were fortified against it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And light I saw in fashion of a river</l>
    <l>Fulvid with its effulgence, 'twixt two banks</l>
    <l>Depicted with an admirable Spring.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Out of this river issued living sparks,</l>
    <l>And on all sides sank down into the flowers,</l>
    <l>Like unto rubies that are set in gold;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And then, as if inebriate with the odours,</l>
    <l>They plunged again into the wondrous torrent,</l>
    <l>And as one entered issued forth another.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;The high desire, that now inflames and moves thee</l>
    <l>To have intelligence of what thou seest,</l>
    <l>Pleaseth me all the more, the more it swells.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But of this water it behoves thee drink</l>
    <l>Before so great a thirst in thee be slaked.&quot;</l>
    <l>Thus said to me the sunshine of mine eyes;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And added: &quot;The river and the topazes</l>
    <l>Going in and out, and the laughing of the herbage,</l>
    <l>Are of their truth foreshadowing prefaces;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not that these things are difficult in themselves,</l>
    <l>But the deficiency is on thy side,</l>
    <l>For yet thou hast not vision so exalted.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There is no babe that leaps so suddenly</l>
    <l>With face towards the milk, if he awake</l>
    <l>Much later than his usual custom is,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As I did, that I might make better mirrors</l>
    <l>Still of mine eyes, down stooping to the wave</l>
    <l>Which flows that we therein be better made.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And even as the penthouse of mine eyelids</l>
    <l>Drank of it, it forthwith appeared to me</l>
    <l>Out of its length to be transformed to round.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then as a folk who have been under masks</l>
    <l>Seem other than before, if they divest</l>
    <l>The semblance not their own they disappeared in,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus into greater pomp were changed for me</l>
    <l>The flowerets and the sparks, so that I saw</l>
    <l>Both of the Courts of Heaven made manifest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O splendour of God! by means of which I saw</l>
    <l>The lofty triumph of the realm veracious,</l>
    <l>Give me the power to say how it I saw!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There is a light above, which visible</l>
    <l>Makes the Creator unto every creature,</l>
    <l>Who only in beholding Him has peace,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And it expands itself in circular form</l>
    <l>To such extent, that its circumference</l>
    <l>Would be too large a girdle for the sun.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The semblance of it is all made of rays</l>
    <l>Reflected from the top of Primal Motion,</l>
    <l>Which takes therefrom vitality and power.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as a hill in water at its base</l>
    <l>Mirrors itself, as if to see its beauty</l>
    <l>When affluent most in verdure and in flowers,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So, ranged aloft all round about the light,</l>
    <l>Mirrored I saw in more ranks than a thousand</l>
    <l>All who above there have from us returned.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if the lowest row collect within it</l>
    <l>So great a light, how vast the amplitude</l>
    <l>Is of this Rose in its extremest leaves!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My vision in the vastness and the height</l>
    <l>Lost not itself, but comprehended all</l>
    <l>The quantity and quality of that gladness.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There near and far nor add nor take away;</l>
    <l>For there where God immediately doth govern,</l>
    <l>The natural law in naught is relevant.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Into the yellow of the Rose Eternal</l>
    <l>That spreads, and multiplies, and breathes an odour</l>
    <l>Of praise unto the ever-vernal Sun,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As one who silent is and fain would speak,</l>
    <l>Me Beatrice drew on, and said: &quot;Behold</l>
    <l>Of the white stoles how vast the convent is!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behold how vast the circuit of our city!</l>
    <l>Behold our seats so filled to overflowing,</l>
    <l>That here henceforward are few people wanting!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>On that great throne whereon thine eyes are fixed</l>
    <l>For the crown's sake already placed upon it,</l>
    <l>Before thou suppest at this wedding feast</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Shall sit the soul (that is to be Augustus</l>
    <l>On earth) of noble Henry, who shall come</l>
    <l>To redress Italy ere she be ready.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Blind covetousness, that casts its spell upon you,</l>
    <l>Has made you like unto the little child,</l>
    <l>Who dies of hunger and drives off the nurse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in the sacred forum then shall be</l>
    <l>A Prefect such, that openly or covert</l>
    <l>On the same road he will not walk with him.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But long of God he will not be endured</l>
    <l>In holy office; he shall be thrust down</l>
    <l>Where Simon Magus is for his deserts,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And make him of Alagna lower go!&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>