<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;If in the heat of love I flame upon thee</l>
    <l>Beyond the measure that on earth is seen,</l>
    <l>So that the valour of thine eyes I vanquish,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Marvel thou not thereat; for this proceeds</l>
    <l>From perfect sight, which as it apprehends</l>
    <l>To the good apprehended moves its feet.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Well I perceive how is already shining</l>
    <l>Into thine intellect the eternal light,</l>
    <l>That only seen enkindles always love;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if some other thing your love seduce,</l>
    <l>'Tis nothing but a vestige of the same,</l>
    <l>Ill understood, which there is shining through.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou fain wouldst know if with another service</l>
    <l>For broken vow can such return be made</l>
    <l>As to secure the soul from further claim.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This Canto thus did Beatrice begin;</l>
    <l>And, as a man who breaks not off his speech,</l>
    <l>Continued thus her holy argument:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;The greatest gift that in his largess God</l>
    <l>Creating made, and unto his own goodness</l>
    <l>Nearest conformed, and that which he doth prize</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Most highly, is the freedom of the will,</l>
    <l>Wherewith the creatures of intelligence</l>
    <l>Both all and only were and are endowed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now wilt thou see, if thence thou reasonest,</l>
    <l>The high worth of a vow, if it he made</l>
    <l>So that when thou consentest God consents:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For, closing between God and man the compact,</l>
    <l>A sacrifice is of this treasure made,</l>
    <l>Such as I say, and made by its own act.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>What can be rendered then as compensation?</l>
    <l>Think'st thou to make good use of what thou'st offered,</l>
    <l>With gains ill gotten thou wouldst do good deed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now art thou certain of the greater point;</l>
    <l>But because Holy Church in this dispenses,</l>
    <l>Which seems against the truth which I have shown thee,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Behoves thee still to sit awhile at table,</l>
    <l>Because the solid food which thou hast taken</l>
    <l>Requireth further aid for thy digestion.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Open thy mind to that which I reveal,</l>
    <l>And fix it there within; for 'tis not knowledge,</l>
    <l>The having heard without retaining it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In the essence of this sacrifice two things</l>
    <l>Convene together; and the one is that</l>
    <l>Of which 'tis made, the other is the agreement.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This last for evermore is cancelled not</l>
    <l>Unless complied with, and concerning this</l>
    <l>With such precision has above been spoken.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore it was enjoined upon the Hebrews</l>
    <l>To offer still, though sometimes what was offered</l>
    <l>Might be commuted, as thou ought'st to know.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The other, which is known to thee as matter,</l>
    <l>May well indeed be such that one errs not</l>
    <l>If it for other matter be exchanged.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But let none shift the burden on his shoulder</l>
    <l>At his arbitrament, without the turning</l>
    <l>Both of the white and of the yellow key;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And every permutation deem as foolish,</l>
    <l>If in the substitute the thing relinquished,</l>
    <l>As the four is in six, be not contained.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore whatever thing has so great weight</l>
    <l>In value that it drags down every balance,</l>
    <l>Cannot be satisfied with other spending.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Let mortals never take a vow in jest;</l>
    <l>Be faithful and not blind in doing that,</l>
    <l>As Jephthah was in his first offering,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whom more beseemed to say, 'I have done wrong,</l>
    <l>Than to do worse by keeping; and as foolish</l>
    <l>Thou the great leader of the Greeks wilt find,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence wept Iphigenia her fair face,</l>
    <l>And made for her both wise and simple weep,</l>
    <l>Who heard such kind of worship spoken of.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Christians, be ye more serious in your movements;</l>
    <l>Be ye not like a feather at each wind,</l>
    <l>And think not every water washes you.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Ye have the Old and the New Testament,</l>
    <l>And the Pastor of the Church who guideth you</l>
    <l>Let this suffice you unto your salvation.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If evil appetite cry aught else to you,</l>
    <l>Be ye as men, and not as silly sheep,</l>
    <l>So that the Jew among you may not mock you.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Be ye not as the lamb that doth abandon</l>
    <l>Its mother's milk, and frolicsome and simple</l>
    <l>Combats at its own pleasure with itself.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus Beatrice to me even as I write it;</l>
    <l>Then all desireful turned herself again</l>
    <l>To that part where the world is most alive.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Her silence and her change of countenance</l>
    <l>Silence imposed upon my eager mind,</l>
    <l>That had already in advance new questions;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as an arrow that upon the mark</l>
    <l>Strikes ere the bowstring quiet hath become,</l>
    <l>So did we speed into the second realm.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>My Lady there so joyful I beheld,</l>
    <l>As into the brightness of that heaven she entered,</l>
    <l>More luminous thereat the planet grew;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And if the star itself was changed and smiled,</l>
    <l>What became I, who by my nature am</l>
    <l>Exceeding mutable in every guise!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As, in a fish-pond which is pure and tranquil,</l>
    <l>The fishes draw to that which from without</l>
    <l>Comes in such fashion that their food they deem it;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So I beheld more than a thousand splendours</l>
    <l>Drawing towards us, and in each was heard:</l>
    <l>&quot;Lo, this is she who shall increase our love.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as each one was coming unto us,</l>
    <l>Full of beatitude the shade was seen,</l>
    <l>By the effulgence clear that issued from it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Think, Reader, if what here is just beginning</l>
    <l>No farther should proceed, how thou wouldst have</l>
    <l>An agonizing need of knowing more;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And of thyself thou'lt see how I from these</l>
    <l>Was in desire of hearing their conditions,</l>
    <l>As they unto mine eyes were manifest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O thou well-born, unto whom Grace concedes</l>
    <l>To see the thrones of the eternal triumph,</l>
    <l>Or ever yet the warfare be abandoned</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With light that through the whole of heaven is spread</l>
    <l>Kindled are we, and hence if thou desirest</l>
    <l>To know of us, at thine own pleasure sate thee.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus by some one among those holy spirits</l>
    <l>Was spoken, and by Beatrice: &quot;Speak, speak</l>
    <l>Securely, and believe them even as Gods.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Well I perceive how thou dost nest thyself</l>
    <l>In thine own light, and drawest it from thine eyes,</l>
    <l>Because they coruscate when thou dost smile,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But know not who thou art, nor why thou hast,</l>
    <l>Spirit august, thy station in the sphere</l>
    <l>That veils itself to men in alien rays.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This said I in direction of the light</l>
    <l>Which first had spoken to me; whence it became</l>
    <l>By far more lucent than it was before.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as the sun, that doth conceal himself</l>
    <l>By too much light, when heat has worn away</l>
    <l>The tempering influence of the vapours dense,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>By greater rapture thus concealed itself</l>
    <l>In its own radiance the figure saintly,</l>
    <l>And thus close, close enfolded answered me</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In fashion as the following Canto sings.</l>
  </p>
</page>