<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O company elect to the great supper</l>
    <l>Of the Lamb benedight, who feedeth you</l>
    <l>So that for ever full is your desire,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If by the grace of God this man foretaste</l>
    <l>Something of that which falleth from your table,</l>
    <l>Or ever death prescribe to him the time,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Direct your mind to his immense desire,</l>
    <l>And him somewhat bedew; ye drinking are</l>
    <l>For ever at the fount whence comes his thought.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus Beatrice; and those souls beatified</l>
    <l>Transformed themselves to spheres on steadfast poles,</l>
    <l>Flaming intensely in the guise of comets.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as the wheels in works of horologes</l>
    <l>Revolve so that the first to the beholder</l>
    <l>Motionless seems, and the last one to fly,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So in like manner did those carols, dancing</l>
    <l>In different measure, of their affluence</l>
    <l>Give me the gauge, as they were swift or slow.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From that one which I noted of most beauty</l>
    <l>Beheld I issue forth a fire so happy</l>
    <l>That none it left there of a greater brightness;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And around Beatrice three several times</l>
    <l>It whirled itself with so divine a song,</l>
    <l>My fantasy repeats it not to me;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore the pen skips, and I write it not,</l>
    <l>Since our imagination for such folds,</l>
    <l>Much more our speech, is of a tint too glaring.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O holy sister mine, who us implorest</l>
    <l>With such devotion, by thine ardent love</l>
    <l>Thou dost unbind me from that beautiful sphere!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafter, having stopped, the blessed fire</l>
    <l>Unto my Lady did direct its breath,</l>
    <l>Which spake in fashion as I here have said.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And she: &quot;O light eterne of the great man</l>
    <l>To whom our Lord delivered up the keys</l>
    <l>He carried down of this miraculous joy,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This one examine on points light and grave,</l>
    <l>As good beseemeth thee, about the Faith</l>
    <l>By means of which thou on the sea didst walk.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If he love well, and hope well, and believe,</l>
    <l>From thee 'tis hid not; for thou hast thy sight</l>
    <l>There where depicted everything is seen.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But since this kingdom has made citizens</l>
    <l>By means of the true Faith, to glorify it</l>
    <l>'Tis well he have the chance to speak thereof.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As baccalaureate arms himself, and speaks not</l>
    <l>Until the master doth propose the question,</l>
    <l>To argue it, and not to terminate it,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So did I arm myself with every reason,</l>
    <l>While she was speaking, that I might be ready</l>
    <l>For such a questioner and such profession.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Say, thou good Christian; manifest thyself;</l>
    <l>What is the Faith?&quot;  Whereat I raised my brow</l>
    <l>Unto that light wherefrom was this breathed forth.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then turned I round to Beatrice, and she</l>
    <l>Prompt signals made to me that I should pour</l>
    <l>The water forth from my internal fountain.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;May grace, that suffers me to make confession,&quot;</l>
    <l>Began I, &quot;to the great centurion,</l>
    <l>Cause my conceptions all to be explicit!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I continued: &quot;As the truthful pen,</l>
    <l>Father, of thy dear brother wrote of it,</l>
    <l>Who put with thee Rome into the good way,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Faith is the substance of the things we hope for,</l>
    <l>And evidence of those that are not seen;</l>
    <l>And this appears to me its quiddity.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then heard I: &quot;Very rightly thou perceivest,</l>
    <l>If well thou understandest why he placed it</l>
    <l>With substances and then with evidences.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I thereafterward: &quot;The things profound,</l>
    <l>That here vouchsafe to me their apparition,</l>
    <l>Unto all eyes below are so concealed,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>That they exist there only in belief,</l>
    <l>Upon the which is founded the high hope,</l>
    <l>And hence it takes the nature of a substance.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And it behoveth us from this belief</l>
    <l>To reason without having other sight,</l>
    <l>And hence it has the nature of evidence.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then heard I: &quot;If whatever is acquired</l>
    <l>Below by doctrine were thus understood,</l>
    <l>No sophist's subtlety would there find place.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus was breathed forth from that enkindled love;</l>
    <l>Then added: &quot;Very well has been gone over</l>
    <l>Already of this coin the alloy and weight;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But tell me if thou hast it in thy purse?&quot;</l>
    <l>And I: &quot;Yes, both so shining and so round</l>
    <l>That in its stamp there is no peradventure.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafter issued from the light profound</l>
    <l>That there resplendent was: &quot;This precious jewel,</l>
    <l>Upon the which is every virtue founded,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence hadst thou it?&quot;  And I: &quot;The large outpouring</l>
    <l>Of Holy Spirit, which has been diffused</l>
    <l>Upon the ancient parchments and the new,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A syllogism is, which proved it to me</l>
    <l>With such acuteness, that, compared therewith,</l>
    <l>All demonstration seems to me obtuse.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And then I heard: &quot;The ancient and the new</l>
    <l>Postulates, that to thee are so conclusive,</l>
    <l>Why dost thou take them for the word divine?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I: &quot;The proofs, which show the truth to me,</l>
    <l>Are the works subsequent, whereunto Nature</l>
    <l>Ne'er heated iron yet, nor anvil beat.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Twas answered me: &quot;Say, who assureth thee</l>
    <l>That those works ever were? the thing itself</l>
    <l>That must be proved, nought else to thee affirms it.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Were the world to Christianity converted,&quot;</l>
    <l>I said, &quot;withouten miracles, this one</l>
    <l>Is such, the rest are not its hundredth part;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Because that poor and fasting thou didst enter</l>
    <l>Into the field to sow there the good plant,</l>
    <l>Which was a vine and has become a thorn!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This being finished, the high, holy Court</l>
    <l>Resounded through the spheres, &quot;One God we praise!&quot;</l>
    <l>In melody that there above is chanted.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And then that Baron, who from branch to branch,</l>
    <l>Examining, had thus conducted me,</l>
    <l>Till the extremest leaves we were approaching,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Again began: &quot;The Grace that dallying</l>
    <l>Plays with thine intellect thy mouth has opened,</l>
    <l>Up to this point, as it should opened be,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that I do approve what forth emerged;</l>
    <l>But now thou must express what thou believest,</l>
    <l>And whence to thy belief it was presented.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O holy father, spirit who beholdest</l>
    <l>What thou believedst so that thou o'ercamest,</l>
    <l>Towards the sepulchre, more youthful feet,&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Began I, &quot;thou dost wish me in this place</l>
    <l>The form to manifest of my prompt belief,</l>
    <l>And likewise thou the cause thereof demandest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I respond: In one God I believe,</l>
    <l>Sole and eterne, who moveth all the heavens</l>
    <l>With love and with desire, himself unmoved;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And of such faith not only have I proofs</l>
    <l>Physical and metaphysical, but gives them</l>
    <l>Likewise the truth that from this place rains down</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Through Moses, through the Prophets and the Psalms,</l>
    <l>Through the Evangel, and through you, who wrote</l>
    <l>After the fiery Spirit sanctified you;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In Persons three eterne believe, and these</l>
    <l>One essence I believe, so one and trine</l>
    <l>They bear conjunction both with 'sunt' and 'est.'</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>With the profound condition and divine</l>
    <l>Which now I touch upon, doth stamp my mind</l>
    <l>Ofttimes the doctrine evangelical.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>This the beginning is, this is the spark</l>
    <l>Which afterwards dilates to vivid flame,</l>
    <l>And, like a star in heaven, is sparkling in me.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even as a lord who hears what pleaseth him</l>
    <l>His servant straight embraces, gratulating</l>
    <l>For the good news as soon as he is silent;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So, giving me its benediction, singing,</l>
    <l>Three times encircled me, when I was silent,</l>
    <l>The apostolic light, at whose command</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I spoken had, in speaking I so pleased him.</l>
  </p>
</page>