<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>A will benign, in which reveals itself</l>
    <l>Ever the love that righteously inspires,</l>
    <l>As in the iniquitous, cupidity,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Silence imposed upon that dulcet lyre,</l>
    <l>And quieted the consecrated chords,</l>
    <l>That Heaven's right hand doth tighten and relax.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>How unto just entreaties shall be deaf</l>
    <l>Those substances, which, to give me desire</l>
    <l>Of praying them, with one accord grew silent?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Tis well that without end he should lament,</l>
    <l>Who for the love of thing that doth not last</l>
    <l>Eternally despoils him of that love!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As through the pure and tranquil evening air</l>
    <l>There shoots from time to time a sudden fire,</l>
    <l>Moving the eyes that steadfast were before,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And seems to be a star that changeth place,</l>
    <l>Except that in the part where it is kindled</l>
    <l>Nothing is missed, and this endureth little;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So from the horn that to the right extends</l>
    <l>Unto that cross's foot there ran a star</l>
    <l>Out of the constellation shining there;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor was the gem dissevered from its ribbon,</l>
    <l>But down the radiant fillet ran along,</l>
    <l>So that fire seemed it behind alabaster.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus piteous did Anchises' shade reach forward,</l>
    <l>If any faith our greatest Muse deserve,</l>
    <l>When in Elysium he his son perceived.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O sanguis meus, O superinfusa</l>
    <l>Gratia Dei, sicut tibi, cui</l>
    <l>Bis unquam Coeli janua reclusa?&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus that effulgence; whence I gave it heed;</l>
    <l>Then round unto my Lady turned my sight,</l>
    <l>And on this side and that was stupefied;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For in her eyes was burning such a smile</l>
    <l>That with mine own methought I touched the bottom</l>
    <l>Both of my grace and of my Paradise!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then, pleasant to the hearing and the sight,</l>
    <l>The spirit joined to its beginning things</l>
    <l>I understood not, so profound it spake;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor did it hide itself from me by choice,</l>
    <l>But by necessity; for its conception</l>
    <l>Above the mark of mortals set itself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And when the bow of burning sympathy</l>
    <l>Was so far slackened, that its speech descended</l>
    <l>Towards the mark of our intelligence,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The first thing that was understood by me</l>
    <l>Was &quot;Benedight be Thou, O Trine and One,</l>
    <l>Who hast unto my seed so courteous been!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And it continued: &quot;Hunger long and grateful,</l>
    <l>Drawn from the reading of the mighty volume</l>
    <l>Wherein is never changed the white nor dark,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou hast appeased, my son, within this light</l>
    <l>In which I speak to thee, by grace of her</l>
    <l>Who to this lofty flight with plumage clothed thee.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou thinkest that to me thy thought doth pass</l>
    <l>From Him who is the first, as from the unit,</l>
    <l>If that be known, ray out the five and six;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And therefore who I am thou askest not,</l>
    <l>And why I seem more joyous unto thee</l>
    <l>Than any other of this gladsome crowd.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou think'st the truth; because the small and great</l>
    <l>Of this existence look into the mirror</l>
    <l>Wherein, before thou think'st, thy thought thou showest.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But that the sacred love, in which I watch</l>
    <l>With sight perpetual, and which makes me thirst</l>
    <l>With sweet desire, may better be fulfilled,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now let thy voice secure and frank and glad</l>
    <l>Proclaim the wishes, the desire proclaim,</l>
    <l>To which my answer is decreed already.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To Beatrice I turned me, and she heard</l>
    <l>Before I spake, and smiled to me a sign,</l>
    <l>That made the wings of my desire increase;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then in this wise began I: &quot;Love and knowledge,</l>
    <l>When on you dawned the first Equality,</l>
    <l>Of the same weight for each of you became;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For in the Sun, which lighted you and burned</l>
    <l>With heat and radiance, they so equal are,</l>
    <l>That all similitudes are insufficient.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But among mortals will and argument,</l>
    <l>For reason that to you is manifest,</l>
    <l>Diversely feathered in their pinions are.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whence I, who mortal am, feel in myself</l>
    <l>This inequality; so give not thanks,</l>
    <l>Save in my heart, for this paternal welcome.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Truly do I entreat thee, living topaz!</l>
    <l>Set in this precious jewel as a gem,</l>
    <l>That thou wilt satisfy me with thy name.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;O leaf of mine, in whom I pleasure took</l>
    <l>E'en while awaiting, I was thine own root!&quot;</l>
    <l>Such a beginning he in answer made me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then said to me: &quot;That one from whom is named</l>
    <l>Thy race, and who a hundred years and more</l>
    <l>Has circled round the mount on the first cornice,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>A son of mine and thy great-grandsire was;</l>
    <l>Well it behoves thee that the long fatigue</l>
    <l>Thou shouldst for him make shorter with thy works.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Florence, within the ancient boundary</l>
    <l>From which she taketh still her tierce and nones,</l>
    <l>Abode in quiet, temperate and chaste.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>No golden chain she had, nor coronal,</l>
    <l>Nor ladies shod with sandal shoon, nor girdle</l>
    <l>That caught the eye more than the person did.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not yet the daughter at her birth struck fear</l>
    <l>Into the father, for the time and dower</l>
    <l>Did not o'errun this side or that the measure.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>No houses had she void of families,</l>
    <l>Not yet had thither come Sardanapalus</l>
    <l>To show what in a chamber can be done;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Not yet surpassed had Montemalo been</l>
    <l>By your Uccellatojo, which surpassed</l>
    <l>Shall in its downfall be as in its rise.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Bellincion Berti saw I go begirt</l>
    <l>With leather and with bone, and from the mirror</l>
    <l>His dame depart without a painted face;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And him of Nerli saw, and him of Vecchio,</l>
    <l>Contented with their simple suits of buff</l>
    <l>And with the spindle and the flax their dames.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O fortunate women! and each one was certain</l>
    <l>Of her own burial-place, and none as yet</l>
    <l>For sake of France was in her bed deserted.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>One o'er the cradle kept her studious watch,</l>
    <l>And in her lullaby the language used</l>
    <l>That first delights the fathers and the mothers;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Another, drawing tresses from her distaff,</l>
    <l>Told o'er among her family the tales</l>
    <l>Of Trojans and of Fesole and Rome.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As great a marvel then would have been held</l>
    <l>A Lapo Salterello, a Cianghella,</l>
    <l>As Cincinnatus or Cornelia now.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To such a quiet, such a beautiful</l>
    <l>Life of the citizen, to such a safe</l>
    <l>Community, and to so sweet an inn,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Did Mary give me, with loud cries invoked,</l>
    <l>And in your ancient Baptistery at once</l>
    <l>Christian and Cacciaguida I became.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Moronto was my brother, and Eliseo;</l>
    <l>From Val di Pado came to me my wife,</l>
    <l>And from that place thy surname was derived.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I followed afterward the Emperor Conrad,</l>
    <l>And he begirt me of his chivalry,</l>
    <l>So much I pleased him with my noble deeds.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I followed in his train against that law's</l>
    <l>Iniquity, whose people doth usurp</l>
    <l>Your just possession, through your Pastor's fault.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There by that execrable race was I</l>
    <l>Released from bonds of the fallacious world,</l>
    <l>The love of which defileth many souls,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And came from martyrdom unto this peace.&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>