<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>O Thou insensate care of mortal men,</l>
    <l>How inconclusive are the syllogisms</l>
    <l>That make thee beat thy wings in downward flight!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>One after laws and one to aphorisms</l>
    <l>Was going, and one following the priesthood,</l>
    <l>And one to reign by force or sophistry,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And one in theft, and one in state affairs,</l>
    <l>One in the pleasures of the flesh involved</l>
    <l>Wearied himself, one gave himself to ease;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When I, from all these things emancipate,</l>
    <l>With Beatrice above there in the Heavens</l>
    <l>With such exceeding glory was received!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When each one had returned unto that point</l>
    <l>Within the circle where it was before,</l>
    <l>It stood as in a candlestick a candle;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And from within the effulgence which at first</l>
    <l>Had spoken unto me, I heard begin</l>
    <l>Smiling while it more luminous became:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Even as I am kindled in its ray,</l>
    <l>So, looking into the Eternal Light,</l>
    <l>The occasion of thy thoughts I apprehend.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thou doubtest, and wouldst have me to resift</l>
    <l>In language so extended and so open</l>
    <l>My speech, that to thy sense it may be plain,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Where just before I said, 'where well one fattens,'</l>
    <l>And where I said, 'there never rose a second;'</l>
    <l>And here 'tis needful we distinguish well.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The Providence, which governeth the world</l>
    <l>With counsel, wherein all created vision</l>
    <l>Is vanquished ere it reach unto the bottom,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>(So that towards her own Beloved might go</l>
    <l>The bride of Him who, uttering a loud cry,</l>
    <l>Espoused her with his consecrated blood,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Self-confident and unto Him more faithful,)</l>
    <l>Two Princes did ordain in her behoof,</l>
    <l>Which on this side and that might be her guide.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The one was all seraphical in ardour;</l>
    <l>The other by his wisdom upon earth</l>
    <l>A splendour was of light cherubical.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>One will I speak of, for of both is spoken</l>
    <l>In praising one, whichever may be taken,</l>
    <l>Because unto one end their labours were.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Between Tupino and the stream that falls</l>
    <l>Down from the hill elect of blessed Ubald,</l>
    <l>A fertile slope of lofty mountain hangs,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From which Perugia feels the cold and heat</l>
    <l>Through Porta Sole, and behind it weep</l>
    <l>Gualdo and Nocera their grievous yoke.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>From out that slope, there where it breaketh most</l>
    <l>Its steepness, rose upon the world a sun</l>
    <l>As this one does sometimes from out the Ganges;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore let him who speaketh of that place,</l>
    <l>Say not Ascesi, for he would say little,</l>
    <l>But Orient, if he properly would speak.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He was not yet far distant from his rising</l>
    <l>Before he had begun to make the earth</l>
    <l>Some comfort from his mighty virtue feel.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>For he in youth his father's wrath incurred</l>
    <l>For certain Dame, to whom, as unto death,</l>
    <l>The gate of pleasure no one doth unlock;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And was before his spiritual court</l>
    <l>'Et coram patre' unto her united;</l>
    <l>Then day by day more fervently he loved her.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>She, reft of her first husband, scorned, obscure,</l>
    <l>One thousand and one hundred years and more,</l>
    <l>Waited without a suitor till he came.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Naught it availed to hear, that with Amyclas</l>
    <l>Found her unmoved at sounding of his voice</l>
    <l>He who struck terror into all the world;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Naught it availed being constant and undaunted,</l>
    <l>So that, when Mary still remained below,</l>
    <l>She mounted up with Christ upon the cross.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But that too darkly I may not proceed,</l>
    <l>Francis and Poverty for these two lovers</l>
    <l>Take thou henceforward in my speech diffuse.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Their concord and their joyous semblances,</l>
    <l>The love, the wonder, and the sweet regard,</l>
    <l>They made to be the cause of holy thoughts;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So much so that the venerable Bernard</l>
    <l>First bared his feet, and after so great peace</l>
    <l>Ran, and, in running, thought himself too slow.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O wealth unknown!  O veritable good!</l>
    <l>Giles bares his feet, and bares his feet Sylvester</l>
    <l>Behind the bridegroom, so doth please the bride!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Then goes his way that father and that master,</l>
    <l>He and his Lady and that family</l>
    <l>Which now was girding on the humble cord;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Nor cowardice of heart weighed down his brow</l>
    <l>At being son of Peter Bernardone,</l>
    <l>Nor for appearing marvellously scorned;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But regally his hard determination</l>
    <l>To Innocent he opened, and from him</l>
    <l>Received the primal seal upon his Order.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>After the people mendicant increased</l>
    <l>Behind this man, whose admirable life</l>
    <l>Better in glory of the heavens were sung,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Incoronated with a second crown</l>
    <l>Was through Honorius by the Eternal Spirit</l>
    <l>The holy purpose of this Archimandrite.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And when he had, through thirst of martyrdom,</l>
    <l>In the proud presence of the Sultan preached</l>
    <l>Christ and the others who came after him,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And, finding for conversion too unripe</l>
    <l>The folk, and not to tarry there in vain,</l>
    <l>Returned to fruit of the Italic grass,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>On the rude rock 'twixt Tiber and the Arno</l>
    <l>From Christ did he receive the final seal,</l>
    <l>Which during two whole years his members bore.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When He, who chose him unto so much good,</l>
    <l>Was pleased to draw him up to the reward</l>
    <l>That he had merited by being lowly,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Unto his friars, as to the rightful heirs,</l>
    <l>His most dear Lady did he recommend,</l>
    <l>And bade that they should love her faithfully;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And from her bosom the illustrious soul</l>
    <l>Wished to depart, returning to its realm,</l>
    <l>And for its body wished no other bier.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Think now what man was he, who was a fit</l>
    <l>Companion over the high seas to keep</l>
    <l>The bark of Peter to its proper bearings.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And this man was our Patriarch; hence whoever</l>
    <l>Doth follow him as he commands can see</l>
    <l>That he is laden with good merchandise.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But for new pasturage his flock has grown</l>
    <l>So greedy, that it is impossible</l>
    <l>They be not scattered over fields diverse;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And in proportion as his sheep remote</l>
    <l>And vagabond go farther off from him,</l>
    <l>More void of milk return they to the fold.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Verily some there are that fear a hurt,</l>
    <l>And keep close to the shepherd; but so few,</l>
    <l>That little cloth doth furnish forth their hoods.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Now if my utterance be not indistinct,</l>
    <l>If thine own hearing hath attentive been,</l>
    <l>If thou recall to mind what I have said,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>In part contented shall thy wishes be;</l>
    <l>For thou shalt see the plant that's chipped away,</l>
    <l>And the rebuke that lieth in the words,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>'Where well one fattens, if he strayeth not.'&quot;</l>
  </p>
</page>