<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <p>
    <l>Even as a bird, 'mid the beloved leaves,</l>
    <l>Quiet upon the nest of her sweet brood</l>
    <l>Throughout the night, that hideth all things from us,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Who, that she may behold their longed-for looks</l>
    <l>And find the food wherewith to nourish them,</l>
    <l>In which, to her, grave labours grateful are,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Anticipates the time on open spray</l>
    <l>And with an ardent longing waits the sun,</l>
    <l>Gazing intent as soon as breaks the dawn:</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Even thus my Lady standing was, erect</l>
    <l>And vigilant, turned round towards the zone</l>
    <l>Underneath which the sun displays less haste;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So that beholding her distraught and wistful,</l>
    <l>Such I became as he is who desiring</l>
    <l>For something yearns, and hoping is appeased.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But brief the space from one When to the other;</l>
    <l>Of my awaiting, say I, and the seeing</l>
    <l>The welkin grow resplendent more and more.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And Beatrice exclaimed: &quot;Behold the hosts</l>
    <l>Of Christ's triumphal march, and all the fruit</l>
    <l>Harvested by the rolling of these spheres!&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>It seemed to me her face was all aflame;</l>
    <l>And eyes she had so full of ecstasy</l>
    <l>That I must needs pass on without describing.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As when in nights serene of the full moon</l>
    <l>Smiles Trivia among the nymphs eternal</l>
    <l>Who paint the firmament through all its gulfs,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Saw I, above the myriads of lamps,</l>
    <l>A Sun that one and all of them enkindled,</l>
    <l>E'en as our own doth the supernal sights,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And through the living light transparent shone</l>
    <l>The lucent substance so intensely clear</l>
    <l>Into my sight, that I sustained it not.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O Beatrice, thou gentle guide and dear!</l>
    <l>To me she said: &quot;What overmasters thee</l>
    <l>A virtue is from which naught shields itself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There are the wisdom and the omnipotence</l>
    <l>That oped the thoroughfares 'twixt heaven and earth,</l>
    <l>For which there erst had been so long a yearning.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As fire from out a cloud unlocks itself,</l>
    <l>Dilating so it finds not room therein,</l>
    <l>And down, against its nature, falls to earth,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So did my mind, among those aliments</l>
    <l>Becoming larger, issue from itself,</l>
    <l>And that which it became cannot remember.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Open thine eyes, and look at what I am:</l>
    <l>Thou hast beheld such things, that strong enough</l>
    <l>Hast thou become to tolerate my smile.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>I was as one who still retains the feeling</l>
    <l>Of a forgotten vision, and endeavours</l>
    <l>In vain to bring it back into his mind,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>When I this invitation heard, deserving</l>
    <l>Of so much gratitude, it never fades</l>
    <l>Out of the book that chronicles the past.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>If at this moment sounded all the tongues</l>
    <l>That Polyhymnia and her sisters made</l>
    <l>Most lubrical with their delicious milk,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>To aid me, to a thousandth of the truth</l>
    <l>It would not reach, singing the holy smile</l>
    <l>And how the holy aspect it illumed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And therefore, representing Paradise,</l>
    <l>The sacred poem must perforce leap over,</l>
    <l>Even as a man who finds his way cut off;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>But whoso thinketh of the ponderous theme,</l>
    <l>And of the mortal shoulder laden with it,</l>
    <l>Should blame it not, if under this it tremble.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>It is no passage for a little boat</l>
    <l>This which goes cleaving the audacious prow,</l>
    <l>Nor for a pilot who would spare himself.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;Why doth my face so much enamour thee,</l>
    <l>That to the garden fair thou turnest not,</l>
    <l>Which under the rays of Christ is blossoming?</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There is the Rose in which the Word Divine</l>
    <l>Became incarnate; there the lilies are</l>
    <l>By whose perfume the good way was discovered.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus Beatrice; and I, who to her counsels</l>
    <l>Was wholly ready, once again betook me</l>
    <l>Unto the battle of the feeble brows.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>As in the sunshine, that unsullied streams</l>
    <l>Through fractured cloud, ere now a meadow of flowers</l>
    <l>Mine eyes with shadow covered o'er have seen,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>So troops of splendours manifold I saw</l>
    <l>Illumined from above with burning rays,</l>
    <l>Beholding not the source of the effulgence.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O power benignant that dost so imprint them!</l>
    <l>Thou didst exalt thyself to give more scope</l>
    <l>There to mine eyes, that were not strong enough.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The name of that fair flower I e'er invoke</l>
    <l>Morning and evening utterly enthralled</l>
    <l>My soul to gaze upon the greater fire.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And when in both mine eyes depicted were</l>
    <l>The glory and greatness of the living star</l>
    <l>Which there excelleth, as it here excelled,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Athwart the heavens a little torch descended</l>
    <l>Formed in a circle like a coronal,</l>
    <l>And cinctured it, and whirled itself about it.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Whatever melody most sweetly soundeth</l>
    <l>On earth, and to itself most draws the soul,</l>
    <l>Would seem a cloud that, rent asunder, thunders,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Compared unto the sounding of that lyre</l>
    <l>Wherewith was crowned the sapphire beautiful,</l>
    <l>Which gives the clearest heaven its sapphire hue.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>&quot;I am Angelic Love, that circle round</l>
    <l>The joy sublime which breathes from out the womb</l>
    <l>That was the hostelry of our Desire;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And I shall circle, Lady of Heaven, while</l>
    <l>Thou followest thy Son, and mak'st diviner</l>
    <l>The sphere supreme, because thou enterest there.&quot;</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thus did the circulated melody</l>
    <l>Seal itself up; and all the other lights</l>
    <l>Were making to resound the name of Mary.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>The regal mantle of the volumes all</l>
    <l>Of that world, which most fervid is and living</l>
    <l>With breath of God and with his works and ways,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Extended over us its inner border,</l>
    <l>So very distant, that the semblance of it</l>
    <l>There where I was not yet appeared to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Therefore mine eyes did not possess the power</l>
    <l>Of following the incoronated flame,</l>
    <l>Which mounted upward near to its own seed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>And as a little child, that towards its mother</l>
    <l>Stretches its arms, when it the milk has taken,</l>
    <l>Through impulse kindled into outward flame,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Each of those gleams of whiteness upward reached</l>
    <l>So with its summit, that the deep affection</l>
    <l>They had for Mary was revealed to me.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>Thereafter they remained there in my sight,</l>
    <l>'Regina coeli' singing with such sweetness,</l>
    <l>That ne'er from me has the delight departed.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>O, what exuberance is garnered up</l>
    <l>Within those richest coffers, which had been</l>
    <l>Good husbandmen for sowing here below!</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There they enjoy and live upon the treasure</l>
    <l>Which was acquired while weeping in the exile</l>
    <l>Of Babylon, wherein the gold was left.</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>There triumpheth, beneath the exalted Son</l>
    <l>Of God and Mary, in his victory,</l>
    <l>Both with the ancient council and the new,</l>
  </p>
  <p>
    <l>He who doth keep the keys of such a glory.</l>
  </p>
</page>