<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>O senseless cares of mortals, how deceiving</l>
		<l>are syllogistic reasonings that bring</l>
		<l>your wings to flight so low, to earthly things!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One studied law and one the Aphorisms</l>
		<l>of the physicians; one was set on priesthood</l>
		<l>and one, through force or fraud, on rulership;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>one meant to plunder, one to politick;</l>
		<l>one labored, tangled in delights of flesh,</l>
		<l>and one was fully bent on indolence;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>while I, delivered from our servitude</l>
		<l>to all these things, was in the height of heaven</l>
		<l>with Beatrice, so gloriously welcomed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After each of those spirits had returned</l>
		<l>to that place in the ring where it had been,</l>
		<l>it halted, like a candle in its stand.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And from within the splendor that had spoken</l>
		<l>to me before, I heard him, as he smiled-</l>
		<l>become more radiant, more pure-begin:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Even as I grow bright within Its rays,</l>
		<l>so, as I gaze at the Eternal Light,</l>
		<l>I can perceive your thoughts and see their cause.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You are in doubt; you want an explanation</l>
		<l>in language that is open and expanded,</l>
		<l>so clear that it contents your understanding</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of two points: where I said, &apos;They fatten well,&apos;</l>
		<l>and where I said, &apos;No other ever rose&apos;-</l>
		<l>and here one has to make a clear distinction.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The Providence that rules the world with wisdom</l>
		<l>so fathomless that creatures&apos; intellects</l>
		<l>are vanquished and can never probe its depth,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that the Bride of Him who, with loud cries,</l>
		<l>had wed her with His blessed blood, might meet</l>
		<l>her Love with more fidelity and more</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>assurance in herself, on her behalf</l>
		<l>commanded that there be two princes, one</l>
		<l>on this side, one on that side, as her guides.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One prince was all seraphic in his ardor;</l>
		<l>the other, for his wisdom, had possessed</l>
		<l>the splendor of cherubic light on earth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I shall devote my tale to one, because</l>
		<l>in praising either prince one praises both:</l>
		<l>the labors of the two were toward one goal.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Between Topino&apos;s stream and that which flows</l>
		<l>down from the hill the blessed Ubaldo chose,</l>
		<l>from a high peak there hangs a fertile slope;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>from there Perugia feels both heat and cold</l>
		<l>at Porta Sole, while behind it sorrow</l>
		<l>Nocera and Gualdo under their hard yoke.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From this hillside, where it abates its rise,</l>
		<l>a sun was born into the world, much like</l>
		<l>this sun when it is climbing from the Ganges.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore let him who names this site not say</l>
		<l>Ascesi, which would be to say too little,</l>
		<l>but Orient, if he would name it rightly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That sun was not yet very distant from</l>
		<l>his rising, when he caused the earth to take</l>
		<l>some comfort from his mighty influence;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for even as a youth, he ran to war</l>
		<l>against his father, on behalf of her-</l>
		<l>the lady unto whom, just as to death,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>none willingly unlocks the door; before</l>
		<l>his spiritual court et coram patre,</l>
		<l>he wed her; day by day he loved her more.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>She was bereft of her first husband; scorned,</l>
		<l>obscure, for some eleven hundred years,</l>
		<l>until that sun came, she had had no suitor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nor did it help her when men heard that he</l>
		<l>who made earth tremble found her unafraid-</l>
		<l>serene, with Amyclas-when he addressed her;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>nor did her constancy and courage help</l>
		<l>when she, even when Mary stayed below,</l>
		<l>suffered with Christ upon the cross. But so</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that I not tell my tale too darkly, you</l>
		<l>may now take Francis and take Poverty</l>
		<l>to be the lovers meant in my recounting.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Their harmony and their glad looks, their love</l>
		<l>and wonder and their gentle contemplation,</l>
		<l>served others as a source of holy thoughts;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so much so, that the venerable Bernard</l>
		<l>went barefoot first; he hurried toward such peace;</l>
		<l>and though he ran, he thought his pace too slow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O wealth unknown! O good that is so fruitful!</l>
		<l>Egidius goes barefoot, and Sylvester,</l>
		<l>behind the groom-the bride delights them so.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then Francis-father, master-goes his way</l>
		<l>with both his lady and his family,</l>
		<l>the lowly cord already round their waists.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nor did he lower his eyes in shame because</l>
		<l>he was the son of Pietro Bernardone,</l>
		<l>nor for the scorn and wonder he aroused;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but like a sovereign, he disclosed in full-</l>
		<l>to Innocent-the sternness of his rule;</l>
		<l>from him he had the first seal of his order.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And after many of the poor had followed</l>
		<l>Francis, whose wondrous life were better sung</l>
		<l>by glory&apos;s choir in the Empyrean,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the sacred purpose of this chief of shepherds</l>
		<l>was then encircled with a second crown</l>
		<l>by the Eternal Spirit through Honorius.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And after, in his thirst for martyrdom,</l>
		<l>within the presence of the haughty Sultan,</l>
		<l>he preached of Christ and those who followed Him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But, finding hearers who were too unripe</l>
		<l>to be converted, he-not wasting time-</l>
		<l>returned to harvest the Italian fields;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>there, on the naked crag between the Arno</l>
		<l>and Tiber, he received the final seal</l>
		<l>from Christ; and this, his limbs bore for two years</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When He who destined Francis to such goodness</l>
		<l>was pleased to draw him up to the reward</l>
		<l>that he had won through his humility,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then to his brothers, as to rightful heirs,</l>
		<l>Francis commended his most precious lady,</l>
		<l>and he bade them to love her faithfully;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and when, returning to its kingdom, his</l>
		<l>bright soul wanted to set forth from her bosom,</l>
		<l>it, for its body, asked no other bier.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Consider now that man who was a colleague</l>
		<l>worthy of Francis; with him, in high seas,</l>
		<l>he kept the bark of Peter on true course.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Such was our patriarch; thus you can see</l>
		<l>that those who follow him as he commands,</l>
		<l>as cargo carry worthy merchandise.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But now his flock is grown so greedy for</l>
		<l>new nourishment that it must wander far,</l>
		<l>in search of strange and distant grazing lands;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and as his sheep, remote and vagabond,</l>
		<l>stray farther from his side, at their return</l>
		<l>into the fold, their lack of milk is greater.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Though there are some indeed who, fearing harm,</l>
		<l>stay near the shepherd, they are few in number-</l>
		<l>to cowl them would require little cloth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now if my words are not too dim and distant,</l>
		<l>if you have listened carefully to them,</l>
		<l>if you can call to mind what has been said,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then part of what you wish to know is answered,</l>
		<l>for you will see the splinters on the plant</l>
		<l>and see what my correction meant: &apos;Where one</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>may fatten well, if one does not stray off.&apos;&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
