<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>After the lady who imparadises</l>
		<l>my mind disclosed the truth that is unlike</l>
		<l>the present life of miserable mortals,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then, just as one who sees a mirrored flame-</l>
		<l>its double candle stands behind his back-</l>
		<l>even before he thought of it or gazed</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>directly at it, and he turns to gauge</l>
		<l>if that glass tells the truth to him, and sees</l>
		<l>that it accords, like voice and instrument,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so-does my memory recall-I did</l>
		<l>after I looked into the lovely eyes</l>
		<l>of which Love made the noose that holds me tight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when I turned and my own eyes were met</l>
		<l>by what appears within that sphere whenever</l>
		<l>one looks intently at its revolution,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw a point that sent forth so acute</l>
		<l>a light, that anyone who faced the force</l>
		<l>with which it blazed would have to shut his eyes,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and any star that, seen from earth, would seem</l>
		<l>to be the smallest, set beside that point,</l>
		<l>as star conjoined with star, would seem a moon.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Around that point a ring of fire wheeled,</l>
		<l>a ring perhaps as far from that point as</l>
		<l>a halo from the star that colors it</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>when mist that forms the halo is most thick.</l>
		<l>It wheeled so quickly that it would outstrip</l>
		<l>the motion that most swiftly girds the world.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That ring was circled by a second ring,</l>
		<l>the second by a third, third by a fourth,</l>
		<l>fourth by a fifth, and fifth ring by a sixth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Beyond, the seventh ring, which followed, was</l>
		<l>so wide that all of Juno&apos;s messenger</l>
		<l>would be too narrow to contain that circle.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The eighth and ninth were wider still; and each,</l>
		<l>even as greater distance lay between</l>
		<l>it and the first ring, moved with lesser speed;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and, I believe, the ring with clearest flame</l>
		<l>was that which lay least far from the pure spark</l>
		<l>because it shares most deeply that point&apos;s truth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My lady, who saw my perplexity-</l>
		<l>I was in such suspense-said: &quot;On that Point</l>
		<l>depend the heavens and the whole of nature.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Look at the circle that is nearest It,</l>
		<l>and know: its revolutions are so swift</l>
		<l>because of burning love that urges it.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I to her: &quot;If earth and the nine spheres</l>
		<l>were ordered like those rings, then I would be</l>
		<l>content with what you have set out before me,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but in the world of sense, what one can see</l>
		<l>are spheres becoming ever more divine</l>
		<l>as they are set more distant from the center.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Thus, if my longing is to gain its end</l>
		<l>in this amazing and angelic temple</l>
		<l>that has, as boundaries, only love and light,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then I still have to hear just how the model</l>
		<l>and copy do not share in one same plan-</l>
		<l>for by myself I think on this in vain.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;You need not wonder if your fingers are</l>
		<l>unable to undo that knot: no one</l>
		<l>has tried, and so that knot is tightened, taut!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>my lady said, and then continued: &quot;If</l>
		<l>you would be satisfied, take what I tell you-</l>
		<l>and let your mind be sharp as I explain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The size of spheres of matter-large or small-</l>
		<l>depends upon the power-more and less-</l>
		<l>that spreads throughout their parts. More excellence</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>yields greater blessedness; more blessedness</l>
		<l>must comprehend a greater body when</l>
		<l>that body&apos;s parts are equally complete.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And thus this sphere, which sweeps along with it</l>
		<l>the rest of all the universe, must match</l>
		<l>the circle that loves most and knows the most,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that, if you but draw your measure round</l>
		<l>the power within-and not the semblance of-</l>
		<l>the angels that appear to you as circles,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you will discern a wonderful accord</l>
		<l>between each sphere and its Intelligence:</l>
		<l>greater accords with more, smaller with less.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as the hemisphere of air remains</l>
		<l>splendid, serene, when from his gentler cheek</l>
		<l>Boreas blows and clears the scoriae,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>dissolves the mist that had defaced the sky,</l>
		<l>so that the heavens smile with loveliness</l>
		<l>in all their regions; even so did I</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>become after my lady had supplied</l>
		<l>her clear response to me, and-like a star</l>
		<l>in heaven-truth was seen. And when her words</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>were done, even as incandescent iron</l>
		<l>will shower sparks, so did those circles sparkle;</l>
		<l>and each spark circled with its flaming ring-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>sparks that were more in number than the sum</l>
		<l>one reaches doubling in succession each</l>
		<l>square of a chessboard, one to sixty-four.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I heard &quot;Hosanna&quot; sung, from choir to choir</l>
		<l>to that fixed Point which holds and always shall</l>
		<l>hold them to where they have forever been.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And she who saw my mind&apos;s perplexities</l>
		<l>said: &quot;The first circles have displayed to you</l>
		<l>the Seraphim and Cherubim. They follow</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the ties of love with such rapidity</l>
		<l>because they are as like the Point as creatures</l>
		<l>can be, a power dependent on their vision.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those other loves that circle round them are</l>
		<l>called Thrones of the divine aspect, because</l>
		<l>they terminated the first group of three;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and know that all delight to the degree</l>
		<l>to which their vision sees-more or less deeply-</l>
		<l>that truth in which all intellects find rest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From this you see that blessedness depends</l>
		<l>upon the act of vision, not upon</l>
		<l>the act of love-which is a consequence;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the measure of their vision lies in merit,</l>
		<l>produced by grace and then by will to goodness:</l>
		<l>and this is the progression, step by step.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The second triad-blossoming in this</l>
		<l>eternal springtime that the nightly Ram</l>
		<l>does not despoil-perpetually sings</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&apos;Hosanna&apos; with three melodies that sound</l>
		<l>in the three ranks of bliss that form this triad;</l>
		<l>within this hierarchy there are three</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>kinds of divinities: first, the Dominions,</l>
		<l>and then the Virtues; and the final order</l>
		<l>contains the Powers. The two penultimate</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>groups of rejoicing ones within the next</l>
		<l>triad are wheeling Principalities</l>
		<l>and the Archangels; last, the playful Angels.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These orders all direct-ecstatically-</l>
		<l>their eyes on high; and downward, they exert</l>
		<l>such force that all are drawn and draw to God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And Dionysius, with much longing, set</l>
		<l>himself to contemplate these orders: he</l>
		<l>named and distinguished them just as I do.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Though, later, Gregory disputed him,</l>
		<l>when Gregory came here-when he could see</l>
		<l>with opened eyes-he smiled at his mistake.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You need not wonder if a mortal told</l>
		<l>such secret truth on earth: it was disclosed</l>
		<l>to him by one who saw it here above-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>both that and other truths about these circles.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
