<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>No sooner had the blessed flame begun</l>
		<l>to speak its final word than the millstone</l>
		<l>of holy lights began to turn, but it</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was not yet done with one full revolution</l>
		<l>before another ring surrounded it,</l>
		<l>and motion matched with motion, song with song-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a song that, sung by those sweet instruments,</l>
		<l>surpasses so our Muses and our Sirens</l>
		<l>as firstlight does the light that is reflected.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as, concentric, like in color, two</l>
		<l>rainbows will curve their way through a thin cloud</l>
		<l>when Juno has commanded her handmaid,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the outer rainbow echoing the inner,</l>
		<l>much like the voice of one-the wandering nymph-</l>
		<l>whom love consumed as sun consumes the mist</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>(and those two bows let people here foretell,</l>
		<l>by reason of the pact God made with Noah,</l>
		<l>that flood will never strike the world again):</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so the two garlands of those everlasting</l>
		<l>roses circled around us, and so did</l>
		<l>the outer circle mime the inner ring.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When dance and jubilation, festival</l>
		<l>of song and flame that answered flame, of light</l>
		<l>with light, of gladness and benevolence,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in one same instant, with one will, fell still</l>
		<l>(just as the eyes, when moved by their desire,</l>
		<l>can only close and open in accord),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then from the heart of one of the new lights</l>
		<l>there came a voice, and as I turned toward it,</l>
		<l>I seemed a needle turning to the polestar;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and it began: &quot;The love that makes me fair</l>
		<l>draws me to speak about the other leader</l>
		<l>because of whom my own was so praised here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Where one is, it is right to introduce</l>
		<l>the other: side by side, they fought, so may</l>
		<l>they share in glory and together gleam.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Christ&apos;s army, whose rearming cost so dearly,</l>
		<l>was slow, uncertain of itself, and scanty</l>
		<l>behind its ensign, when the Emperor</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who rules forever helped his ranks in danger-</l>
		<l>only out of His grace and not their merits.</l>
		<l>And, as was said, He then sustained His bride,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>providing her with two who could revive</l>
		<l>a straggling people: champions who would</l>
		<l>by doing and by preaching bring new life.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In that part of the West where gentle zephyr</l>
		<l>rises to open those new leaves in which</l>
		<l>Europe appears reclothed, not far from where,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>behind the waves that beat upon the coast,</l>
		<l>the sun, grown weary from its lengthy course,</l>
		<l>at times conceals itself from all men&apos;s eyes-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>there, Calaroga, blessed by fortune, sits</l>
		<l>under the aegis of the mighty shield</l>
		<l>on which the lion loses and prevails.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within its walls was born the loving vassal</l>
		<l>of Christian faith, the holy athlete, one</l>
		<l>kind to his own and harsh to enemies;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>no sooner was his mind created than</l>
		<l>it was so full of living force that it,</l>
		<l>still in his mother&apos;s womb, made her prophetic.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, at the sacred font, where Faith and he</l>
		<l>brought mutual salvation as their dowry,</l>
		<l>the rites of their espousal were complete.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The lady who had given the assent</l>
		<l>for him saw, in a dream, astonishing</l>
		<l>fruit that would spring from him and from his heir</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And that his name might echo what he was,</l>
		<l>a spirit moved from here to have him called</l>
		<l>by the possessive of the One by whom</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he was possessed completely. Dominic</l>
		<l>became his name; I speak of him as one</l>
		<l>whom Christ chose as the worker in His garden.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He seemed the fitting messenger and servant</l>
		<l>of Christ: the very first love that he showed</l>
		<l>was for the first injunction Christ had given.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His nurse would often find him on the ground,</l>
		<l>alert and silent, in a way that said:</l>
		<l>&apos;It is for this that I have come.&apos; Truly,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>his father was Felice and his mother</l>
		<l>Giovanna if her name, interpreted,</l>
		<l>is in accord with what has been asserted.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Not for the world, for which men now travail</l>
		<l>along Taddeo&apos;s way or Ostian&apos;s,</l>
		<l>but through his love of the true manna, he</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>became, in a brief time, so great a teacher</l>
		<l>that he began to oversee the vineyard</l>
		<l>that withers when neglected by its keeper.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And from the seat that once was kinder to</l>
		<l>the righteous poor (and now has gone astray,</l>
		<l>not in itself, but in its occupant),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>he did not ask to offer two or three</l>
		<l>for six, nor for a vacant benefice,</l>
		<l>nor decimas, quae sunt pauperum Dei-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but pleaded for the right to fight against</l>
		<l>the erring world, to serve the seed from which</l>
		<l>there grew the four-and-twenty plants that ring you.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he, with both his learning and his zeal,</l>
		<l>and with his apostolic office, like</l>
		<l>a torrent hurtled from a mountain source,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>coursed, and his impetus, with greatest force,</l>
		<l>struck where the thickets of the heretics</l>
		<l>offered the most resistance. And from him</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>there sprang the streams with which the catholic</l>
		<l>garden has found abundant watering,</l>
		<l>so that its saplings have more life, more green.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If such was one wheel of the chariot</l>
		<l>in which the Holy Church, in her defense,</l>
		<l>taking the field, defeated enemies</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>within, then you must see the excellence</l>
		<l>of him-the other wheel-whom Thomas praised</l>
		<l>so graciously before I made my entry.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And yet the track traced by the outer rim</l>
		<l>of that wheel is abandoned now-as in</l>
		<l>a cask of wine when crust gives way to mold.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His family, which once advanced with steps</l>
		<l>that followed his footprints, has now turned back:</l>
		<l>its forward foot now seeks the foot that lags.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And soon we are to see, at harvest time,</l>
		<l>the poor grain gathered, when the tares will be</l>
		<l>denied a place within the bin-and weep.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I do admit that, if one were to search</l>
		<l>our volume leaf by leaf, he might still read</l>
		<l>one page with, &apos;I am as I always was&apos;;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but those of Acquasparta or Casale</l>
		<l>who read our Rule are either given to</l>
		<l>escaping it or making it too strict.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I am the living light of Bonaventure</l>
		<l>of Bagnorea; in high offices</l>
		<l>I always put the left-hand interests last.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Illuminato and Augustine are here;</l>
		<l>they were among the first unshod poor brothers</l>
		<l>to wear the cord, becoming friends of God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Hugh of St. Victor, too, is here with them;</l>
		<l>Peter of Spain, who, with his twelve books, glows</l>
		<l>on earth below; and Peter Book-Devourer,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nathan the prophet, Anselm, and Chrysostom</l>
		<l>the Metropolitan, and that Donatus</l>
		<l>who deigned to deal with that art which comes first.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Rabanus, too, is here; and at my side</l>
		<l>shines the Calabrian Abbot Joachim,</l>
		<l>who had the gift of the prophetic spirit.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To this-my praise of such a paladin-</l>
		<l>the glowing courtesy and the discerning</l>
		<l>language of Thomas urged me on and stirred,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>with me, the souls that form this company.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
