<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Though he had been absorbed in his delight,</l>
		<l>that contemplator freely undertook</l>
		<l>the task of teaching; and his holy words</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>began: &quot;The wound that Mary closed and then</l>
		<l>anointed was the wound that Eve-so lovely</l>
		<l>at Mary&apos;s feet-had opened and had pierced.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Below her, in the seats of the third rank,</l>
		<l>Rachel and Beatrice, as you see, sit.</l>
		<l>Sarah, Rebecca, Judith, and the one</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who was the great-grandmother of the singer</l>
		<l>who, as he sorrowed for his sinfulness,</l>
		<l>cried, &apos;Miserere mei&apos;-these you can see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>from rank to rank as I, in moving through</l>
		<l>the Rose, from petal unto petal, give</l>
		<l>to each her name. And from the seventh rank,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just as they did within the ranks above,</l>
		<l>the Hebrew women follow-ranging downward-</l>
		<l>dividing all the tresses of the Rose.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>They are the wall by which the sacred stairs</l>
		<l>divide, depending on the view of Christ</l>
		<l>with which their faith aligned. Upon one side,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>there where the Rose is ripe, with all its petals,</l>
		<l>are those whose faith was in the Christ to come;</l>
		<l>and on the other side-that semicircle</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>whose space is broken up by vacant places-</l>
		<l>sit those whose sight was set upon the Christ</l>
		<l>who had already come. And just as on</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>this side, to serve as such a great partition,</l>
		<l>there is the throne in glory of the Lady</l>
		<l>of Heaven and the seats that range below it,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, opposite, the seat of the great John-</l>
		<l>who, always saintly, suffered both the desert</l>
		<l>and martyrdom, and then two years of Hell-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>serves to divide; below him sit, assigned</l>
		<l>to this partition, Francis, Benedict,</l>
		<l>and Augustine, and others, rank on rank,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>down to this center of the Rose. Now see</l>
		<l>how deep is God&apos;s foresight: both aspects of</l>
		<l>the faith shall fill this garden equally.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And know that there, below the transverse row</l>
		<l>that cuts across the two divisions, sit</l>
		<l>souls who are there for merits not their own,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but-with certain conditions-others&apos; merits;</l>
		<l>for all of these are souls who left their bodies</l>
		<l>before they had the power of true choice.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Indeed, you may perceive this by yourself-</l>
		<l>their faces, childlike voices, are enough,</l>
		<l>if you look well at them and hear them sing.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But now you doubt and, doubting, do not speak;</l>
		<l>yet I shall loose that knot; I can release</l>
		<l>you from the bonds of subtle reasoning.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within the ample breadth of this domain,</l>
		<l>no point can find its place by chance, just as</l>
		<l>there is no place for sorrow, thirst, or hunger;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>whatever you may see has been ordained</l>
		<l>by everlasting law, so that the fit</l>
		<l>of ring and finger here must be exact;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and thus these souls who have, precociously,</l>
		<l>reached the true life do not, among themselves,</l>
		<l>find places high or low without some cause.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The King through whom this kingdom finds content</l>
		<l>in so much love and so much joyousness</l>
		<l>that no desire would dare to ask for more,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>creating every mind in His glad sight,</l>
		<l>bestows His grace diversely, at His pleasure-</l>
		<l>and here the fact alone must be enough.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And this is clearly and expressly noted</l>
		<l>for you in Holy Scripture, in those twins</l>
		<l>who, in their mother&apos;s womb, were moved to anger.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Thus, it is just for the celestial light</l>
		<l>to grace their heads with a becoming crown,</l>
		<l>according to the color of their hair.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Without, then, any merit in their works,</l>
		<l>these infants are assigned to different ranks-</l>
		<l>proclivity at birth, the only difference.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In early centuries, their parents&apos; faith</l>
		<l>alone, and their own innocence, sufficed</l>
		<l>for the salvation of the children; when</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>those early times had reached completion, then</l>
		<l>each male child had to find, through circumcision,</l>
		<l>the power needed by his innocent</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>member; but then the age of grace arrived,</l>
		<l>and without perfect baptism in Christ,</l>
		<l>such innocence was kept below, in Limbo.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Look now upon the face that is most like</l>
		<l>the face of Christ, for only through its brightness</l>
		<l>can you prepare your vision to see Him.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw such joy rain down upon her, joy</l>
		<l>carried by holy intellects created</l>
		<l>to fly at such a height, that all which I</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>had seen before did not transfix me with</l>
		<l>amazement so intense, nor show to me</l>
		<l>a semblance that was so akin to God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And the angelic love who had descended</l>
		<l>earlier, now spread his wings before her,</l>
		<l>singing &quot;Ave Maria, gratia plena.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>On every side, the blessed court replied,</l>
		<l>singing responses to his godly song,</l>
		<l>so that each spirit there grew more serene.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O holy father-who, for me, endure</l>
		<l>your being here below, leaving the sweet</l>
		<l>place where eternal lot assigns your seat-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who is that angel who with such delight</l>
		<l>looks into our Queen&apos;s eyes-he who is so</l>
		<l>enraptured that he seems to be a flame?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, once again, I called upon the teaching</l>
		<l>of him who drew from Mary beauty, as</l>
		<l>the morning star draws beauty from the sun.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he to me: &quot;All of the gallantry</l>
		<l>and confidence that there can be in angel</l>
		<l>or blessed soul are found in him, and we</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>would have it so, for it was he who carried</l>
		<l>the palm below to Mary, when God&apos;s Son</l>
		<l>wanted to bear our flesh as His own burden.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But follow with your eyes even as I</l>
		<l>proceed to speak, and note the great patricians</l>
		<l>of this most just and merciful empire.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those two who, there above, are seated, most</l>
		<l>happy to be so near the Empress, may</l>
		<l>be likened to the two roots of this Rose:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the one who, on her left, sits closest, is</l>
		<l>the father whose presumptuous tasting</l>
		<l>caused humankind to taste such bitterness;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and on the right, you see that ancient father</l>
		<l>of Holy Church, into whose care the keys</l>
		<l>of this fair flower were consigned by Christ.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he who saw, before he died, all of</l>
		<l>the troubled era of the lovely Bride-</l>
		<l>whom lance and nails had won-sits at his side;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and at the side of Adam sits that guide</l>
		<l>under whose rule the people, thankless, fickle,</l>
		<l>and stubborn, lived on manna. Facing Peter,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Anna is seated, so content to see</l>
		<l>her daughter that, as Anna sings hosannas,</l>
		<l>she does not move her eyes. And opposite</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the greatest father of a family,</l>
		<l>Lucia sits, she who urged on your lady</l>
		<l>when you bent your brows downward, to your ruin.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But time, which brings you sleep, takes flight, an</l>
		<l>we shall stop here-even as a good tailor</l>
		<l>who cuts the garment as his cloth allows-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and turn our vision to the Primal Love,</l>
		<l>that, gazing at Him, you may penetrate-</l>
		<l>as far as that can be-His radiance.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But lest you now fall back when, even as</l>
		<l>you move your wings, you think that you advance,</l>
		<l>imploring grace, through prayer you must beseech</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>grace from that one who has the power to help you;</l>
		<l>and do you follow me with your affection-</l>
		<l>so may my words and your heart share one way.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he began this holy supplication:</l>
	</p>
</page>
