<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>The glory of the One who moves all things</l>
		<l>permeates the universe and glows</l>
		<l>in one part more and in another less.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I was within the heaven that receives</l>
		<l>more of His light; and I saw things that he</l>
		<l>who from that height descends, forgets or can</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>not speak; for nearing its desired end,</l>
		<l>our intellect sinks into an abyss</l>
		<l>so deep that memory fails to follow it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nevertheless, as much as I, within</l>
		<l>my mind, could treasure of the holy kingdom</l>
		<l>shall now become the matter of my song.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O good Apollo, for this final task</l>
		<l>make me the vessel of your excellence,</l>
		<l>what you, to merit your loved laurel, ask.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Until this point, one of Parnassus&apos; peaks</l>
		<l>sufficed for me; but now I face the test</l>
		<l>the agon that is left; I need both crests.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Enter into my breast; within me breathe</l>
		<l>the very power you made manifest</l>
		<l>when you drew Marsyas out from his limbs&apos; sheath.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O godly force, if you so lend yourself</l>
		<l>to me, that I might show the shadow of</l>
		<l>the blessed realm inscribed within my mind,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then you would see me underneath the tree</l>
		<l>you love; there I shall take as crown the leaves</l>
		<l>of which my theme and you shall make me worthy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So seldom, father, are those garlands gathered</l>
		<l>for triumph of a ruler or a poet-</l>
		<l>a sign of fault or shame in human wills-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that when Peneian branches can incite</l>
		<l>someone to long and thirst for them, delight</l>
		<l>must fill the happy Delphic deity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Great fire can follow a small spark: there may</l>
		<l>be better voices after me to pray</l>
		<l>to Cyrrha&apos;s god for aid-that he may answer.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The lantern of the world approaches mortals</l>
		<l>by varied paths; but on that way which links</l>
		<l>four circles with three crosses, it emerges</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>joined to a better constellation and</l>
		<l>along a better course, and it can temper</l>
		<l>and stamp the world&apos;s wax more in its own manner.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Its entry from that point of the horizon</l>
		<l>brought morning there and evening here; almost</l>
		<l>all of that hemisphere was white-while ours</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was dark-when I saw Beatrice turn round</l>
		<l>and left, that she might see the sun; no eagle</l>
		<l>has ever stared so steadily at it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as a second ray will issue from the</l>
		<l>first and reascend, much like a pilgrim</l>
		<l>who seeks his home again, so on her action,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>fed by my eyes to my imagination,</l>
		<l>my action drew, and on the sun I set</l>
		<l>my sight more than we usually do.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>More is permitted to our powers there</l>
		<l>than is permitted here, by virtue of</l>
		<l>that place, made for mankind as its true home.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I did not bear it long, but not so briefly</l>
		<l>as not to see it sparkling round about,</l>
		<l>like molten iron emerging from the fire;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and suddenly it seemed that day had been</l>
		<l>added to day, as if the One who can</l>
		<l>had graced the heavens with a second sun.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The eyes of Beatrice were all intent</l>
		<l>on the eternal circles; from the sun,</l>
		<l>I turned aside; I set my eyes on her.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In watching her, within me I was changed</l>
		<l>as Glaucus changed, tasting the herb that made</l>
		<l>him a companion of the other sea gods.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Passing beyond the human cannot be</l>
		<l>worded; let Glaucus serve as simile-</l>
		<l>until grace grant you the experience.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Whether I only was the part of me</l>
		<l>that You created last, You-governing</l>
		<l>the heavens-know: it was Your light that raised me</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When that wheel which You make eternal through</l>
		<l>the heavens&apos; longing for You drew me with</l>
		<l>the harmony You temper and distinguish,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the fire of the sun then seemed to me</l>
		<l>to kindle so much of the sky, that rain</l>
		<l>or river never formed so broad a lake.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The newness of the sound and the great light</l>
		<l>incited me to learn their cause-I was</l>
		<l>more keen than I had ever been before.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And she who read me as I read myself,</l>
		<l>to quiet the commotion in my mind,</l>
		<l>opened her lips before I opened mine</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to ask, and she began: &quot;You make yourself</l>
		<l>obtuse with false imagining; you can</l>
		<l>not see what you would see if you dispelled it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You are not on the earth as you believe;</l>
		<l>but lightning, flying from its own abode,</l>
		<l>is less swift than you are, returning home.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>While I was freed from my first doubt by these</l>
		<l>brief words she smiled to me, I was yet caught</l>
		<l>in new perplexity. I said: &quot;I was</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>content already; after such great wonder,</l>
		<l>I rested. But again I wonder how</l>
		<l>my body rises past these lighter bodies.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At which, after a sigh of pity, she</l>
		<l>settled her eyes on me with the same look</l>
		<l>a mother casts upon a raving child,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and she began: &quot;All things, among themselves,</l>
		<l>possess an order; and this order is</l>
		<l>the form that makes the universe like God.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here do the higher beings see the imprint</l>
		<l>of the Eternal Worth, which is the end</l>
		<l>to which the pattern I have mentioned tends.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Within that order, every nature has</l>
		<l>its bent, according to a different station,</l>
		<l>nearer or less near to its origin.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore, these natures move to different ports</l>
		<l>across the mighty sea of being, each</l>
		<l>given the impulse that will bear it on.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This impulse carries fire to the moon;</l>
		<l>this is the motive force in mortal creatures;</l>
		<l>this binds the earth together, makes it one.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Not only does the shaft shot from this bow</l>
		<l>strike creatures lacking intellect, but those</l>
		<l>who have intelligence, and who can love.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The Providence that has arrayed all this</l>
		<l>forever quiets-with Its light-that heaven</l>
		<l>in which the swiftest of the spheres revolves;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to there, as toward a destined place, we now</l>
		<l>are carried by the power of the bow</l>
		<l>that always aims its shaft at a glad mark.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Yet it is true that, even as a shape</l>
		<l>may, often, not accord with art&apos;s intent,</l>
		<l>since matter may be unresponsive, deaf,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, from this course, the creature strays at times</l>
		<l>because he has the power, once impelled,</l>
		<l>to swerve elsewhere; as lightning from a cloud</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>is seen to fall, so does the first impulse,</l>
		<l>when man has been diverted by false pleasure,</l>
		<l>turn him toward earth. You should-if I am right-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>not feel more marvel at your climbing than</l>
		<l>you would were you considering a stream</l>
		<l>that from a mountain&apos;s height falls to its base.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It would be cause for wonder in you if,</l>
		<l>no longer hindered, you remained below,</l>
		<l>as if, on earth, a living flame stood still.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then she again turned her gaze heavenward.</l>
	</p>
</page>
