<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Generous will-in which is manifest</l>
		<l>always the love that breathes toward righteousness,</l>
		<l>as in contorted will is greediness-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>imposing silence on that gentle lyre,</l>
		<l>brought quiet to the consecrated chords</l>
		<l>that Heaven&apos;s right hand slackens and draws taut.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Can souls who prompted me to pray to them,</l>
		<l>by falling silent all in unison,</l>
		<l>be deaf to men&apos;s just prayers? Then he may grieve</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>indeed and endlessly-the man who leaves</l>
		<l>behind such love and turns instead to seek</l>
		<l>things that do not endure eternally.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As, through the pure and tranquil skies of night,</l>
		<l>at times a sudden fire shoots, and moves</l>
		<l>eyes that were motionless-a fire that seems</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a star that shifts its place, except that in</l>
		<l>that portion of the heavens where it flared,</l>
		<l>nothing is lost, and its own course is short-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, from the horn that stretches on the right,</l>
		<l>down to the foot of that cross, a star ran</l>
		<l>out of the constellation glowing there;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>nor did that gem desert the cross&apos;s track,</l>
		<l>but coursed along the radii, and seemed</l>
		<l>just like a flame that alabaster screens.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>With such affection did Anchises&apos; shade</l>
		<l>reach out (if we may trust our greatest muse)</l>
		<l>when in Elysium he saw his son.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O blood of mine-o the celestial grace</l>
		<l>bestowed beyond all measure-unto whom</l>
		<l>as unto you was Heaven&apos;s gate twice opened?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That light said this; at which, I stared at him.</l>
		<l>Then, looking back to see my lady, I,</l>
		<l>on this side and on that, was stupefied;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for in the smile that glowed within her eyes,</l>
		<l>I thought that I-with mine-had touched the height</l>
		<l>of both my blessedness and paradise.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then-and he was a joy to hear and see-</l>
		<l>that spirit added to his first words things</l>
		<l>that were too deep to meet my understanding.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Not that he chose to hide his sense from me;</l>
		<l>necessity compelled him; he conceived</l>
		<l>beyond the mark a mortal mind can reach.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when his bow of burning sympathy</l>
		<l>was slack enough to let his speech descend</l>
		<l>to meet the limit of our intellect,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>these were the first words where I caught the sense:</l>
		<l>&quot;Blessed be you, both Three and One, who show</l>
		<l>such favor to my seed.&quot; And he continued:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The long and happy hungering I drew</l>
		<l>from reading that great volume where both black</l>
		<l>and white are never changed, you-son-have now</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>appeased within this light in which I speak</l>
		<l>to you; for this, I owe my gratitude</l>
		<l>to her who gave you wings for your high flight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You think your thoughts flow into me from Him</l>
		<l>who is the First-as from the number one,</l>
		<l>the five and six derive, if one is known-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and so you do not ask me who I am</l>
		<l>and why I seem more joyous to you than</l>
		<l>all other spirits in this festive throng.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Your thought is true, for both the small and great</l>
		<l>of this life gaze into that mirror where,</l>
		<l>before you think, your thoughts have been displayed</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But that the sacred love in which I keep</l>
		<l>my vigil with unending watchfulness,</l>
		<l>the love that makes me thirst with sweet desire,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>be better satisfied, let your voice-bold,</l>
		<l>assured, and glad-proclaim your will and longing,</l>
		<l>to which my answer is decreed already.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I turned to Beatrice, but she heard me</l>
		<l>before I spoke; her smile to me was signal</l>
		<l>that made the wings of my desire grow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I began: &quot;As soon as you beheld</l>
		<l>the First Equality, both intellect</l>
		<l>and love weighed equally for each of you,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>because the Sun that brought you light and heat</l>
		<l>possesses heat and light so equally</l>
		<l>that no thing matches His equality;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>whereas in mortals, word and sentiment-</l>
		<l>to you, the cause of this is evident-</l>
		<l>are wings whose featherings are disparate.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I-mortal-feel this inequality;</l>
		<l>thus, it is only with my heart that I</l>
		<l>can offer thanks for your paternal greeting.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Indeed I do beseech you, living topaz,</l>
		<l>set in this precious jewel as a gem:</l>
		<l>fulfill my longing-let me know your name.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O you, my branch in whom I took delight</l>
		<l>even awaiting you, I am your root,&quot;</l>
		<l>so he, in his reply to me, began,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>then said:&quot;The man who gave your family</l>
		<l>its name, who for a century and more</l>
		<l>has circled the first ledge of Purgatory,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was son to me and was your great-grandfather;</l>
		<l>it is indeed appropriate for you</l>
		<l>to shorten his long toil with your good works.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Florence, within her ancient ring of walls-</l>
		<l>that ring from which she still draws tierce and nones-</l>
		<l>sober and chaste, lived in tranquillity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No necklace and no coronal were there,</l>
		<l>and no embroidered gowns; there was no girdle</l>
		<l>that caught the eye more than the one who wore it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No daughter&apos;s birth brought fear unto her father,</l>
		<l>for age and dowry then did not imbalance-</l>
		<l>to this side and to that-the proper measure.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There were no families that bore no children;</l>
		<l>and Sardanapalus was still a stranger-</l>
		<l>not come as yet to teach in the bedchamber.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Not yet had your Uccellatoio&apos;s rise</l>
		<l>outdone the rise of Monte Mario,</l>
		<l>which, too, will be outdone in its decline.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw Bellincione Berti girt</l>
		<l>with leather and with bone, and saw his wife</l>
		<l>come from her mirror with her face unpainted.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw dei Nerli and del Vecchio</l>
		<l>content to wear their suits of unlined skins,</l>
		<l>and saw their wives at spindle and at spool.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O happy wives! Each one was sure of her</l>
		<l>own burial place, and none-for France&apos;s sake-</l>
		<l>as yet was left deserted in her bed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One woman watched with loving care the cradle</l>
		<l>and, as she soothed her infant, used the way</l>
		<l>of speech with which fathers and mothers play;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>another, as she drew threads from the distaff,</l>
		<l>would tell, among her household, tales of Trojans,</l>
		<l>and tales of Fiesole, and tales of Rome.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>A Lapo Salterello, a Cianghella,</l>
		<l>would then have stirred as much dismay as now</l>
		<l>a Cincinnatus and Cornelia would.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To such a life-so tranquil and so lovely-</l>
		<l>of citizens in true community,</l>
		<l>into so sweet a dwelling place did Mary,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>invoked in pains of birth, deliver me;</l>
		<l>and I, within your ancient Baptistery,</l>
		<l>at once became Christian and Cacciaguida.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Moronto was my brother, and Eliseo;</l>
		<l>my wife came from the valley of the Po-</l>
		<l>the surname that you bear was brought by her.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>In later years I served the Emperor</l>
		<l>Conrad-and my good works so gained his favor</l>
		<l>that he gave me the girdle of his knighthood.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I followed him to war against the evil</l>
		<l>of that law whose adherents have usurped-</l>
		<l>this, through your Pastors&apos; fault-your just possessions.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, by that execrable race, I was</l>
		<l>set free from fetters of the erring world,</l>
		<l>the love of which defiles so many souls.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From martyrdom I came unto this peace.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
