<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>As long as both Latona&apos;s children take</l>
		<l>(when, covered by the Ram and Scales, they make</l>
		<l>their belt of the horizon at the same</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>moment) to pass from equilibrium-</l>
		<l>the zenith held in balance-to that state</l>
		<l>where, changing hemispheres, each leaves that belt</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so long did Beatrice, a smile upon</l>
		<l>her face, keep silent, even as she gazed</l>
		<l>intently at the Point that overwhelmed me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then she began: &quot;I tell-not ask-what you</l>
		<l>now want to hear, for I have seen it there</l>
		<l>where, in one point, all whens and ubis end.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Not to acquire new goodness for Himself-</l>
		<l>which cannot be-but that his splendor might,</l>
		<l>as it shines back to Him, declare &apos;Subsisto,&apos;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in His eternity outside of time,</l>
		<l>beyond all other borders, as pleased Him,</l>
		<l>Eternal Love opened into new loves.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nor did he lie, before this, as if languid;</l>
		<l>there was no after, no before-they were</l>
		<l>not there until God moved upon these waters.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then form and matter, either separately</l>
		<l>or in mixed state, emerged as flawless being,</l>
		<l>as from a three-stringed bow, three arrows spring.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as a ray shines into amber, crystal,</l>
		<l>or glass, so that there is no interval</l>
		<l>between its coming and its lighting all,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did the three-form, matter, and their union-</l>
		<l>flash into being from the Lord with no</l>
		<l>distinction in beginning: all at once.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Created with the substances were order</l>
		<l>and pattern; at the summit of the world</l>
		<l>were those in whom pure act had been produced;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and pure potentiality possessed</l>
		<l>the lowest part; and in the middle, act</l>
		<l>so joined potentiality that they</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>never disjoin. For you, Jerome has written</l>
		<l>that the creation of the angels came</l>
		<l>long centuries before all else was made;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but this, the truth I speak, is written by</l>
		<l>scribes of the Holy Ghost-as you can find</l>
		<l>if you look carefully-on many pages;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and reason, too, can see in part this truth,</l>
		<l>for it would not admit that those who move</l>
		<l>the heavens could, for so long, be without</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>their perfect task. Now you know where and when</l>
		<l>and how these loving spirits were created:</l>
		<l>with this, three flames of your desire are quenche</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, sooner than it takes to count to twenty,</l>
		<l>a portion of the angels violently</l>
		<l>disturbed the lowest of your elements.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The rest remained; and they, with such rejoicing,</l>
		<l>began the office you can see, that they</l>
		<l>never desert their circling contemplation.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The fall had its beginning in the cursed</l>
		<l>pride of the one you saw, held in constraint</l>
		<l>by all of the world&apos;s weights. Those whom you see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in Heaven here were modestly aware</l>
		<l>that they were ready for intelligence</l>
		<l>so vast, because of that Good which had made them:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>through this, their vision was exalted with</l>
		<l>illuminating grace and with their merit,</l>
		<l>so that their will is constant and intact.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I would not have you doubt, but have you know</l>
		<l>surely that there is merit in receiving</l>
		<l>grace, measured by the longing to receive it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By now, if you have taken in my words,</l>
		<l>you need no other aid to contemplate</l>
		<l>much in regard to this consistory.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But since on earth, throughout your schools, they</l>
		<l>that it is in the nature of the angels</l>
		<l>to understand, to recollect, to will,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I shall say more, so that you may see clearly</l>
		<l>the truth that, there below, has been confused</l>
		<l>by teaching that is so ambiguous.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These beings, since they first were gladdened by</l>
		<l>the face of God, from which no thing is hidden,</l>
		<l>have never turned their vision from that face,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that their sight is never intercepted</l>
		<l>by a new object, and they have no need</l>
		<l>to recollect an interrupted concept.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So that, below, though not asleep, men dream,</l>
		<l>speaking in good faith or in bad-the last,</l>
		<l>however, merits greater blame and shame.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Below, you do not follow one sole path</l>
		<l>as you philosophize-your love of show</l>
		<l>and thought of it so carry you astray!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Yet even love of show is suffered here</l>
		<l>with less disdain than the subordination</l>
		<l>or the perversion of the Holy Scripture.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, they devote no thought to how much blood</l>
		<l>it costs to sow it in the world, to how</l>
		<l>pleasing is he who-humbly-holds it fast.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Each one strives for display, elaborates</l>
		<l>his own inventions; preachers speak at length</l>
		<l>of these-meanwhile the Gospels do not speak.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One says that, to prevent the sun from reaching</l>
		<l>below, the moon-when Christ was crucified-</l>
		<l>moved back along the zodiac, so as</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to interpose itself; who says so, lies-</l>
		<l>for sunlight hid itself; not only Jews,</l>
		<l>but Spaniards, Indians, too, saw that eclipse.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Such fables, shouted through the year from pulpits-</l>
		<l>some here, some there-outnumber even all</l>
		<l>the Lapos and the Bindos Florence has;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that the wretched sheep, in ignorance,</l>
		<l>return from pasture, having fed on wind-</l>
		<l>but to be blind to harm does not excuse them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Christ did not say to his first company:</l>
		<l>&apos;Go, and preach idle stories to the world&apos;;</l>
		<l>but he gave them the teaching that is truth,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and truth alone was sounded when they spoke;</l>
		<l>and thus, to battle to enkindle faith,</l>
		<l>the Gospels served them as both shield and lance.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But now men go to preach with jests and jeers,</l>
		<l>and just as long as they can raise a laugh,</l>
		<l>the cowl puffs up, and nothing more is asked.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But such a bird nests in that cowl, that if</l>
		<l>the people saw it, they would recognize</l>
		<l>as lies the pardons in which they confide-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>pardons through which the world&apos;s credulity</l>
		<l>increases so, that people throng to every</l>
		<l>indulgence backed by no authority;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and this allows the Antonines to fatten</l>
		<l>their pigs, and others, too, more piggish still,</l>
		<l>who pay with counterfeit, illegal tender.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But since we have digressed enough, turn back</l>
		<l>your eyes now to the way that is direct;</l>
		<l>our time is short-so, too, must be our path.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The number of these angels is so great</l>
		<l>that there has never been a mortal speech</l>
		<l>or mortal thought that named a sum so steep;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and if you look at that which is revealed</l>
		<l>by Daniel, you will see that, while he mentions</l>
		<l>thousands, he gives no number with precision.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The First Light reaches them in ways as many</l>
		<l>as are the angels to which It conjoins</l>
		<l>Itself, as It illumines all of them;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and this is why (because affection follows</l>
		<l>the act of knowledge) the intensity</l>
		<l>of love&apos;s sweetness appears unequally.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By now you see the height, you see the breadth,</l>
		<l>of the Eternal Goodness: It has made</l>
		<l>so many mirrors, which divide Its light,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but, as before, Its own Self still is One.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
