<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O fellowship that has been chosen for</l>
		<l>the Blessed Lamb&apos;s great supper, where He feeds</l>
		<l>you so as always to fulfill your need,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>since by the grace of God, this man receives</l>
		<l>foretaste of something fallen from your table</l>
		<l>before death has assigned his time its limit,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>direct your mind to his immense desire,</l>
		<l>quench him somewhat: you who forever drink</l>
		<l>from that Source which his thought and longing see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So Beatrice; and these delighted souls</l>
		<l>formed companies of spheres around fixed poles,</l>
		<l>flaming as they revolved, as comets glow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as, in a clock&apos;s machinery,</l>
		<l>to one who watches them, the wheels turn so</l>
		<l>that, while the first wheel seems to rest, the last</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>wheel flies; so did those circling dancers-as</l>
		<l>they danced to different measures, swift and slow-</l>
		<l>make me a judge of what their riches were.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From that sphere which I noted as most precious,</l>
		<l>I saw a flame come forth with so much gladness</l>
		<l>that none it left behind had greater brightness;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and that flame whirled three times round Beatrice</l>
		<l>while singing so divine a song that my</l>
		<l>imagination cannot shape it for me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My pen leaps over it; I do not write:</l>
		<l>our fantasy and, all the more so, speech</l>
		<l>are far too gross for painting folds so deep.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O you who pray to us with such devotion-</l>
		<l>my holy sister-with your warm affection,</l>
		<l>you have released me from that lovely sphere.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, after he had stopped his motion, did</l>
		<l>the blessed flame breathe forth unto my lady;</l>
		<l>and what he said I have reported here.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>She answered: &quot;O eternal light of that</l>
		<l>great man to whom our Lord bequeathed the keys</l>
		<l>of this astonishing gladness-the keys</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He bore to earth-do test this man concerning</l>
		<l>the faith by which you walked upon the sea;</l>
		<l>ask him points light and grave, just as you please</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That he loves well and hopes well and has faith</l>
		<l>is not concealed from you: you see that Place</l>
		<l>where everything that happens is displayed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But since this realm has gained its citizens</l>
		<l>through the true faith, it rightly falls to him</l>
		<l>to speak of faith, that he may glorify it.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as the bachelor candidate must arm</l>
		<l>himself and does not speak until the master</l>
		<l>submits the question for discussion-not</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for settlement-so while she spoke I armed</l>
		<l>myself with all my arguments, preparing</l>
		<l>for such a questioner and such professing.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>On hearing that light breathe, &quot;Good Christian, speak,</l>
		<l>show yourself clearly: what is faith?&quot; I raised</l>
		<l>my brow, then turned to Beatrice, whose glance</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>immediately signaled me to let</l>
		<l>the waters of my inner source pour forth.</l>
		<l>Then I: &quot;So may the Grace that grants to me</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to make confession to the Chief Centurion</l>
		<l>permit my thoughts to find their fit expression&quot;;</l>
		<l>and followed, &quot;Father, as the truthful pen</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>of your dear brother wrote-that brother who,</l>
		<l>with you, set Rome upon the righteous road-</l>
		<l>faith is the substance of the things we hope for</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and is the evidence of things not seen;</l>
		<l>and this I take to be its quiddity.&quot;</l>
		<l>And then I heard: &quot;You understand precisely,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>if it is fully clear to you why he</l>
		<l>has first placed faith among the substances</l>
		<l>and then defines it as an evidence.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I next: &quot;The deep things that on me bestow</l>
		<l>their image here, are hid from sight below,</l>
		<l>so that their being lies in faith alone,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and on that faith the highest hope is founded;</l>
		<l>and thus it is that faith is called a substance.</l>
		<l>And it is from this faith that we must reason,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>deducing what we can from syllogisms,</l>
		<l>without our being able to see more:</l>
		<l>thus faith is also called an evidence.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And then I heard: &quot;If all one learns below</l>
		<l>as doctrine were so understood, there would</l>
		<l>be no place for the sophist&apos;s cleverness.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This speech was breathed from that enkindled love.</l>
		<l>He added: &quot;Now this coin is well-examined,</l>
		<l>and now we know its alloy and its weight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But tell me: do you have it in your purse?&quot;</l>
		<l>And I: &quot;Indeed I do-so bright and round</l>
		<l>that nothing in its stamp leads me to doubt.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Next, from the deep light gleaming there, I heard:</l>
		<l>&quot;What is the origin of the dear gem</l>
		<l>that comes to you, the gem on which all virtues</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>are founded?&quot; I: &quot;The Holy Ghost&apos;s abundant</l>
		<l>rain poured upon the parchments old and new;</l>
		<l>that is the syllogism that has proved</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>with such persuasiveness that faith has truth-</l>
		<l>when set beside that argument, all other</l>
		<l>demonstrations seem to me obtuse.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I heard: &quot;The premises of old and new</l>
		<l>impelling your conclusion-why do you</l>
		<l>hold these to be the speech of God?&quot; And I:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The proof revealing truth to me relies</l>
		<l>on acts that happened; for such miracles,</l>
		<l>nature can heat no iron, beat no anvil.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Say, who assures you that those works were real?&quot;</l>
		<l>came the reply. &quot;The very thing that needs</l>
		<l>proof-no thing else-attests these works to you.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I said: &quot;If without miracles the world</l>
		<l>was turned to Christianity, that is</l>
		<l>so great a miracle that all the rest</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>are not its hundredth part: for you were poor</l>
		<l>and hungry when you found the field and sowed</l>
		<l>the good plant-once a vine and now a thorn.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This done, the high and holy court resounded</l>
		<l>throughout its spheres with &quot;Te Deum laudamus,&quot;</l>
		<l>sung with the melody they use on high.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then he who had examined me, that baron</l>
		<l>who led me on from branch to branch so that</l>
		<l>we now were drawing close to the last leaves,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>began again: &quot;That Grace which-lovingly-</l>
		<l>directs your mind, until this point has taught</l>
		<l>you how to find the seemly words for thought,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that I do approve what you brought forth;</l>
		<l>but now you must declare what you believe</l>
		<l>and what gave you the faith that you receive.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O holy father, soul who now can see</l>
		<l>what you believed with such intensity</l>
		<l>that, to His tomb, you outran younger feet,&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I then began, &quot;you would have me tell plainly</l>
		<l>the form of my unhesitating faith,</l>
		<l>and also ask me to declare its source.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I answer: I believe in one God-sole,</l>
		<l>eternal-He who, motionless, moves all</l>
		<l>the heavens with His love and love for Him;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for this belief I have not only proofs</l>
		<l>both physical and metaphysical;</l>
		<l>I also have the truth that here rains down</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>through Moses and the Prophets and the Psalms</l>
		<l>and through the Gospels and through you who wrote</l>
		<l>words given to you by the Holy Ghost.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I believe in three Eternal Persons,</l>
		<l>and these I do believe to be one essence,</l>
		<l>so single and threefold as to allow</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>both is and are. Of this profound condition</l>
		<l>of God that I have touched on, Gospel teaching</l>
		<l>has often set the imprint on my mind.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This is the origin, this is the spark</l>
		<l>that then extends into a vivid flame</l>
		<l>and, like a star in heaven, glows in me.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just as the lord who listens to his servant&apos;s</l>
		<l>announcement, then, as soon as he is silent,</l>
		<l>embraces him, both glad with the good news,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did the apostolic light at whose</l>
		<l>command I had replied, while blessing me</l>
		<l>and singing, then encircle me three times:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the speech I spoke had brought him such delight.</l>
	</p>
</page>
