<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Amazement overwhelming me, I-like</l>
		<l>a child who always hurries back to find</l>
		<l>that place he trusts the most-turned to my guide;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and like a mother quick to reassure</l>
		<l>her pale and panting son with the same voice</l>
		<l>that she has often used to comfort him,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>she said: &quot;Do you not know you are in Heaven,</l>
		<l>not know how holy all of Heaven is,</l>
		<l>how righteous zeal moves every action here?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now, since this cry has agitated you</l>
		<l>so much, you can conceive how-had you seen</l>
		<l>me smile and heard song here-you would have been</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>confounded; and if you had understood</l>
		<l>the prayer within that cry, by now you would</l>
		<l>know the revenge you&apos;ll see before your death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The sword that strikes from Heaven&apos;s height is neither</l>
		<l>hasty nor slow, except as it appears</l>
		<l>to him who waits for it-who longs or fears.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But turn now toward the other spirits here;</l>
		<l>for if you set your sight as I suggest,</l>
		<l>you will see many who are notable.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As pleased my guide, I turned my eyes and saw</l>
		<l>a hundred little suns; as these together</l>
		<l>cast light, each made the other lovelier.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I stood as one who curbs within himself</l>
		<l>the goad of longing and, in fear of being</l>
		<l>too forward, does not dare to ask a question.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this, the largest and most radiant</l>
		<l>among those pearls moved forward that he might</l>
		<l>appease my need to hear who he might be.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, in that light, I heard: &quot;Were you to see,</l>
		<l>even as I do see, the charity</l>
		<l>that burns in us, your thoughts would have been uttered.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But lest, by waiting, you be slow to reach</l>
		<l>the high goal of your seeking, I shall answer</l>
		<l>what you were thinking when you curbed your speech</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That mountain on whose flank Cassino lies</l>
		<l>was once frequented on its summit by</l>
		<l>those who were still deluded, still awry;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and I am he who was the first to carry</l>
		<l>up to that peak the name of Him who brought</l>
		<l>to earth the truth that lifts us to the heights.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And such abundant grace had brought me light</l>
		<l>that, from corrupted worship that seduced</l>
		<l>the world, I won away the nearby sites.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>These other flames were all contemplatives,</l>
		<l>men who were kindled by that heat which brings</l>
		<l>to birth the blessed flowers and blessed fruits.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Here is Macarius, here is Romualdus,</l>
		<l>here are my brothers, those who stayed their steps</l>
		<l>in cloistered walls, who kept their hearts steadfast."</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I answered: &quot;The affection that you show</l>
		<l>in speech to me, and kindness that I see</l>
		<l>and note within the flaming of your lights,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>have given me so much more confidence,</l>
		<l>just like the sun that makes the rose expand</l>
		<l>and reach the fullest flowering it can.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore I pray you, father-and may you</l>
		<l>assure me that I can receive such grace-</l>
		<l>to let me see, unveiled, your human face.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he: &quot;Brother, your high desire will be</l>
		<l>fulfilled within the final sphere, as all</l>
		<l>the other souls&apos; and my own longing will.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There, each desire is perfect, ripe, intact;</l>
		<l>and only there, within that final sphere,</l>
		<l>is every part where it has always been.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That sphere is not in space and has no poles;</l>
		<l>our ladder reaches up to it, and that</l>
		<l>is why it now is hidden from your sight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Up to that sphere, Jacob the patriarch</l>
		<l>could see that ladder&apos;s topmost portion reach,</l>
		<l>when it appeared to him so thronged with angels.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But no one now would lift his feet from earth</l>
		<l>to climb that ladder, and my Rule is left</l>
		<l>to waste the paper it was written on.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What once were abbey walls are robbers&apos; dens;</l>
		<l>what once were cowls are sacks of rotten meal.</l>
		<l>But even heavy usury does not</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>offend the will of God as grievously</l>
		<l>as the appropriation of that fruit</l>
		<l>which makes the hearts of monks go mad with greed;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for all within the keeping of the Church</l>
		<l>belongs to those who ask it in God&apos;s name,</l>
		<l>and not to relatives or concubines.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The flesh of mortals yields so easily-</l>
		<l>on earth a good beginning does not run</l>
		<l>from when the oak is born until the acorn.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Peter began with neither gold nor silver,</l>
		<l>and I with prayer and fasting, and when Francis</l>
		<l>began his fellowship, he did it humbly;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>if you observe the starting point of each,</l>
		<l>and look again to see where it has strayed,</l>
		<l>then you will see how white has gone to gray.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And yet, the Jordan in retreat, the sea</l>
		<l>in flight when God had willed it so, were sights</l>
		<l>more wonderful than His help here will be.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So did he speak to me, and he drew back</l>
		<l>to join his company, which closed, compact;</l>
		<l>then, like a whirlwind, upward, all were swept.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The gentle lady-simply with a sign-</l>
		<l>impelled me after them and up that ladder,</l>
		<l>so did her power overcome my nature;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and never here below, where our ascent</l>
		<l>and descent follow nature&apos;s law, was there</l>
		<l>motion as swift as mine when I took wing.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, reader, may I once again return</l>
		<l>to those triumphant ranks-an end for which</l>
		<l>I often beat my breast, weep for my sins-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>more quickly than your finger can withdraw</l>
		<l>from flame and be thrust into it, I saw,</l>
		<l>and was within, the sign that follows Taurus.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O stars of glory, constellation steeped</l>
		<l>in mighty force, all of my genius-</l>
		<l>whatever be its worth-has you as source:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>with you was born and under you was hidden</l>
		<l>he who is father of all mortal lives,</l>
		<l>when I first felt the air of Tuscany;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and then, when grace was granted me to enter</l>
		<l>the high wheel that impels your revolutions,</l>
		<l>your region was my fated point of entry.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>To you my soul now sighs devotedly,</l>
		<l>that it may gain the force for this attempt,</l>
		<l>hard trial that now demands its every strength.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;You are so near the final blessedness,&quot;</l>
		<l>so Beatrice began, &quot;that you have need</l>
		<l>of vision clear and keen; and thus, before</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you enter farther, do look downward, see</l>
		<l>what I have set beneath your feet already:</l>
		<l>much of the world is there. If you see that,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>your heart may then present itself with all</l>
		<l>the joy it can to the triumphant throng</l>
		<l>that comes in gladness through this ether&apos;s rounds."</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My eyes returned through all the seven spheres</l>
		<l>and saw this globe in such a way that I</l>
		<l>smiled at its scrawny image: I approve</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that judgment as the best, which holds this earth</l>
		<l>to be the least; and he whose thoughts are set</l>
		<l>elsewhere, can truly be called virtuous.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw Latona&apos;s daughter radiant,</l>
		<l>without the shadow that had made me once</l>
		<l>believe that she contained both rare and dense.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there, Hyperion, I could sustain</l>
		<l>the vision of your son, and saw Dione</l>
		<l>and Maia as they circled nearby him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The temperate Jupiter appeared to me</l>
		<l>between his father and his son; and I</l>
		<l>saw clearly how they vary their positions.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And all the seven heavens showed to me</l>
		<l>their magnitudes, their speeds, the distances</l>
		<l>of each from each. The little threshing floor</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that so incites our savagery was all-</l>
		<l>from hills to river mouths-revealed to me</l>
		<l>while I wheeled with eternal Gemini.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My eyes then turned again to the fair eyes.</l>
	</p>
</page>
