<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;After Constantine had turned the Eagle</l>
		<l>counter to heaven&apos;s course, the course it took</l>
		<l>behind the ancient one who wed Lavinia,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>one hundred and one hundred years and more,</l>
		<l>the bird of God remained near Europe&apos;s borders,</l>
		<l>close to the peaks from which it first emerged;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>beneath the shadow of the sacred wings,</l>
		<l>it ruled the world, from hand to hand, until</l>
		<l>that governing-changing-became my task.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Caesar I was and am Justinian,</l>
		<l>who, through the will of Primal Love I feel,</l>
		<l>removed the vain and needless from the laws.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Before I grew attentive to this labor,</l>
		<l>I held that but one nature-and no more-</l>
		<l>was Christ&apos;s-and in that faith, I was content;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but then the blessed Agapetus, he</l>
		<l>who was chief shepherd, with his words turned me</l>
		<l>to that faith which has truth and purity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I did believe him, and now clearly see</l>
		<l>his faith, as you with contradictories</l>
		<l>can see that one is true and one is false.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As soon as my steps shared the Church&apos;s path,</l>
		<l>God, of His grace, inspired my high task</l>
		<l>as pleased Him. I was fully drawn to that.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Entrusting to my Belisarius</l>
		<l>my arms, I found a sign for me to rest</l>
		<l>from war: Heaven&apos;s right hand so favored him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My answer to the question you first asked</l>
		<l>ends here, and yet the nature of this answer</l>
		<l>leads me to add a sequel, so that you</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>may see with how much reason they attack</l>
		<l>the sacred standard-those who seem to act</l>
		<l>on its behalf and those opposing it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>See what great virtue made that Eagle worthy</l>
		<l>of reverence, beginning from that hour</l>
		<l>when Pallas died that it might gain a kingdom.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You know that for three hundred years and more,</l>
		<l>it lived in Alba, until, at the end,</l>
		<l>three still fought three, contending for that standard</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You know how, under seven kings, it conquered</l>
		<l>its neighbors-in the era reaching from</l>
		<l>wronged Sabine women to Lucrece&apos;s grief-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and what it did when carried by courageous</l>
		<l>Romans, who hurried to encounter Brennus,</l>
		<l>Pyrrhus, and other principates and cities.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Through this, Torquatus, Quinctius (who is named</l>
		<l>for his disheveled hair), the Decii,</l>
		<l>and Fabii gained the fame I gladly honor.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That standard brought the pride of Arabs low</l>
		<l>when they had followed Hannibal across</l>
		<l>those Alpine rocks from which, Po, you descend.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Beneath that standard, Scipio, Pompey-</l>
		<l>though young-triumphed; and to that hill beneath</l>
		<l>which you were born, that standard seemed most harsh</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, near the time when Heaven wished to bring</l>
		<l>all of the world to Heaven&apos;s way-serene-</l>
		<l>Caesar, as Rome had willed, took up that standard.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And what it did from Var to Rhine was seen</l>
		<l>by the Isere, Saone, and Seine and all</l>
		<l>the valley-floors whose rivers feed the Rhone.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And what it did, once it had left Ravenna</l>
		<l>and leaped the Rubicon, was such a flight</l>
		<l>as neither tongue nor writing can describe.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That standard led the legions on to Spain,</l>
		<l>then toward Durazzo, and it struck Pharsalia</l>
		<l>so hard that the warm Nile could feel that hurt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>It saw again its source, Antandros and</l>
		<l>Simois, and the place where Hector lies;</l>
		<l>then roused itself-the worse for Ptolemy.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From Egypt, lightning-like, it fell on Juba;</l>
		<l>and then it hurried to the west of you,</l>
		<l>where it could hear the trumpet of Pompey.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Because of what that standard did, with him</l>
		<l>who bore it next, Brutus and Cassius howl</l>
		<l>in Hell, and grief seized Modena, Perugia.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Because of it, sad Cleopatra weeps</l>
		<l>still; as she fled that standard, from the asp</l>
		<l>she drew a sudden and atrocious death.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And, with that very bearer, it then reached</l>
		<l>the Red Sea shore: with him, that emblem brought</l>
		<l>the world such peace that Janus&apos; shrine was shut.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But what the standard that has made me speak</l>
		<l>had done before or then was yet to do</l>
		<l>throughout the mortal realm where it holds rule,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>comes to seem faint and insignificant</l>
		<l>if one, with clear sight and pure sentiment,</l>
		<l>sees what it did in the third Caesar&apos;s hand;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for the true Justice that inspires me</l>
		<l>granted to it-in that next Caesar&apos;s hand-</l>
		<l>the glory of avenging His own wrath.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now marvel here at what I show to you:</l>
		<l>with Titus-afterward-it hurried toward</l>
		<l>avenging vengeance for the ancient sin.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And when the Lombard tooth bit Holy Church,</l>
		<l>then Charlemagne, under the Eagle&apos;s wings,</l>
		<l>through victories he gained, brought help to her.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now you can judge those I condemned above,</l>
		<l>and judge how such men have offended, have</l>
		<l>become the origin of all your evils.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For some oppose the universal emblem</l>
		<l>with yellow lilies; others claim that emblem</l>
		<l>for party: it is hard to see who is worse.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Let Ghibellines pursue their undertakings</l>
		<l>beneath another sign, for those who sever</l>
		<l>this sign and justice are bad followers.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And let not this new Charles strike at it with</l>
		<l>his Guelphs-but let him fear the claws that stripped</l>
		<l>a more courageous lion of its hide.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The sons have often wept for a father&apos;s fault;</l>
		<l>and let this son not think that God will change</l>
		<l>the emblem of His force for Charles&apos;s lilies.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This little planet is adorned with spirits</l>
		<l>whose acts were righteous, but who acted for</l>
		<l>the honor and the fame that they would gain:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and when desires tend toward earthly ends,</l>
		<l>then, so deflected, rays of the true love</l>
		<l>mount toward the life above with lesser force.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But part of our delight is measuring</l>
		<l>rewards against our merit, and we see</l>
		<l>that our rewards are neither less nor more.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Thus does the Living Justice make so sweet</l>
		<l>the sentiments in us, that we are free</l>
		<l>of any turning toward iniquity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Differing voices join to sound sweet music;</l>
		<l>so do the different orders in our life</l>
		<l>render sweet harmony among these spheres.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And in this very pearl there also shines</l>
		<l>the light of Romeo, of one whose acts,</l>
		<l>though great and noble, met ungratefulness.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And yet those Provencals who schemed against him</l>
		<l>had little chance to laugh, for he who finds</l>
		<l>harm to himself in others&apos; righteous acts</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>takes the wrong path. Of Raymond Berenger&apos;s</l>
		<l>four daughters, each became a queen-and this,</l>
		<l>poor and a stranger, Romeo accomplished.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then Berenger was moved by vicious tongues</l>
		<l>to ask this just man for accounting-one</l>
		<l>who, given ten, gave Raymond five and seven.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And Romeo, the poor, the old, departed;</l>
		<l>and were the world to know the heart he had</l>
		<l>while begging, crust by crust, for his life-bread,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>it-though it praise him now-would praise him more.</l>
	</p>
</page>
