<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>When he who graces all the world with light</l>
		<l>has sunk so far below our hemisphere</l>
		<l>that on all sides the day is spent, the sky,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>which had been lit before by him alone,</l>
		<l>immediately shows itself again</l>
		<l>with many lights reflecting one same source,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and I remembered this celestial course</l>
		<l>when, in the blessed beak, the emblem of</l>
		<l>the world and of its guardians fell silent;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for then all of those living lights grew more</l>
		<l>resplendent, but the songs that they began</l>
		<l>were labile-they escape my memory.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O gentle love that wears a smile as mantle,</l>
		<l>how ardent was your image in those torches</l>
		<l>filled only with the breath of holy thoughts!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After the precious, gleaming jewels with which</l>
		<l>the sixth of Heaven&apos;s heavens was engemmed</l>
		<l>had ended their angelic song in silence,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I seemed to hear the murmur of a torrent</l>
		<l>that, limpid, falls from rock to rock, whose flow</l>
		<l>shows the abundance of its mountain source.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Even as sound takes shape at the lute&apos;s neck,</l>
		<l>and even as the wind that penetrates</l>
		<l>the blow-hole of the bagpipe, so-with no</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>delay-that murmur of the Eagle rose</l>
		<l>straight up, directly through its neck as if</l>
		<l>its neck were hollow; and that murmuring</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>became a voice that issued from its beak,</l>
		<l>taking the shape of words desired by</l>
		<l>my heart-and that is where they were transcribed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;Now you must watch-and steadily-that part</l>
		<l>of me that can, in mortal eagles, see</l>
		<l>and suffer the sun&apos;s force,&quot; it then began</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to say to me, &quot;because, of all the flames</l>
		<l>from which I shape my form, those six with which</l>
		<l>the eye in my head glows hold highest rank.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He who gleams in the center, my eye&apos;s pupil-</l>
		<l>he was the singer of the Holy Spirit,</l>
		<l>who bore the ark from one town to another;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>now he has learned the merit will can earn-</l>
		<l>his song had not been spurred by grace alone,</l>
		<l>but his own will, in part, had urged him on.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Of those five flames that, arching, form my brow,</l>
		<l>he who is nearest to my beak is one</l>
		<l>who comforted the widow for her son;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>now he has learned the price one pays for not</l>
		<l>following Christ, through his experience</l>
		<l>of this sweet life and of its opposite.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he whose place is next on the circumference</l>
		<l>of which I speak, along the upward arc,</l>
		<l>delayed his death through truthful penitence;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>now he has learned that the eternal judgment</l>
		<l>remains unchanged, though worthy prayer below</l>
		<l>makes what falls due today take place tomorrow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The next who follows-one whose good intention</l>
		<l>bore evil fruit-to give place to the Shepherd,</l>
		<l>with both the laws and me, made himself Greek;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>now he has learned that, even though the world</l>
		<l>be ruined by the evil that derives</l>
		<l>from his good act, that evil does not harm him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He whom you see-along the downward arc-</l>
		<l>was William, and the land that mourns his death,</l>
		<l>for living Charles and Frederick, now laments;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>now he has learned how Heaven loves the just</l>
		<l>ruler, and he would show this outwardly</l>
		<l>as well, so radiantly visible.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Who in the erring world below would hold</l>
		<l>that he who was the fifth among the lights</l>
		<l>that formed this circle was the Trojan Ripheus?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Now he has learned much that the world cannot</l>
		<l>discern of God&apos;s own grace, although his sight</l>
		<l>cannot divine, not reach its deepest site.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As if it were a lark at large in air,</l>
		<l>a lark that sings at first and then falls still,</l>
		<l>content with final sweetness that fulfills,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>such seemed to me the image of the seal</l>
		<l>of that Eternal Pleasure through whose will</l>
		<l>each thing becomes the being that it is.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And though the doubt I felt there was as plain</l>
		<l>as any colored surface cloaked by glass,</l>
		<l>it could not wait to voice itself, but with</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the thrust and weight of urgency it forced</l>
		<l>&quot;Can such things be?&quot; out from my lips, at which</l>
		<l>I saw lights flash-a vast festivity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And then the blessed sign-its eye grown still</l>
		<l>more bright-replied, that I might not be kept</l>
		<l>suspended in amazement: &quot;I can see</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that, since you speak of them, you do believe</l>
		<l>these things but cannot see how they may be;</l>
		<l>and thus, though you believe them, they are hidden</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You act as one who apprehends a thing</l>
		<l>by name but cannot see its quiddity</l>
		<l>unless another set it forth to him.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Regnum celorum suffers violence</l>
		<l>from ardent love and living hope, for these</l>
		<l>can be the conquerors of Heaven&apos;s Will;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>yet not as man defeats another man:</l>
		<l>the Will of God is won because It would</l>
		<l>be won and, won, wins through benevolence.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You were amazed to see the angels&apos; realm</l>
		<l>adorned with those who were the first and fifth</l>
		<l>among the living souls that form my eyebrow.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When these souls left their bodies, they were not</l>
		<l>Gentiles-as you believe-but Christians, one</l>
		<l>with firm faith in the Feet that suffered, one</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in Feet that were to suffer. One, from Hell,</l>
		<l>where there is no returning to right will,</l>
		<l>returned to his own bones, as the reward</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>bestowed upon a living hope, the hope</l>
		<l>that gave force to the prayers offered God</l>
		<l>to resurrect him and convert his will.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Returning briefly to the flesh, that soul</l>
		<l>in glory-he of whom I speak-believed</l>
		<l>in Him whose power could help him and, believing,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was kindled to such fire of true love</l>
		<l>that, when he died a second death, he was</l>
		<l>worthy to join in this festivity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The other, through the grace that surges from</l>
		<l>a well so deep that no created one</l>
		<l>has ever thrust his eye to its first source,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>below, set all his love on righteousness,</l>
		<l>so that, through grace on grace, God granted him</l>
		<l>the sight of our redemption in the future;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>thus he, believing that, no longer suffered</l>
		<l>the stench of paganism and rebuked</l>
		<l>those who persisted in that perverse way.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>More than a thousand years before baptizing,</l>
		<l>to baptize him there were the same three women</l>
		<l>you saw along the chariot&apos;s right-hand side.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>How distant, o predestination, is</l>
		<l>your root from those whose vision does not see</l>
		<l>the Primal Cause in Its entirety!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And, mortals, do take care-judge prudently:</l>
		<l>for we, though we see God, do not yet know</l>
		<l>all those whom He has chosen; but within</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the incompleteness of our knowledge is</l>
		<l>a sweetness, for our good is then refined</l>
		<l>in this good, since what God wills, we too will.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, from the image God Himself had drawn,</l>
		<l>what I received was gentle medicine;</l>
		<l>and I saw my shortsightedness plainly.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as a lutanist accompanies-</l>
		<l>expert-with trembling strings, the expert singer,</l>
		<l>by which the song acquires sweeter savor,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, while the Eagle spoke-I can remember-</l>
		<l>I saw the pair of blessed lights together,</l>
		<l>like eyes that wink in concord, move their flames</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>in ways that were at one with what he said.</l>
	</p>
</page>
