<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>By now that blessed mirror was delighting</l>
		<l>in its own inner words; I, tasting mine,</l>
		<l>was tempering the bitter with the sweet.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But she, the lady leading me to God,</l>
		<l>said: &quot;Shift your thoughts: remember-I am close</l>
		<l>to Him who lightens every unjust hurt.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Hearing the loving sound my solace spoke,</l>
		<l>I turned. But here I have to leave untold</l>
		<l>what love I saw within her holy eyes,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>not just because I do not trust my speech,</l>
		<l>but, too, because recall cannot retrieve</l>
		<l>that much, unless Another is its guide.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This only-of that moment-can I tell:</l>
		<l>that even as I gazed at her, my soul</l>
		<l>was free from any other need as long</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as the Eternal Loveliness that shone</l>
		<l>on Beatrice directly, from her eyes,</l>
		<l>contented me with the reflected light.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But, conquering my will with her smile&apos;s splendor,</l>
		<l>she told me: &quot;Turn to him and listen-for</l>
		<l>not only in my eyes is Paradise.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As, here on earth, at times our sentiment,</l>
		<l>if it be passionate enough to take</l>
		<l>the soul entirely, shows in the face,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, in the flaming of the holy fire</l>
		<l>to which I turned, I saw that he desired</l>
		<l>some further words with me. And he began:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;In this fifth resting place, upon the tree</l>
		<l>that grows down from its crown and endlessly</l>
		<l>bears fruit and never loses any leaves,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>are blessed souls that, down below, before</l>
		<l>they came to heaven, were so notable</l>
		<l>that any poem would be enriched by them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore look at the cross, along its horns:</l>
		<l>those whom I name will race as swiftly as,</l>
		<l>within a cloud, its rapid lightnings flash.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, just as soon as Joshua was named,</l>
		<l>I saw a splendor thrust along the cross,</l>
		<l>nor did I note the name before the act.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And at the name of noble Maccabeus,</l>
		<l>I saw another flame wheel round itself,</l>
		<l>and gladness was the whip that spurred that top.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So, too, for Charlemagne and Roland-my</l>
		<l>attentive eye held fast to that pair like</l>
		<l>a falconer who tracks his falcon&apos;s flight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The next to draw my eyes along that cross</l>
		<l>were William and Renouard and, too, Duke Godfrey</l>
		<l>and Robert Guiscard. Then, when he had left me</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and mingled with the other lights, the soul</l>
		<l>who had addressed me showed his artistry,</l>
		<l>singing among the singers in that sphere.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I turned to my right side to see if I</l>
		<l>might see if Beatrice had signified</l>
		<l>by word or gesture what I was to do</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and saw such purity within her eyes,</l>
		<l>such joy, that her appearance now surpassed</l>
		<l>its guise at other times, even the last.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as, by feeling greater joyousness</l>
		<l>in doing good, a man becomes aware</l>
		<l>that day by day his virtue is advancing,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so I became aware that my revolving</l>
		<l>with heaven had increased its arc-by seeing</l>
		<l>that miracle becoming still more brilliant.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And like the rapid change that one can see</l>
		<l>in a pale woman&apos;s face when it has freed</l>
		<l>itself from bearing bashful modesty,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>such change I, turning, saw: the red of Mars</l>
		<l>was gone-and now the temperate sixth star&apos;s</l>
		<l>white heaven welcomed me into itself.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw within that torch of Jupiter</l>
		<l>the sparkling of the love that it contained</l>
		<l>design before my eyes the signs we speak.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as birds that rise from riverbanks,</l>
		<l>as if rejoicing after feeding there,</l>
		<l>will form a round flock or another shape,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, in their lights, the saintly beings sang</l>
		<l>and, in their flight, the figures that they spelled</l>
		<l>were now a D, now I, and now an L.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>First, they moved to the rhythm of their song;</l>
		<l>then, after they had finished forming one</l>
		<l>letter, they halted for a while, in silence.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O godly Pegasea, you who give</l>
		<l>to genius glory and long life, as it,</l>
		<l>through you, gives these to kingdoms and to cities</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>give me your light that I may emphasize</l>
		<l>these signs as I inscribed them in my mind:</l>
		<l>your power-may it appear in these brief lines!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Those blessed spirits took the shape of five</l>
		<l>times seven vowels and consonants, and I</l>
		<l>noted the parts as they were spelled for me.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>DILIGITE IUSTITIAM were the verb</l>
		<l>and noun that first appeared in that depiction;</l>
		<l>QUI IUDICATIS TERRAM followed after.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, having formed the M of the fifth word,</l>
		<l>those spirits kept their order; Jupiter&apos;s</l>
		<l>silver, at that point, seemed embossed with gold.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I saw other lights descending on</l>
		<l>the apex of the M and, settling, singing-</l>
		<l>I think-the Good that draws them to Itself.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then, as innumerable sparks rise up</l>
		<l>when one strikes burning logs (and in those sparks</l>
		<l>fools have a way of reading auguries),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>from that M seemed to surge more than a thousand</l>
		<l>lights; and they climbed, some high, some low, jus</l>
		<l>the Sun that kindles them assigned positions.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>With each light settled quietly in place,</l>
		<l>I saw that the array of fire had shaped</l>
		<l>the image of an eagle&apos;s head and neck.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He who paints there has no one as His guide:</l>
		<l>He guides Himself; in Him we recognize</l>
		<l>the shaping force that flows from nest to nest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The other lights, who were, it seemed, content</l>
		<l>at first to form a lily on the M,</l>
		<l>moving a little, formed the eagle&apos;s frame.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O gentle star, what-and how many-gems</l>
		<l>made plain to me that justice here on earth</l>
		<l>depends upon the heaven you engem!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Therefore I pray the Mind in which begin</l>
		<l>your motion and your force, to watch that place</l>
		<l>which has produced the smoke that dims your rays,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that once again His anger fall upon</l>
		<l>those who would buy and sell within that temple</l>
		<l>whose walls were built by miracles and martyrs.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O hosts of Heaven whom I contemplate,</l>
		<l>for all who, led by bad example, stray</l>
		<l>within the life they live on earth, do pray!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Men once were used to waging war with swords;</l>
		<l>now war means seizing here and there the bread</l>
		<l>the tender Father would deny to none.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But you who only write to then erase,</l>
		<l>remember this: Peter and Paul, who died</l>
		<l>to save the vines you spoil, are still alive.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Well may you say:&quot;My longing is so bent</l>
		<l>on him who chose the solitary life</l>
		<l>and for a dance was dragged to martyrdom-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I do not know the Fisherman or Paul.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
