<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>Unto the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost,</l>
		<l>glory!&quot;-all Paradise began, so that</l>
		<l>the sweetness of the singing held me rapt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What I saw seemed to me to be a smile</l>
		<l>the universe had smiled; my rapture had</l>
		<l>entered by way of hearing and of sight.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O joy! O gladness words can never speak!</l>
		<l>O life perfected by both love and peace!</l>
		<l>O richness so assured, that knows no longing!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Before my eyes, there stood, aflame, the four</l>
		<l>torches, and that which had been first to come</l>
		<l>began to glow with greater radiance,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and what its image then became was like</l>
		<l>what Jupiter&apos;s would be if Mars and he</l>
		<l>were birds and had exchanged their plumages.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>After the Providence that there assigns</l>
		<l>to every office its appointed time</l>
		<l>had, to those holy choirs, on every side,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>commanded silence, I then heard: &quot;If I</l>
		<l>change color, do not be amazed, for as</l>
		<l>I speak, you will see change in all these flames.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>He who on earth usurps my place, my place,</l>
		<l>my place that in the sight of God&apos;s own Son</l>
		<l>is vacant now, has made my burial ground</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>a sewer of blood, a sewer of stench, so that</l>
		<l>the perverse one who fell from Heaven, here</l>
		<l>above, can find contentment there below.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then I saw all the heaven colored by</l>
		<l>the hue that paints the clouds at morning and</l>
		<l>at evening, with the sun confronting them.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And like a woman who, although secure</l>
		<l>in her own honesty, will pale on even</l>
		<l>hearing about another woman&apos;s failing,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just so did Beatrice change in appearance;</l>
		<l>and I believe that such eclipse was in</l>
		<l>the sky when He, the Highest Power, suffered.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Then his words followed with a voice so altered</l>
		<l>from what it was before-even his likeness</l>
		<l>did not display a greater change than that.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The Bride of Christ was never nurtured by</l>
		<l>my blood, and blood of Linus and of Cletus,</l>
		<l>to be employed in gaining greater riches;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>but to acquire this life of joyousness,</l>
		<l>Sixtus and Pius, Urban and Calixtus,</l>
		<l>after much lamentation, shed their blood.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>We did not want one portion of Christ&apos;s people</l>
		<l>to sit at the right side of our successors,</l>
		<l>while, on the left, the other portion sat,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>nor did we want the keys that were consigned</l>
		<l>to me, to serve as an escutcheon on</l>
		<l>a banner that waged war against the baptized;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>nor did we want my form upon a seal</l>
		<l>for trafficking in lying privileges-</l>
		<l>for which I often blush and flash with anger.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From here on high one sees rapacious wolves</l>
		<l>clothed in the cloaks of shepherds. You, the vengeance</l>
		<l>of God, oh, why do you still lie concealed?</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The Gascons and the Cahorsines-they both</l>
		<l>prepare to drink our blood: o good beginning,</l>
		<l>to what a miserable end you fall!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But that high Providence which once preserved,</l>
		<l>with Scipio, the glory of the world</l>
		<l>for Rome, will soon bring help, as I conceive;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and you, my son, who through your mortal weight</l>
		<l>will yet return below, speak plainly there,</l>
		<l>and do not hide that which I do not hide.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As, when the horn of heaven&apos;s Goat abuts</l>
		<l>the sun, our sky flakes frozen vapors downward,</l>
		<l>so did I see that ether there adorned;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for from that sphere, triumphant vapors now</l>
		<l>were flaking up to the Empyrean-</l>
		<l>returning after dwelling here with us.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My sight was following their semblances-</l>
		<l>until the space between us grew so great</l>
		<l>as to deny my eyes all farther reach.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>At this, my lady, seeing me set free</l>
		<l>from gazing upward, told me: &quot;Let your eyes</l>
		<l>look down and see how far you have revolved.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw that, from the time when I looked down</l>
		<l>before, I had traversed all of the arc</l>
		<l>of the first clime, from its midpoint to end,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so that, beyond Cadiz, I saw Ulysses&apos;</l>
		<l>mad course and, to the east, could almost see</l>
		<l>that shoreline where Europa was sweet burden.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I should have seen more of this threshing floor</l>
		<l>but for the motion of the sun beneath</l>
		<l>my feet: it was a sign and more away.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>My mind, enraptured, always longing for</l>
		<l>my lady gallantly, was burning more</l>
		<l>than ever for my eyes&apos; return to her;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and if-by means of human,flesh or portraits-</l>
		<l>nature or art has fashioned lures to draw</l>
		<l>the eye so as to grip the mind, all these</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>would seem nothing if set beside the godly</l>
		<l>beauty that shone upon me when I turned</l>
		<l>to see the smiling face of Beatrice.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The powers that her gaze now granted me</l>
		<l>drew me out of the lovely nest of Leda</l>
		<l>and thrust me into heaven&apos;s swiftest sphere.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Its parts were all so equally alive</l>
		<l>and excellent, that I cannot say which</l>
		<l>place Beatrice selected for my entry.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But she, who saw what my desire was-</l>
		<l>her smile had so much gladness that within</l>
		<l>her face there seemed to be God&apos;s joy-began:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;The nature of the universe, which holds</l>
		<l>the center still and moves all else around it,</l>
		<l>begins here as if from its turning-post.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This heaven has no other where than this:</l>
		<l>the mind of God, in which are kindled both</l>
		<l>the love that turns it and the force it rains.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As in a circle, light and love enclose it,</l>
		<l>as it surrounds the rest-and that enclosing,</l>
		<l>only He who encloses understands.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No other heaven measures this sphere&apos;s motion,</l>
		<l>but it serves as the measure for the rest,</l>
		<l>even as half and fifth determine ten;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and now it can be evident to you</l>
		<l>how time has roots within this vessel and,</l>
		<l>within the other vessels, has its leaves.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O greediness, you who-within your depths-</l>
		<l>cause mortals to sink so, that none is left</l>
		<l>able to lift his eyes above your waves!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The will has a good blossoming in men;</l>
		<l>but then the never-ending downpours turn</l>
		<l>the sound plums into rotten, empty skins.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>For innocence and trust are to be found</l>
		<l>only in little children; then they flee</l>
		<l>even before a full beard cloaks the cheeks.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One, for as long as he still lisps, will fast,</l>
		<l>but when his tongue is free at last, he gorges,</l>
		<l>devouring any food through any month;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and one, while he still lisps, will love and heed</l>
		<l>his mother, but when he acquires speech</l>
		<l>more fully, he will long to see her buried.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Just so, white skin turns black when it is struck</l>
		<l>by direct light-the lovely daughter of</l>
		<l>the one who brings us dawn and leaves us evening.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That you not be amazed at what I say,</l>
		<l>consider this: on earth no king holds sway;</l>
		<l>therefore, the family of humans strays.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But well before a thousand years have passed</l>
		<l>(and January is unwintered by</l>
		<l>day&apos;s hundredth part, which they neglect below),</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>this high sphere shall shine so, that Providence,</l>
		<l>long waited for, will turn the sterns to where</l>
		<l>the prows now are, so that the fleet runs straight</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and then fine fruit shall follow on the flower.&quot;</l>
	</p>
</page>
