<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>So, in the shape of that white Rose, the holy</l>
		<l>legion was shown to me-the host that Christ,</l>
		<l>with His own blood, had taken as His bride.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The other host, which, flying, sees and sings</l>
		<l>the glory of the One who draws its love,</l>
		<l>and that goodness which granted it such glory,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>just like a swarm of bees that, at one moment,</l>
		<l>enters the flowers and, at another, turns</l>
		<l>back to that labor which yields such sweet savor,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>descended into that vast flower graced</l>
		<l>with many petals, then again rose up</l>
		<l>to the eternal dwelling of its love.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Their faces were all living flame; their wings</l>
		<l>were gold; and for the rest, their white was so</l>
		<l>intense, no snow can match the white they showed.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When they climbed down into that flowering Rose,</l>
		<l>from rank to rank, they shared that peace and ardor</l>
		<l>which they had gained, with wings that fanned their sides,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nor did so vast a throng in flight, although</l>
		<l>it interposed between the candid Rose</l>
		<l>and light above, obstruct the sight or splendor,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>because the light of God so penetrates</l>
		<l>the universe according to the worth</l>
		<l>of every part, that no thing can impede it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>This confident and joyous kingdom, thronged</l>
		<l>with people of both new and ancient times,</l>
		<l>turned all its sight and ardor to one mark.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O threefold Light that, in a single star</l>
		<l>sparkling into their eyes, contents them so,</l>
		<l>look down and see our tempest here below!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>If the Barbarians, when they came from</l>
		<l>a region that is covered every day</l>
		<l>by Helice, who wheels with her loved son,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>were, seeing Rome and her vast works, struck dumb</l>
		<l>(when, of all mortal things, the Lateran</l>
		<l>was the most eminent), then what amazement</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>must have filled me when I to the divine</l>
		<l>came from the human, to eternity</l>
		<l>from time, and to a people just and sane</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>from Florence came! And certainly, between</l>
		<l>the wonder and the joy, it must have been</l>
		<l>welcome to me to hear and speak nothing.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as a pilgrim, in the temple he</l>
		<l>had vowed to reach, renews himself-he looks</l>
		<l>and hopes he can describe what it was like-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did I journey through the living light,</l>
		<l>guiding my eyes, from rank to rank, along</l>
		<l>a path now up, now down, now circling round.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>There I saw faces given up to love-</l>
		<l>graced with Another&apos;s light and their own smile-</l>
		<l>and movements graced with every dignity.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>By now my gaze had taken in the whole</l>
		<l>of Paradise-its form in general-</l>
		<l>but without looking hard at any part;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>and I, my will rekindled, turning toward</l>
		<l>my lady, was prepared to ask about</l>
		<l>those matters that inclined my mind to doubt.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Where I expected her, another answered:</l>
		<l>I thought I should see Beatrice, and saw</l>
		<l>an elder dressed like those who are in glory.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>His gracious gladness filled his eyes, suffused</l>
		<l>his cheeks; his manner had that kindliness</l>
		<l>which suits a tender father. &quot;Where is she?&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I asked him instantly. And he replied:</l>
		<l>&quot;That all your longings may be satisfied,</l>
		<l>Beatrice urged me from my place. If you</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>look up and to the circle that is third</l>
		<l>from that rank which is highest, you will see</l>
		<l>her on the throne her merits have assigned her.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I, without answering, then looked on high</l>
		<l>and saw that round her now a crown took shape</l>
		<l>as she reflected the eternal rays.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>No mortal eye, not even one that plunged</l>
		<l>into deep seas, would be so distant from</l>
		<l>that region where the highest thunder forms,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as-there-my sight was far from Beatrice;</l>
		<l>but distance was no hindrance, for her semblance</l>
		<l>reached me-undimmed by any thing between.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;O lady, you in whom my hope gains strength,</l>
		<l>you who, for my salvation, have allowed</l>
		<l>your footsteps to be left in Hell, in all</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the things that I have seen, I recognize</l>
		<l>the grace and benefit that I, depending</l>
		<l>upon your power and goodness, have received.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>You drew me out from slavery to freedom</l>
		<l>by all those paths, by all those means that were</l>
		<l>within your power. Do, in me, preserve</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>your generosity, so that my soul,</l>
		<l>which you have healed, when it is set loose from</l>
		<l>my body, be a soul that you will welcome.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>So did I pray. And she, however far</l>
		<l>away she seemed, smiled, and she looked at me.</l>
		<l>Then she turned back to the eternal fountain.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And he, the holy elder, said: &quot;That you</l>
		<l>may consummate your journey perfectly-</l>
		<l>for this, both prayer and holy love have sent me</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>to help you-let your sight fly round this garden;</l>
		<l>by gazing so, your vision will be made</l>
		<l>more ready to ascend through God&apos;s own ray.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>The Queen of Heaven, for whom I am all</l>
		<l>aflame with love, will grant us every grace:</l>
		<l>I am her faithful Bernard.&quot; Just as one</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>who, from Croatia perhaps, has come</l>
		<l>to visit our Veronica-one whose</l>
		<l>old hunger is not sated, who, as long</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>as it is shown, repeats these words in thought:</l>
		<l>&quot;O my Lord Jesus Christ, true God, was then</l>
		<l>Your image like the image I see now?&quot;-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>such was I as I watched the living love</l>
		<l>of him who, in this world, in contemplation,</l>
		<l>tasted that peace. And he said: &quot;Son of grace,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>you will not come to know this joyous state</l>
		<l>if your eyes only look down at the base;</l>
		<l>but look upon the circles, look at those</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that sit in a position more remote,</l>
		<l>until you see upon her seat the Queen</l>
		<l>to whom this realm is subject and devoted.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I lifted up my eyes; and as, at morning,</l>
		<l>the eastern side of the horizon shows</l>
		<l>more splendor than the side where the sun sets,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, as if climbing with my eyes from valley</l>
		<l>to summit, I saw one part of the farthest</l>
		<l>rank of the Rose more bright than all the rest.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And as, on earth, the point where we await</l>
		<l>the shaft that Phaethon had misguided glows</l>
		<l>brightest, while, to each side, the light shades off</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so did the peaceful oriflamme appear</l>
		<l>brightest at its midpoint, so did its flame,</l>
		<l>on each side, taper off at equal pace.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>I saw, around that midpoint, festive angels-</l>
		<l>more than a thousand-with their wings outspread;</l>
		<l>each was distinct in splendor and in skill.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And there I saw a loveliness that when</l>
		<l>it smiled at the angelic songs and games</l>
		<l>made glad the eyes of all the other saints.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And even if my speech were rich as my</l>
		<l>imagination is, I should not try</l>
		<l>to tell the very least of her delights.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Bernard-when he had seen my eyes intent,</l>
		<l>fixed on the object of his burning fervor-</l>
		<l>turned his own eyes to her with such affection</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that he made mine gaze still more ardently.</l>
	</p>
</page>
