<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<p>
		<l>From rim to center, center out to rim,</l>
		<l>so does the water move in a round vessel,</l>
		<l>as it is struck without, or struck within.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>What I am saying fell most suddenly</l>
		<l>into my mind, as soon as Thomas&apos;s</l>
		<l>glorious living flame fell silent, since</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>between his speech and that of Beatrice,</l>
		<l>a similarity was born. And she,</l>
		<l>when he was done, was pleased to start with this:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>&quot;He does not tell you of it-not with speech</l>
		<l>nor in his thoughts as yet-but this man needs</l>
		<l>to reach the root of still another truth.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Do tell him if that light with which your soul</l>
		<l>blossoms will stay with you eternally</l>
		<l>even as it is now; and if it stays,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>do tell him how, when you are once again</l>
		<l>made visible, it will be possible</l>
		<l>for you to see such light and not be harmed.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As dancers in a ring, when drawn and driven</l>
		<l>by greater gladness, lift at times their voices</l>
		<l>and dance their dance with more exuberance,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, when they heard that prompt, devout request,</l>
		<l>the blessed circles showed new joyousness</l>
		<l>in wheeling dance and in amazing song.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Whoever weeps because on earth we die</l>
		<l>that we may live on high, has never seen</l>
		<l>eternal showers that bring refreshment there.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>That One and Two and Three who ever lives</l>
		<l>and ever reigns in Three and Two and One,</l>
		<l>not circumscribed and circumscribing all,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>was sung three times by each and all those souls</l>
		<l>with such a melody that it would be</l>
		<l>appropriate reward for every merit.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And I could hear within the smaller circle&apos;s</l>
		<l>divinest light a modest voice (perhaps</l>
		<l>much like the angel&apos;s voice in speech to Mary)</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>reply: &quot;As long as the festivity</l>
		<l>of Paradise shall be, so long shall our</l>
		<l>love radiate around us such a garment.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Its brightness takes its measure from our ardor,</l>
		<l>our ardor from our vision, which is measured</l>
		<l>by what grace each receives beyond his merit.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>When, glorified and sanctified, the flesh</l>
		<l>is once again our dress, our persons shall,</l>
		<l>in being all complete, please all the more;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>therefore, whatever light gratuitous</l>
		<l>the Highest Good gives us will be enhanced-</l>
		<l>the light that will allow us to see Him;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>that light will cause our vision to increase,</l>
		<l>the ardor vision kindles to increase,</l>
		<l>the brightness born of ardor to increase.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Yet even as a coal engenders flame,</l>
		<l>but with intenser glow outshines it, so</l>
		<l>that in that flame the coal persists, it shows,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so will the brightness that envelops us</l>
		<l>be then surpassed in visibility</l>
		<l>by reborn flesh, which earth now covers up.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Nor will we tire when faced with such bright light</l>
		<l>for then the body&apos;s organs will have force</l>
		<l>enough for all in which we can delight.&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>One and the other choir seemed to me</l>
		<l>so quick and keen to say &quot;Amen&quot; that they</l>
		<l>showed clearly how they longed for their dead bodies-</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>not only for themselves, perhaps, but for</l>
		<l>their mothers, fathers, and for others dear</l>
		<l>to them before they were eternal flames.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And-look!-beyond the light already there,</l>
		<l>an added luster rose around those rings,</l>
		<l>even as a horizon brightening.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And even as, at the approach of evening,</l>
		<l>new lights begin to show along the sky,</l>
		<l>so that the sight seems and does not seem real,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>it seemed to me that I began to see</l>
		<l>new spirits there, forming a ring beyond</l>
		<l>the choirs with their two circumferences.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>O the true sparkling of the Holy Ghost-</l>
		<l>how rapid and how radiant before</l>
		<l>my eyes that, overcome, could not sustain it!</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But, smiling, Beatrice then showed to me</l>
		<l>such loveliness-it must be left among</l>
		<l>the visions that take flight from memory.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>From this my eyes regained the strength to look</l>
		<l>above again; I saw myself translated</l>
		<l>to higher blessedness, alone with my</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>lady; and I was sure that I had risen</l>
		<l>because the smiling star was red as fire-</l>
		<l>beyond the customary red of Mars.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>With all my heart and in that language which</l>
		<l>is one for all, for this new grace I gave</l>
		<l>to God my holocaust, appropriate.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Though in my breast that burning sacrifice</l>
		<l>was not completed yet, I was aware</l>
		<l>that it had been accepted and auspicious;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>for splendors, in two rays, appeared to me,</l>
		<l>so radiant and fiery that I said:</l>
		<l>&quot;O Helios, you who adorn them thus!&quot;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>As, graced with lesser and with larger lights</l>
		<l>between the poles of the world, the Galaxy</l>
		<l>gleams so that even sages are perplexed;</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, constellated in the depth of Mars,</l>
		<l>those rays described the venerable sign</l>
		<l>a circle&apos;s quadrants form where they are joined.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And here my memory defeats my wit:</l>
		<l>Christ&apos;s flaming from that cross was such that I</l>
		<l>can find no fit similitude for it.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But he who takes his cross and follows Christ</l>
		<l>will pardon me again for my omission-</l>
		<l>my seeing Christ flash forth undid my force.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Lights moved along that cross from horn to horn</l>
		<l>and from the summit to the base, and as</l>
		<l>they met and passed, they sparkled, radiant:</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, straight and slant and quick and slow, one see</l>
		<l>on earth the particles of bodies, long</l>
		<l>and short, in shifting shapes, that move along</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>the ray of light that sometimes streaks across</l>
		<l>the shade that men devise with skill and art</l>
		<l>to serve as their defense against the sun.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>And just as harp and viol, whose many chords</l>
		<l>are tempered, taut, produce sweet harmony</l>
		<l>although each single note is not distinct,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>so, from the lights that then appeared to me,</l>
		<l>out from that cross there spread a melody</l>
		<l>that held me rapt, although I could not tell</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>what hymn it was. I knew it sang high praise,</l>
		<l>since I heard &quot;Rise&quot; and &quot;Conquer,&quot; but I was</l>
		<l>as one who hears but cannot seize the sense.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>Yet I was so enchanted by the sound</l>
		<l>that until then no thing had ever bound</l>
		<l>me with such gentle bonds. My words may seem</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>presumptuous, as though I dared to deem</l>
		<l>a lesser thing the lovely eyes that bring</l>
		<l>to my desire, as it gazes, peace.</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>But he who notes that, in ascent, her eyes-</l>
		<l>all beauty&apos;s living seals-gain force, and notes</l>
		<l>that I had not yet turned to them in Mars,</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>can then excuse me-just as I accuse</l>
		<l>myself, thus to excuse myself-and see</l>
		<l>that I speak truly: here her holy beauty</l>
	</p>
	<p>
		<l>is not denied-ascent makes it more perfect.</l>
	</p>
</page>
